<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Liggat.org]]></title>
  <link href="http://liggat.org/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://liggat.org/"/>
  <updated>2015-01-30T14:42:45-08:00</updated>
  <id>http://liggat.org/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Dave Liggat]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Personal CVs With Curriculum-Vitml]]></title>
    <link href="http://liggat.org/2015/01/30/personal-cvs-with-curriculum-vitml/"/>
    <updated>2015-01-30T12:16:04-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://liggat.org/2015/01/30/personal-cvs-with-curriculum-vitml</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Word-processing documents are, charitably, a <em>less-than-ideal</em> way to represent textual content. As a recipient, they necessitate the presence of current and often expensive application software (i.e. Microsoft Office) &ndash; at least if you want to view the document with its original visual fidelity intact.<!--more--> As a creator, they are even worse: one ends up pouring effort into a <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Binary_large_object">binary-blob</a><sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" rel="footnote">1</a></sup> artifact that is, practically-speaking, untraceable and unversionable. Even if all of these objections were addressed, a substantial existential quandary remains: Word processing workflows were built for a paper centric world. We no longer live in such a world.</p>

<p>And yet, the obvious candidate to replace these has existed for some time: the web!</p>

<p>For all of my philosophical objections to <code>.docx</code> and its various derivatives and predecessors and workflows, there&rsquo;s only a single such document in my life that I begrudgingly find myself re-opening to replenish its life and relevance: my resume. I set out to build a better solution.</p>

<h3>Requirements</h3>

<p>A better replacement for a word-processor-based resume requires the following:</p>

<ul>
<li>Built with web technologies (HTML, CSS)</li>
<li>Easy to deploy and update at a URL endpoint</li>
<li>Version controlled content with <code>git</code></li>
<li>Responsive layout for acceptable mobile-sized viewing</li>
<li>Reasonable print-to-PDF output for when that&rsquo;s inevitably requested</li>
</ul>


<h3>Curriculum-Vitml</h3>

<p>I&rsquo;ve written a tool to address this need called <a href="https://github.com/dliggat/curriculum-vitml">curriculum-vitml</a><sup id="fnref:2"><a href="#fn:2" rel="footnote">2</a></sup>. It&rsquo;s a Ruby-<a href="https://middlemanapp.com/">Middleman</a> static site generator which relies on <a href="http://foundation.zurb.com">Foundation</a> for responsiveness, <a href="http://sass-lang.com/">Sass/SCSS</a> for styling and <a href="http://slim-lang.com/">Slim</a> partials and templates for the various resume elements. Its final output is a static HTML document with a single accompanying stylesheet, but the middleman server and SCSS/Slim components provide an easy update cycle. And of course the whole thing is inherently versionable<sup id="fnref:3"><a href="#fn:3" rel="footnote">3</a></sup>.</p>

<h3>Entry</h3>

<p>A single <a href="https://github.com/dliggat/curriculum-vitml/blob/master/source/content/roles/_01_role.html.slim">CV entry</a> looks like this:</p>

<figure class='code'><figcaption><span>_01_role.html.slim: A Slim partial representing a CV-entry </span></figcaption>
<div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
<span class='line-number'>3</span>
<span class='line-number'>4</span>
<span class='line-number'>5</span>
<span class='line-number'>6</span>
<span class='line-number'>7</span>
<span class='line-number'>8</span>
<span class='line-number'>9</span>
<span class='line-number'>10</span>
<span class='line-number'>11</span>
<span class='line-number'>12</span>
<span class='line-number'>13</span>
<span class='line-number'>14</span>
<span class='line-number'>15</span>
<span class='line-number'>16</span>
<span class='line-number'>17</span>
<span class='line-number'>18</span>
<span class='line-number'>19</span>
<span class='line-number'>20</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class='rb'><span class='line'><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">cv</span><span class="o">-</span><span class="n">entry</span>
</span><span class='line'>  <span class="o">.</span><span class="n">coordinates</span>
</span><span class='line'>    <span class="o">.</span><span class="n">duration</span>
</span><span class='line'>      <span class="n">h4</span> <span class="no">Apr</span><span class="o">-</span><span class="mi">2012</span> <span class="err">–</span> <span class="n">present</span>
</span><span class='line'>    <span class="n">h3</span> <span class="no">Chief</span> <span class="no">Awesome</span> <span class="no">Officer</span>
</span><span class='line'>    <span class="n">h4</span>
</span><span class='line'>      <span class="n">span</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">company</span> <span class="no">Initech</span>
</span><span class='line'>      <span class="n">span</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">location</span> <span class="no">Vancouver</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="no">BC</span>
</span><span class='line'>  <span class="o">.</span><span class="n">synopsis</span>
</span><span class='line'>    <span class="nb">p</span>
</span><span class='line'>      <span class="o">|</span>
</span><span class='line'>        <span class="no">Here</span> <span class="n">I</span> <span class="n">did</span> <span class="n">awesome</span> <span class="n">things</span><span class="o">.</span>
</span><span class='line'>  <span class="o">.</span><span class="n">additional</span>
</span><span class='line'>    <span class="n">h4</span> <span class="no">Highlights</span>
</span><span class='line'>    <span class="n">ul</span>
</span><span class='line'>      <span class="n">li</span> <span class="no">Crafted</span> <span class="n">artisanal</span> <span class="n">code</span> <span class="n">with</span> <span class="n">a</span> <span class="n">focus</span> <span class="n">on</span> <span class="n">awesomeness</span>
</span><span class='line'>      <span class="n">li</span> <span class="no">Ensured</span> <span class="n">I</span> <span class="n">is</span> <span class="ow">not</span> <span class="k">in</span> <span class="no">TEAM</span>
</span><span class='line'>      <span class="n">li</span> <span class="no">Leveraged</span> <span class="n">core</span> <span class="n">competencies</span> <span class="n">with</span> <span class="n">a</span> <span class="n">focus</span> <span class="n">on</span> <span class="n">profitability</span>
</span><span class='line'>    <span class="n">h4</span> <span class="no">Technologies</span>
</span><span class='line'>    <span class="nb">p</span> <span class="no">Ruby</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="no">JavaScript</span>
</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p>Each job or &lsquo;role&rsquo; is represented by one of these Slim partials in the repository. I thought about using JSON or YAML for the data storage, but Slim is so readable and easy to update that I decided it wasn&rsquo;t even worth the translation. Additionally – keeping things in web markup allows for custom sections of data – an education section with a grade <code>&lt;table&gt;</code> for instance.</p>

<h3>Output</h3>

<p>The final web output looks quite notionally like a traditional resume at desktop size:</p>

<p><img class="center" src="http://liggat.org/images/2015/resume-desktop.png" width="500" title="'Resume Desktop'" ></p>

<p>It&rsquo;s responsive on mobile:</p>

<p><img class="center" src="http://liggat.org/images/2015/resume-mobile.png" width="500" title="'Resume Mobile'" ></p>

<p>And its print media queries allow for reasonable <a href="https://github.com/dliggat/curriculum-vitml/blob/master/sample/curriculum-vitml.pdf?raw=true">PDF output</a> (this was generated from Chrome using OS X&rsquo;s &lsquo;print to PDF&rsquo;).</p>

<p>Of course, this is all very specific to resume-needs in general, and my resume-needs in particular. But it&rsquo;s the only &lsquo;document&rsquo; in my life with a reasonable chance of still being requested in &lsquo;file&rsquo; format instead of &lsquo;URL&rsquo; format. This bridges that gap. Feel free to use it as a starting point for your own.</p>
<div class="footnotes">
<hr/>
<ol>
<li id="fn:1">
<p>That may no longer <em>technically</em> be true with the onset of <code>.docx</code> versus <code>.doc</code> but it&rsquo;s true for all practical purposes. No one&rsquo;s putting their Word docs in <code>git repositories</code>, and if they are, they aren&rsquo;t happy about it.<a href="#fnref:1" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
<li id="fn:2">
<p>A lazy portmanteau of <em>curriulum-vitae</em> and <em>HTML</em>.<a href="#fnref:2" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
<li id="fn:3">
<p>My own personal resume is now a private fork of this repo.<a href="#fnref:3" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
</ol>
</div>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[HTTPS: Emulate the Newspaper]]></title>
    <link href="http://liggat.org/2015/01/07/https-emulate-the-newspaper/"/>
    <updated>2015-01-07T20:47:11-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://liggat.org/2015/01/07/https-emulate-the-newspaper</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>There&rsquo;s a pretty substantial effort around the Internet to get <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Transport_Layer_Security">SSL/TLS</a> (i.e. <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/HTTP_Secure">HTTPS</a> as far as the web is concerned) deployed as widely as possible in favour of unencrypted-<a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hypertext_Transfer_Protocol">HTTP</a>. I won&rsquo;t enumerate the reasons here, though I will direct the reader to <a href="https://www.tbray.org/ongoing/misc/Tim">Tim Bray</a>&rsquo;s excellent <a href="https://www.tbray.org/ongoing/When/201x/2012/12/02/HTTPS">Private by Default</a> post on the topic.<!--more--></p>

<p>This issue was further covered for a couple of weeks by the folks on the <a href="http://atp.fm">ATP podcast</a>; in particular they <a href="http://atp.fm/episodes/97">discussed</a> the issue of whether HTTPS is worth bothering with on mostly-or-entirely static endpoints such as blogs or news sites. They mentioned a number of excellent points, including the use of HTTPS as a mechanism to defeat, or at least hinder, the repellent practice of a <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Man-in-the-middle_attack">man-in-the-middle</a> injecting <a href="https://www.eff.org/deeplinks/2014/11/verizon-x-uidh">ad tracking codes</a> into the unencrypted-HTTP payloads, or otherwise monkeying with the payload in any way en-route to its client.</p>

<p>Between these and other worthwhile discussions of the issue, I don&rsquo;t have a great deal to add, especially since <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Information_security">infosec</a> is a discipline for which I have nothing but personal interest to purvey as a credential. However, an analogy did recently occur to me, and though it&rsquo;s clearly <a href="#flawed">flawed</a>, as are all analogies, it just might be a helpful way to think about the issue.</p>

<p>Imagine a mailbox, attached to a house. The occupant is an enthusiastic reader; and subscribes to a substantial bundle of newspapers. Daily, the occupant retrieves the newspapers, brings them into the house, and behind closed doors engages in an leisurely perusal of their contents.</p>

<p>Any observer of this ritual – from the delivering postal-worker to the binoculared-neighbour on the lookout for prurient gossip – is only able to gain <em>limited</em> insight into the interests of the occupant. Certainly, the newspapers themselves leak information about the occupant – conclusions are immediately drawn upon witnessing the various publication titles, and the personal interests and perhaps even personality characteristics that their <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Union_%28set_theory%29">union</a> implies.</p>

<p>But that&rsquo;s as far as it goes. <em>Crucially</em> – no observer is privy to the set of <em>actual articles</em> that pique the occupant&rsquo;s interest, and the time spent reading each one. It is between the occupant and the bundle itself how high-brow, or how low-brow those interests are, how much time is spent on world affairs versus comics and sports, whether any lingering on the seedier classifieds goes on, and so on.</p>

<p>It&rsquo;s undoubtedly clear where this is going: hosts on the web are newspapers, and URLs are articles. Host visitation may well be visible to the observer; URL visitation should not be. It is entirely reasonable to demand that the web should seek to emulate, at a minimum, a comparable privacy affordance to that which naturally exists in the newspaper scenario. Asterisks and fine-print abound, but HTTPS brings this newspaper-esque privacy to the web.</p>

<p>Given the extent to which life – personal, civic, political and otherwise – has moved, and continues to move online, private-by-default is a crucial and long-overdue evolutionary step for the Internet. Whether any given site is largely &lsquo;static&rsquo; or not – it&rsquo;s a distinction that&rsquo;s ultimately irrelevant.</p>

<h3><a name="flawed" class="target">Addendum I</a></h3>


<p><em>Of course the analogy breaks comprehensively upon casual analysis: newspapers don&rsquo;t have certificate authorities and the attendant hassles; it&rsquo;s hard to fail at privately reading newspapers but easy to fail at deploying and consuming TLS; things like <a href="http://heartbleed.com/">Heartbleed</a> happen, etc. It&rsquo;s also the case that without particular care taken, the <a href="http://security.stackexchange.com/questions/73309/do-payload-sizes-reveal-urls-when-https-is-deployed-on-news-blogs-etc">unique payload</a> sizes for the set of site URLs will be able to imply URL visitation anyhow. And perhaps most obviously: the newspaper itself doesn&rsquo;t receive requests for which individual articles you&rsquo;d like you read.</em></p>

<h3>Addendum II</h3>

<p><em>I&rsquo;m very vulnerable to charges of hypocrisy, or at least neglect – this very site has no HTTPS endpoint. That&rsquo;ll be rectified this year &ndash; probably as a test case for when the <a href="https://letsencrypt.org/">Let&rsquo;s Encrypt</a> Certificate Authority launches.</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[A Full AWS Rails Stack Provision and Deployment With the Rubber Gem]]></title>
    <link href="http://liggat.org/2014/12/13/a-full-AWS-rails-stack-provision-and-deployment-with-the-rubber-gem/"/>
    <updated>2014-12-13T16:00:21-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://liggat.org/2014/12/13/a-full-AWS-rails-stack-provision-and-deployment-with-the-rubber-gem</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>It&rsquo;d been some time since I&rsquo;d set up a full <a href="http://rubyonrails.org/">Rails</a> stack and deployment process on <a href="http://aws.amazon.com/">Amazon Web Services</a>. I thought it would be worth trying out <a href="https://github.com/rubber/rubber">rubber</a> from scratch to provision a full <strong>{Nginx, Passenger, PostgreSQL}</strong> stack on a single AWS host, with as much automation as possible, but without prematurely resorting to the cognitive-overhead of <a href="http://docs.aws.amazon.com/opsworks/latest/userguide/workingcookbook-chef11.html">Chef/OpsWorks</a>. This is my attempt to document the process, as I ran into a few roadblocks along the way.</p>

<!--more-->


<p>The <a href="http://railscasts.com/episodes/347-rubber-and-amazon-ec2">RailsCast</a> on <code>rubber</code> is a great place to start, as it gives a good overview/refresher on some of the primitive pieces such as setting up EC2 key-pairs and so on. This post is written under the assumption it has been watched and understood, but I&rsquo;ll be targeting the <code>complete_passenger_nginx_postgresql</code> template rather than <code>complete_passenger_postgresql</code>, which the episode uses. The various other <code>rubber</code> templates are all available <a href="https://github.com/rubber/rubber/tree/master/templates">in its repo</a>.</p>

<h2>Creating And Deploying &lsquo;bloggy&rsquo;</h2>

<p>I started out with a super basic Rails app, unimaginatively named <code>bloggy</code>. The <code>git</code> repository is available <a href="https://github.com/dliggat/bloggy">here</a>; each commit in the <a href="https://github.com/dliggat/bloggy/commits/master">history</a> corresponds to a step along the way. It has a root route which renders a page with the current time and hostname, and a single <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Representational_state_transfer">REST</a>-ful resource: <code>/posts</code>.</p>

<h3>(1) Set Up the Basic App</h3>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://github.com/dliggat/bloggy/commit/e52a13e96549230cb8f0f1ad7e81381ae2434013">Create</a> the app: <code>rails new bloggy -d postgresql</code></li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/dliggat/bloggy/commit/dcddbc02350812ce9f94842d09078b93f2257cb7">Scaffold</a> a model: <code>bundle exec rails g scaffold post title:string body:text</code></li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/dliggat/bloggy/commit/f59b8f311aab8cd24c8213f64b4e1441fdf03243">Create</a> database and migrate: <code>bundle exec rake db:create db:migrate</code></li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/dliggat/bloggy/commit/521fac60a7ab97e9c7a1fb2c6f54b514dbaa2a44">Add</a> a root route and a basic root page</li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/dliggat/bloggy/commit/5999bed32663165875726437cf04f3a0a23ff6ea">Add</a> <code>dotenv</code> for environment variable management in production</li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/dliggat/bloggy/compare/5999bed...63b4a27">Add</a> the following gems:

<ul>
<li><code>capistrano</code>: for deployment automation</li>
<li><code>rubber</code>: for EC2 provisioning</li>
<li><code>passenger</code>: for the Rails app server</li>
<li><code>therubyracer</code>: for asset precompilation in production</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>


<h3>(2) Configure Rubber</h3>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://github.com/dliggat/bloggy/commit/de11b73ede158f3b6a439ea68d8ebdc797850e74">Vulcanize</a> the desired stack: <code>vulcanize complete_passenger_nginx_postgresql</code></li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/dliggat/bloggy/compare/de11b73...d2536ec">Set</a> appropriate versions of <code>ruby</code> (for me: <code>2.1.2</code>), <code>ruby-build</code> and <code>passenger</code><sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" rel="footnote">1</a></sup>.</li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/dliggat/bloggy/commit/d046ae4314ba669f465c18c9be0606de3398e22f">Set</a> basic properties of the app; <code>app_name</code> and so on.</li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/dliggat/bloggy/commit/d71b25d31986cd56543eeaae2b36b091f08de4f6">Pick</a> an EC2 image size and type compliant with your region. I&rsquo;m using Ubuntu 14.04 LTS in <code>us-west-2</code> (Oregon)<sup id="fnref:2"><a href="#fn:2" rel="footnote">2</a></sup>.</li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/dliggat/bloggy/commit/b1f0d94aba4da1e6eabdfb01290c3b06ead8384f">Enable</a> secure AWS credential storage for <code>rubber</code> using <code>~/.ec2/rubber-secret.yml</code>. You <strong>do not</strong> want to have these credentials in a <code>git</code> repository, irrespective of whether your repository is private or public (like <a href="https://github.com/dliggat/bloggy">mine</a>). My EC2 keys and credential file all live in <code>~/.ec2</code>:</li>
</ul>


<p><img class="center" src="http://liggat.org/images/2014/ec2.png" width="700" title="'EC2'" ></p>

<h3>(3) Instantiate the EC2 Instance</h3>

<p>At this point, we&rsquo;re ready to fire up the EC2 instance:</p>

<ul>
<li><code>bundle exec cap rubber:create</code></li>
<li>Name the single instance <code>production</code> and assign it every role within the app: <code>web,app,db:primary=true</code><sup id="fnref:3"><a href="#fn:3" rel="footnote">3</a></sup>.</li>
<li>Enter your local admin password when prompted – so <code>rubber</code> can modify your <code>/etc/hosts</code> file.</li>
<li>Log into the AWS console => EC2, and ensure the image has been started. Grab the public DNS name of the instance<sup id="fnref:4"><a href="#fn:4" rel="footnote">4</a></sup>.</li>
</ul>


<p>If all has gone well, and the keys were setup correctly ahead of time, it should be possible to <code>ssh</code> to the newly launched instance:</p>

<figure class='code'><figcaption><span>SSH to the instance </span></figcaption>
<div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class='sh'><span class='line'>ssh -v -i ~/.ec2/gsg-keypair ubuntu@ec2-54-69-180-182.us-west-2.compute.amazonaws.com
</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<h3>(4) Provision the Environment</h3>

<p>With the instance running, we can now instruct <code>rubber</code> to install the relevant packages that are necessary to build the environment. Locally, run <code>bundle exec cap rubber:bootstrap</code>. This can take a while: it installs Linux updates, configures Nginx, builds and installs <code>ruby</code>, etc. This is the core of the annoying, manual, error-prone work that we seek to eliminate with <code>rubber</code>.</p>

<p>Once that completes, the instance is mostly ready to go. After <code>ssh</code>-ing to the instance we can verify that the correct version of <code>ruby</code> is installed, etc:</p>

<pre><code># ruby --version
ruby 2.1.2p95 (2014-05-08 revision 45877) [x86_64-linux]
</code></pre>

<h3>(5) Initial Deployment</h3>

<p>With the instance ready, we can now use <code>capistrano</code> to deploy. This is where I first ran into issues. After attempting to deploy using <code>bundle exec cap deploy:cold</code>, I received the <code>rubber</code> error output:</p>

<pre><code>** [out :: production.bloggy.com] [ALERT] 347/141816 (2034) :
** [out :: production.bloggy.com] Starting proxy passenger_proxy: cannot bind socket
** [out :: production.bloggy.com]
** [out :: production.bloggy.com]
** [out :: production.bloggy.com]
** [out :: production.bloggy.com] [
** [out :: production.bloggy.com]
** [out :: production.bloggy.com] fail
** [out :: production.bloggy.com]
</code></pre>

<p>It turns out we need to delete the default Nginx configuration, which is conflicting with the port (obviously <code>80</code>) we&rsquo;re attempting to use. After <code>ssh</code>-ing to the instance:</p>

<ul>
<li>Delete the default configuration file: <code>sudo rm /etc/nginx/sites-enabled/default</code></li>
<li>Restart Nginx: <code>sudo service nginx restart</code></li>
</ul>


<p>Back again locally, attempt to deploy once more: <code>bundle exec cap deploy:cold</code>. It should succeed this time around without the error message we encountered previously.</p>

<h3>(6) Accessing the App</h3>

<p>With the instance provisioned, we are close to success. However, at this point I got an error page at <a href="http://ec2-54-69-180-182.us-west-2.compute.amazonaws.com">http://ec2-54-69-180-182.us-west-2.compute.amazonaws.com</a> in the browser. <code>curl</code> gives some insight as to what&rsquo;s going on:</p>

<pre><code>$ curl -i http://ec2-54-69-180-182.us-west-2.compute.amazonaws.com
HTTP/1.1 502 Bad Gateway
Server: nginx/1.6.2
Date: Sun, 14 Dec 2014 22:29:03 GMT
Content-Type: text/html
Content-Length: 1477
Connection: keep-alive
</code></pre>

<p>To proceed, we need to take a look at the Nginx logs. After <code>ssh</code>-ing again to our instance, we can <code>tail -f /var/log/nginx/error.log</code> and notice that:</p>

<pre><code>App 2213 stderr: [ 2014-12-14 14:29:03.3709 2275/0x007f5d4ea08798(Worker 1) utils.rb:84 ]: *** Exception RuntimeError in Rack application object (Missing `secret_key_base` for 'production' environment, set this value in `config/secrets.yml`) (process 2275, thread 0x007f5d4ea08798(Worker 1)):
App 2213 stderr:  from /mnt/bloggy-production/shared/bundle/ruby/2.1.0/gems/railties-4.1.7/lib/rails/application.rb:462:in `validate_secret_key_config!'
</code></pre>

<p>We need to create an <code>.env</code> file in the Rails app root directory that the <code>dotenv-deployment</code> gem will use to set the missing <code>SECRET_KEY_BASE</code> cryptographic environment variable that is referenced in the app&rsquo;s <code>config/secrets.yml</code>. Locally, create a <code>.env</code> file and copy it to the server:</p>

<figure class='code'><figcaption><span>Copying an .env file to the server </span></figcaption>
<div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
<span class='line-number'>3</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class='sh'><span class='line'><span class="nb">echo</span> <span class="s2">&quot;SECRET_KEY_BASE=`bundle exec rake secret`&quot;</span> &gt; .env
</span><span class='line'>scp -v -i ~/.ec2/gsg-keypair .env ubuntu@ec2-54-69-180-182.us-west-2.compute.amazonaws.com:/home/ubuntu
</span><span class='line'>rm .env
</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p>Back on the server, <code>sudo mv /home/ubuntu/.env /mnt/bloggy-production/shared/</code> to copy the file to the appropriate place. The final <a href="https://github.com/dliggat/bloggy/commit/23bac39176accbee69ba3465d8aad92e822f2972">repo commit</a> ensures that <code>capistrano</code> will symlink this from the <code>release</code> directory into the <code>shared</code> directory on deployment.</p>

<p>One final deployment should do the trick to get this into the Rails app on production: <code>bundle exec cap deploy</code>. Sure enough:</p>

<pre><code>ubuntu@production:~$ cd /mnt/bloggy-production/current/
ubuntu@production:/mnt/bloggy-production/current$ ls -la .env
lrwxrwxrwx 1 root root 34 Dec 14 14:49 .env -&gt; /mnt/bloggy-production/shared/.env
</code></pre>

<p>With that in place, we can visit the URL once more:</p>

<p><img class="center" src="http://liggat.org/images/2014/app.png" width="700" title="'App on EC2'" ></p>

<p>And there we have it! The full stack <strong>{Nginx, Passenger, PostgreSQL}</strong> app is now live on the EC2 instance. This process falls slightly short of the ideal of <em>one-click instance provisioning</em>, but it&rsquo;s pretty close<sup id="fnref:5"><a href="#fn:5" rel="footnote">5</a></sup>. Going through this additional work seems preferable to me versus <a href="https://www.heroku.com/">Heroku</a> or <a href="http://aws.amazon.com/elasticbeanstalk/">Elastic Beanstalk</a> &ndash; both of which have their place<sup id="fnref:6"><a href="#fn:6" rel="footnote">6</a></sup> to be sure, but ultimately abstract away rather more of these details than I would prefer.</p>

<p>With the basic app deployed with a production-grade full stack using <code>rubber</code> &ndash; we can be sure we have a clear, repeatable, configurable path for future vertical and/or horizontal scaling if and when the need should arise.</p>

<h3>(7) Teardown</h3>

<p>Finally, the deployed instance can be dismantled via <code>bundle exec cap rubber:destroy_all</code> when it&rsquo;s no longer needed, as of course EC2 bills by the hour.</p>

<h3>Addendum: Asset Compilation</h3>

<p>Thanks to the <code>therubyracer</code> gem added earlier, we can observe that the application&rsquo;s JavaScript has indeed undergone precompilation in deployment.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="http://liggat.org/images/2014/assets.png" width="700" title="'Precompilation'" ></p>
<div class="footnotes">
<hr/>
<ol>
<li id="fn:1">
<p>There&rsquo;s a fair bit of documentation staleness around these values, so unless you&rsquo;re reading this around December 2014, the world has likely moved onto something newer, and you may get errors as a result. Look for values that will be mutually compliant <em>today</em>, whenever that might be.<a href="#fnref:1" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
<li id="fn:2">
<p>You can find the various options in the dropdown on the right side of <a href="http://alestic.com">alestic.com</a>.<a href="#fnref:2" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
<li id="fn:3">
<p>As the app matures, these roles would tend to migrate to separate instances, and possibly leverage other AWS services such as <a href="http://aws.amazon.com/rds/">RDS</a>, but for now one instance is adequate for all the roles.<a href="#fnref:3" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
<li id="fn:4">
<p><code>rubber</code> monkeys with your <code>/etc/hosts</code> file to alias this locally, but I tend to ignore that and just grab it directly from the EC2 console.<a href="#fnref:4" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
<li id="fn:5">
<p>This could likely be slightly streamlined with some <code>rubber</code> pull requests, which I hope to create and contribute in the near future.<a href="#fnref:5" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
<li id="fn:6">
<p>Heroku remains the undisputed master of the <em>get this thing deployed ASAP</em> market in my book<a href="#fnref:6" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
</ol>
</div>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Wealthsimple Review]]></title>
    <link href="http://liggat.org/2014/11/27/wealthsimple-review/"/>
    <updated>2014-11-27T11:12:15-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://liggat.org/2014/11/27/wealthsimple-review</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I&rsquo;ve been watching the ascent of automated index investing services (e.g. <a href="https://www.wealthfront.com">Wealthfront</a>) in the United States with keen interest, and I have been looking forward to the arrival of similar services in Canada. The value proposition is pretty straightfoward: you invest in securities (i.e. <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Exchange-traded_fund">ETFs</a>) in accordance with your savings goals, time horizon, risk tolerance, etc – and they take care of the messy details such as trading, rebalancing, and even tax-loss harvesting.<!--more--> Because computers are involved, and automating this process, it can be done very cheaply and efficiently, but more importantly: <em>sans</em> any human emotion – so often the destroyer of portfolio returns.</p>

<p>So long as you are convinced by the soundness<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" rel="footnote">1</a></sup> of <a href="http://canadiancouchpotato.com/couch-potato-faq/">index investing</a> as a strategy – and I invite the skeptic to examine the boatloads of <a href="https://pressroom.vanguard.com/content/nonindexed/Updated_The_Case_for_Index_Fund_Investing_4.9.2014.pdf">evidence</a> to that effect – there is a lot to like about this concept. When I heard about <a href="https://www.wealthsimple.com">Wealthsimple</a>&rsquo;s launch in Canada, I immediately signed up to try it out.</p>

<p><em>As with anything I write on the topic of finance or investing – this is all just a layperson&rsquo;s opinion – not the provision of advice. Do your own research, or consult with a trusted, qualified advisor.</em></p>

<h2>First Impressions</h2>

<p>I&rsquo;ve long been a critic of bad software, and in particular <a href="http://liggat.org/2014/04/22/a-call-for-modern-banking/">bad software</a> in financial services. It amazes me that these organizations, with such vast market capitalizations and elephantine top and bottom lines, still mostly have web applications straight out of 2004 – <em>putting it charitably</em>.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="http://liggat.org/images/2014/wealthsimple.png" width="700" title="'Wealthsimple'" ></p>

<p>Wealthsimple is, refreshingly, a company that appears to <em>get it</em> in this regard. Right on the landing page are some positive indicators: an <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Extended_Validation_Certificate">EV TLS</a> certificate, responsive design, good typography. This is all <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Necessity_and_sufficiency">necessary but not sufficient</a> of course, i.e. certainly not proof-positive of the company&rsquo;s engineering and/or financial acumen – but it is very encouraging on a first-impressions basis<sup id="fnref:2"><a href="#fn:2" rel="footnote">2</a></sup>.</p>

<h2>Onboarding Process</h2>

<p>Getting signed up was pretty smooth, and involved zero pieces of physical paper<sup id="fnref:3"><a href="#fn:3" rel="footnote">3</a></sup>. They walk you through a progression of steps where you verify identification, prove ownership of your bank account, and so on. At any given point, it&rsquo;s very clear how things are progressing. Given the fairly strict requirements on identify verification and so on in financial services – this is about as pleasant a process as one could hope for.</p>

<p>As part of the signup, new users also participate in a risk tolerance questionnaire – fairly standard stuff. I can&rsquo;t meaningfully comment on this as I have my own well-established opinions in that area.</p>

<p>Wealthsimple differs from its peers – certainly Wealthfront – in at least one important way: investors have access to an advisor figure who can, presumably, offer advice on matters relating to financial milestones and tax optimization. As part of the onboarding process, they invite you to schedule a brief call with your assigned advisor. I&rsquo;m not sure to what extent this person is available to the investor, and to what extent their advice is personalized, but their presence is surely comforting to any investor keen to escape the fleecing<sup id="fnref:4"><a href="#fn:4" rel="footnote">4</a></sup> of their <code>2.5% MER</code> mutual funds, but is not quite ready to be fully self-directed.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="http://liggat.org/images/2014/chart.png" width="600" title="'Chart'" ></p>

<h2>Investing</h2>

<p>With your risk tolerance identified, Wealthsimple builds a portfolio by transacting ETFs on your behalf.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="http://liggat.org/images/2014/portfolio.png" width="600" title="'Portfolio'" ></p>

<p>There&rsquo;s a lot to like here; <a href="http://www.blackrock.com/ca/individual/en/products/239837/ishares-sptsx-capped-composite-index-etf">XIC</a> and <a href="https://personal.vanguard.com/us/funds/snapshot?FundId=0970&amp;FundIntExt=INT">VTI</a> are used for Canadian and US equity respectively. These are large, diverse total stock market indices with ultra-cheap <code>0.05%</code> MERs<sup id="fnref:5"><a href="#fn:5" rel="footnote">5</a></sup>. Moreover, they trade in USD-based securities where appropriate – presumably after first <a href="http://liggat.org/2013/09/06/efficient-currency-conversion/">converting cheaply</a>. This is advantageous, not only for currency diversification reasons, but also for eliminating US <a href="http://canadiancouchpotato.com/2010/03/05/put-your-assets-in-their-place/">dividend-withholding</a> in RRSPs.</p>

<p>Other choices in the portfolio – I&rsquo;m not so sure. For example, the category of <strong>Risk-Managed Stocks</strong> has the descriptor <em>&lsquo;uses a momentum-based strategy designed to protect investors against big market downturns&rsquo;</em>, which sounds awfully <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Active_management#Disadvantages_of_active_management">active-management</a> to me. Given that I essentially subscribe to the weak efficient-market hypothesis, and believe stochastic forecasting <a href="http://liggat.org/2014/06/30/why-publicly-forecast/">is impossible</a> – this is problematic for my own personal investing philosophy. Others may well differ on this point.</p>

<p>Regardless of the ultimate performance of these more exotic securities &ndash; their management doesn&rsquo;t come especially cheap. Their presence inflates the weighted MER of the portfolio in my account to <code>0.3622%</code>. Speaking of pricing:</p>

<h2>Pricing</h2>

<p>Wealthsimple has various offerings depending on the size of the portfolio under management, but generally speaking:</p>

<ul>
<li>investors pay a management fee of <code>0.5%</code>; less on Premium (above $100k) or above portfolios</li>
<li>automated <a href="http://canadiancouchpotato.com/2014/09/26/is-it-time-for-tax-loss-selling/">tax-loss harvesting</a> is included with Premium accounts and above</li>
<li>ETF trading fees are <em>not</em> charged; this is covered by Wealthsimple<sup id="fnref:6"><a href="#fn:6" rel="footnote">6</a></sup></li>
<li>The management fee is <em>not inclusive</em> of the MER of the underlying ETFs, so it&rsquo;s really <code>0.5% + 0.3622%</code>, assuming the same portfolio as mine in Wealthsimple.</li>
</ul>


<p>Here is how Wealthsimple&rsquo;s portfolio fees compare to other options. These options are discussed in more detail at <a href="http://canadiancouchpotato.com/model-portfolios/">Canadian Couch Potato</a>, and I won&rsquo;t replicate that here. I operate in the <em>Low-cost Index ETF</em> category myself.</p>

<div class="summary">
  <table>
    <thead>
      <tr>
        <td>Method</td>
        <td>Weighted MER (Approx %)</td>
      </tr>
    </thead>
    <tbody>
      <tr>
        <td>Typical Mutual Funds</td>
        <td><span>2.5</span></td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>Tangerine Mutual Funds</td>
        <td><span>1.07</span></td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>Wealthsimple (MER + fee)</td>
        <td><span><strong>0.85</strong></span></td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>TD e-series Mutual Funds</td>
        <td><span>0.44</span></td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>Low-cost Index ETFs</td>
        <td><span>0.18</span></td>
      </tr>
    </tbody>
  </table>
</div>


<p>Wealthsimple is undoubtedly far, far cheaper than the most egregious mutual fund offerings to be found in this country. However, it remains quite a bit more expensive than either a TD <a href="https://www.tdcanadatrust.com/products-services/investing/mutual-funds/td-eseries-funds.jsp">e-series</a> portfolio, or a low-cost ETF portfolio. Obviously this isn&rsquo;t an apples-to-apples comparison; Wealthsimple automates much of the work and provides access to an advisor – neither of which is available in the cheaper options above. The more exotic ETF choices are harder for me to justify. Ultimately, it&rsquo;s up to the individual investor whether the value justifies the cost based on their needs and philosophy. There&rsquo;s nothing wrong with paying more to get a better level of service or experience, so long as one is aware that seemingly small percentages in fact <a href="http://www.michaeljamesonmoney.com/2011/12/better-way-to-explain-investing-costs.html">compound</a> rather substantially.</p>

<p>As it stands, right now I still see TD <a href="https://www.tdcanadatrust.com/products-services/investing/mutual-funds/td-eseries-funds.jsp">e-series</a> remaining in the sweet spot, given its low cost and relative lack of maintenance required.</p>

<h2>Would I Use It?</h2>

<p>I&rsquo;ll probably keep my initial deposit invested as an experiment, but I&rsquo;m unlikely to go all-in on it with my entire portfolio. Leaving aside my investment objections raised above, I&rsquo;m ultimately not really the target market. I&rsquo;m a finance geek – I <em>like</em> executing trades, <a href="http://liggat.org/2013/09/06/efficient-currency-conversion/">efficiently converting currency</a>, manually rebalancing – this stuff is interesting and intellectually rewarding to me. Saving roughly sixty basis points for doing this on my own is simply a bonus for doing something I&rsquo;m inclined towards anyway.</p>

<h2>Conclusion</h2>

<p>I&rsquo;ll be following Wealthsimple&rsquo;s progress with great interest. I can object about their precise portfolio choices, or the size of their fee in relation to other alternatives, but these aspects of the service needn&rsquo;t be permanently fixed. I would like to see them at least <em>offer</em> a more traditional indexed option aside from what they have. Of particular interest to me is if they can find a way to enable frequent, dollar-cost averaged purchases – <em>crucially</em> with a good solution for calculating <a href="http://www.theglobeandmail.com/globe-investor/investor-education/the-abcs-of-tracking-your-acb/article17838427/">adjusted cost-bases</a> in non-registered accounts. This is a very difficult thing to achieve elsewhere, even at TD e-series.</p>

<p>Taken as a whole, it seems to me that they&rsquo;ve built the beginnings of something great. However their offerings play out, the fees that most investors in this country pay, often-unwittingly, are <em>eye-wateringly</em> high, so it seems to me there is a pretty substantial <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Price_umbrella">price umbrella</a> for Wealthsimple to comfortably sit under! Investing is a natural place for software to be deployed, and after wistfully observing the US-market progress on this front, I&rsquo;m happy to see Canada start to catch up. I wish Wealthsimple the best of luck – innovation in the customer facing part of banking and investing is always appreciated, and seems to be oddly rare among the incumbents.</p>
<div class="footnotes">
<hr/>
<ol>
<li id="fn:1">
<p>To what extent Wealthsimple truly adheres to indexing is not fully clear, as explored below.<a href="#fnref:1" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
<li id="fn:2">
<p>Especially <a href="http://liggat.org/about/">to me</a>, as I&rsquo;m immersed in web application engineering and infrastructure daily.<a href="#fnref:2" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
<li id="fn:3">
<p>I <a href="http://liggat.org/2013/07/21/paperless/">went paperless</a> over a year ago, so this is always appreciated.<a href="#fnref:3" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
<li id="fn:4">
<p>This is about the least harsh word I can reasonably apply here.<a href="#fnref:4" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
<li id="fn:5">
<p>That&rsquo;s a fee of $5 for every $10,000 invested. It doesn&rsquo;t get much better than that.<a href="#fnref:5" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
<li id="fn:6">
<p>Self-directed investors typically pay $9.95 or so for a trade, so this represents a cost saving. The transactional batching may well have bid/ask spread implications though, but I didn&rsquo;t look into this.<a href="#fnref:6" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
</ol>
</div>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Zsh Evangelism]]></title>
    <link href="http://liggat.org/2014/09/07/zsh-evangelism/"/>
    <updated>2014-09-07T14:29:24-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://liggat.org/2014/09/07/zsh-evangelism</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>After a decade of stubbornly sticking with <code>bash</code>, I&rsquo;ve <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Chsh">changed shells</a> to <code>zsh</code> and couldn&rsquo;t be happier with the decision. The only regret is in not having switched long before now.<!--more--> This was a <code>svn</code> => <code>git</code><sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" rel="footnote">1</a></sup> sort of transition for me: <em>of course, I should&rsquo;ve been using it all along!</em></p>

<p>By way of evangelism, a few notes on my configuration:</p>

<h3>Prompt</h3>

<p>It is much easier and cleaner to customize a <code>zsh</code> prompt than in <code>bash</code>. It also has a notion of an <code>RPROMPT</code> – the right-aligned prompt – which is excellent for supplementary directory information<sup id="fnref:2"><a href="#fn:2" rel="footnote">2</a></sup>.
<img class="center" src="http://liggat.org/images/2014/zsh.png" width="700" title="'Zsh Prompt'" ></p>

<p>My prompt configuration can be found <a href="https://github.com/dliggat/dotfiles/blob/master/zsh/05_prompt.zsh">here</a>.</p>

<h3>Oh My Zsh!</h3>

<p>Another advantage of switching to <code>zsh</code> is the opportunity to use <a href="http://ohmyz.sh">oh-my-zsh</a>, a set of plugins, helper functions, and themes for <code>zsh</code>. I&rsquo;m not using any of the themes directly<sup id="fnref:3"><a href="#fn:3" rel="footnote">3</a></sup>, but the plugins are really nice, and provide, for example, tab completion for executables like <code>ruby</code>, <code>git</code>, etc.</p>

<h3>Dotfiles</h3>

<p>I&rsquo;ve structured my dotfile repository in a modular way: separating into various concern areas such as <a href="https://github.com/dliggat/dotfiles/blob/master/zsh/03_aliases.zsh">aliases.zsh</a>, <a href="https://github.com/dliggat/dotfiles/blob/master/zsh/04_functions.zsh">functions.zsh</a>, and so on. The top level <code>~/.zshrc</code> symlink-target consequently reduces down to a simple <a href="https://github.com/dliggat/dotfiles/blob/master/zshrc">script</a>; its only job is to set a few <code>zsh</code> options and then <code>source</code> the individual modules:</p>

<figure class='code'><figcaption><span>.zshrc: Shell Configuration </span></figcaption>
<div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
<span class='line-number'>3</span>
<span class='line-number'>4</span>
<span class='line-number'>5</span>
<span class='line-number'>6</span>
<span class='line-number'>7</span>
<span class='line-number'>8</span>
<span class='line-number'>9</span>
<span class='line-number'>10</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class='bash'><span class='line'><span class="c">#!/bin/zsh</span>
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'>setopt HIST_IGNORE_ALL_DUPS
</span><span class='line'>setopt HIST_IGNORE_SPACE
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'><span class="nb">export </span><span class="nv">DOTFILES</span><span class="o">=</span><span class="nv">$HOME</span>/git/me/dotfiles
</span><span class='line'><span class="k">for </span>zsh_config in <span class="sb">`</span>ls <span class="nv">$DOTFILES</span>/zsh/*.zsh | sort<span class="sb">`</span>  <span class="c"># Sort =&gt; source in order.</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="k">do</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="k">  </span><span class="nb">source</span> <span class="nv">$zsh_config</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="k">done</span>
</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p>If, like me until recently, inertia still keeps you on <code>bash</code> – definitely give <code>zsh</code> a try. You won&rsquo;t regret it.</p>
<div class="footnotes">
<hr/>
<ol>
<li id="fn:1">
<p>Well, <em>any source control system</em> => <code>git</code>, really.<a href="#fnref:1" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
<li id="fn:2">
<p>In my case: <code>git</code> repository status and <code>ruby</code> version information as set by <code>rbenv</code>.<a href="#fnref:2" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
<li id="fn:3">
<p>My prompt is a custom version of the <a href="https://github.com/robbyrussell/oh-my-zsh/blob/master/themes/gallois.zsh-theme">gallois</a> theme.<a href="#fnref:3" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
</ol>
</div>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Everyone Should Use Twitter]]></title>
    <link href="http://liggat.org/2014/08/27/everyone-should-use-twitter/"/>
    <updated>2014-08-27T15:20:45-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://liggat.org/2014/08/27/everyone-should-use-twitter</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Twitter&rsquo;s role in the public sphere is a contradictory one. It is at once ubiquious – adorning all manner of billboards and signs, not to mention the lower fifth of the screen of cable news broadcasts – and yet almost entirely foreign to those who do not use it. That last clause verges on the tautological, but the emphasis is on <em>foreign</em>; I submit that Twitter is <em>bizarre</em> and outright <em>strange</em> to its non-users to a much greater extent than is true in the case of Facebook or just about any of the other prominent social web services.<!--more--></p>

<p>Although Twitter&rsquo;s ubiquity ensures that just about everyone has <em>heard</em> of it, and may even be aware that it has developed into a substantial forum for worldwide discourse, I get the sense that most people have never been shown a single, compelling reason why they might personally trouble to open an account.</p>

<p>As a devoted, adoring user of the service<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" rel="footnote">1</a></sup>, this strikes me as a mild tragedy. It is understandable why many people might feel this way; bootstrapping an account from naught to useful is not an especially easy task, and is fraught with several meaningful obstacles:</p>

<ul>
<li><strong>The Bootstrapping Problem</strong>: Twitter gets more interesting with each additional account you discover and follow<sup id="fnref:2"><a href="#fn:2" rel="footnote">2</a></sup>. However, at the dawn of an account – with zero follows – Twitter&rsquo;s &lsquo;interestingness&rsquo; is at a minimum, as low as it will ever be. This is not encouraging to a newcomer.</li>
<li><strong>Utility</strong>: As a consequence, it is not at all clear to a newcomer what possible utility they might receive from this new account. Moreover, newcomers seem to believe that the primary purpose of Twitter is in <em>tweeting</em><sup id="fnref:3"><a href="#fn:3" rel="footnote">3</a></sup>, when in actual fact, <em>reading the timeline</em> is the main reason it&rsquo;s worth having an account. To be sure, it&rsquo;s fun to participate in conversations once in a while, but one can receive an enormous amount of value from Twitter simply by following a set of interesting accounts, reading their updates, and perhaps never once sending a tweet.</li>
<li><strong>Esotericism</strong>: Twitter pioneered, or at least greatly popularized, several new dynamics such as the asymmetric follower/following relationship and <code>@</code>-mentioning. It also has its own conventions which are opaque from the outset<sup id="fnref:4"><a href="#fn:4" rel="footnote">4</a></sup>. Although all of this is well understood by regular users, I get the impression it is intimidating to start with.</li>
</ul>


<p>Twitter has visibly attempted to address these issues<sup id="fnref:5"><a href="#fn:5" rel="footnote">5</a></sup>, though not satisfactorially I would argue. The onboarding process addresses the bootstrapping problem to a degree, but that&rsquo;s only useful once a newcomer has been convinced to sign up. Prior to that point, Twitter has done a poor job communicating the message that, <strong>if you like reading stuff on the web, and most people do, after all; then you would almost certainly enjoy having a Twitter account</strong>.</p>

<p>That is exactly my position. I posit that the intersection of people who (a) currently like reading the internet and (b) would enjoy Twitter with a sufficiently-well-constructed following-list is one and the same.</p>

<p>If you&rsquo;re reading this, and don&rsquo;t have a Twitter account, I <em>implore</em> you to give it a try.</p>

<ol>
<li>Open an account. Using your real name or having the account be associated in any way with your real identity is strictly optional.</li>
<li>Pick some people to follow. See the end of this page for some suggestions.</li>
<li>Have a look at the timeline several times a day. It&rsquo;s not a corporate email inbox – to be doggedly read to completion, but rather, a river of interesting things for perusal and sampling at any time.</li>
</ol>


<p>With a judiciously selected follow-list, Twitter has the potential to become a fascinating window onto the world, tailored to your own interests. It is truly fantastic, and you should give it a try if you haven&rsquo;t already.</p>

<h3>Addendum: Some Follow Suggestions</h3>

<p>Here&rsquo;s a few suggestions of worthwhile accounts to follow<sup id="fnref:6"><a href="#fn:6" rel="footnote">6</a></sup> based on my own interests (the categories are overly-simplistic, of course):</p>

<ul>
<li>Canadian-focus <a href="https://twitter.com/acoyne">@acoyne</a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/MikePMoffatt">@MikePMoffatt</a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/stephenfgordon">@stephenfgordon</a></li>
<li>News <a href="https://twitter.com/guardian">@guardian</a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/BreakingNews">@BreakingNews</a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/CBCNews">@CBCNews</a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/BBCNews">@BBCNews</a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/TheTyee">@TheTyee</a></li>
<li>Economics <a href="https://twitter.com/TheEconomist">@TheEconomist</a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/TimHarford">@TimHarford</a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/Pricenomics">@Pricenomics</a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/planetmoney">@planetmoney</a></li>
<li>Finance <a href="https://twitter.com/felixsalmon">@felixsalmon</a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/dealbook">@dealbook</a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/CdnCouchPotato">@CdnCouchPotato</a></li>
<li>Tech <a href="https://twitter.com/pmarca">@pmarca</a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/BenedictEvans">@BenedictEvans</a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/monkbent">@monkbent</a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/fmanjoo">@fmanjoo</a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/gruber">@gruber</a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/troyhunt">@troyhunt</a></li>
<li>Urbanism <a href="https://twitter.com/StrongTowns">@StrongTowns</a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/neil21">@neil21</a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/modacitylife">@modacitylife</a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/copenhagenize">@copenhagenize</a></li>
<li>Miscellaneous <a href="https://twitter.com/mathbabedotorg">@mathbabedotorg</a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/TheOnion">@TheOnion</a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/StatFact">@StatFact</a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/RealTimeWWII">@RealTimeWWII</a></li>
</ul>

<div class="footnotes">
<hr/>
<ol>
<li id="fn:1">
<p>Twitter is quite possibly <em>my favourite thing</em> about our modern, connected, mobile world &ndash; and I include my iPhone in that list.<a href="#fnref:1" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
<li id="fn:2">
<p>Unlike Facebook, which I contend gets less interesting with each additional friend (beyond a minimal set of close contacts).<a href="#fnref:2" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
<li id="fn:3">
<p>What a tweet even <em>is</em> seems to cause some degree of consternation initially, with many newcomers believing that the act of tweeting is predominantly a way to share breakfast photographs, express inane self-indulgences, or bolster your public persona if you happen to be Ashton Kutcher – all things that no right-thinking individual should engage in.<a href="#fnref:3" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
<li id="fn:4">
<p>e.g. 140-char limit, <code>@</code>-replies <a href="https://support.twitter.com/articles/119138-types-of-tweets-and-where-they-appear">only appear</a> in the timelines of mutual follows.<a href="#fnref:4" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
<li id="fn:5">
<p>As I write this, in August 2014, there has been word of Twitter monkeying with what shows up in timelines; heretofore this was strictly determined by one&rsquo;s followed accounts. This is <strong>not</strong> the way to solve the utility problem, and I hope they see sense.<a href="#fnref:5" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
<li id="fn:6">
<p>Following does not imply endorsement, but it does imply <em>interest</em>.<a href="#fnref:6" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
</ol>
</div>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Why Publicly Forecast?]]></title>
    <link href="http://liggat.org/2014/06/30/why-publicly-forecast/"/>
    <updated>2014-06-30T18:10:31-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://liggat.org/2014/06/30/why-publicly-forecast</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>As part of my <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Operations_research">Operations Research</a> training, I took a course in statistical forecasting. The course, despite being replete with interesting concepts and methods, had a fairly simple takeaway: more often than not, <em>forecasting is impossible</em>. This is particularly true in scenarios with a <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Martingale_(probability_theory)">martingale</a>-property such as stock prices.<!--more--></p>

<p>So it is with that in mind that I cannot help but be cynical when I see a prominent organization, usually a bank or investment house of some sort, publicly forecast financial figures such as currency exchange rates or stock prices.</p>

<p>Consider this statement, as reported by the CBC in January of 2014:</p>

<h4><a href="http://www.cbc.ca/news/business/canadian-dollar-headed-to-85-cents-us-td-says-1.2516849">Canadian dollar headed to 85 cents US, TD says</a></h4>

<blockquote><p>In the near-term, the loonie is forecast to fall as low as 85 cents U.S. by mid-year.</p></blockquote>

<p>Why do this? It is hard to ascribe intellectual honesty to such prognostication. For one thing, I&rsquo;m largely convinced by the [weak] <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Efficient-market_hypothesis">efficient-market hypothesis</a>, and thus don&rsquo;t believe it is actually <em>possible</em> to forecast the price of a currency six months out<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" rel="footnote">1</a></sup>. Furthermore, assuming one <em>could</em> perform this forecasting with better-than-chance accuracy &ndash; why share that secret with the world? That knowledge, guarded jealously and carefully executed upon, would lead to untold riches. It is therefore difficult to arrive at charitable reasons why an organization would make such a pronouncement<sup id="fnref:2"><a href="#fn:2" rel="footnote">2</a></sup>.</p>

<p>As it turns out, this particular &lsquo;mid-year&rsquo; forecast was dead wrong:</p>

<h4><a href="http://www.cbc.ca/news/business/canadian-dollar-nears-2014-high-against-u-s-greenback-1.2689863">Canadian dollar nears 2014 high against U.S. greenback</a></h4>

<blockquote><p>The Canadian dollar tested six-month highs Friday, but analysts say they don’t expect the loonie’s recent strength to be the new normal. The Canadian dollar rose almost three-tenths of a cent to close at 93.80 cents US Friday</p></blockquote>

<p>Interestingly, coverage of such forecasts never seem to hold the prognosticators to account. Although the banks involved in these two statements were different, I have never seen the CBC or other news organization publicly examine the historical record for such forecasts.</p>

<p>My take: forecasting is generally impossible. Stochastic, martingale forecasting <strong>is</strong> impossible. Don&rsquo;t believe anyone who claims otherwise.</p>
<div class="footnotes">
<hr/>
<ol>
<li id="fn:1">
<p>Speaking very imprecisely: if the information existed in the present to do this forecasting, it would quickly be arbitraged away such that the advantage would disappear.<a href="#fnref:1" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
<li id="fn:2">
<p>TD happens to be the forecasting organization in this case, but this activity is by no means exclusive to them. It is very, very common to read all manner of financial forecasts by banks, analysis firms, etc.<a href="#fnref:2" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
</ol>
</div>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Accounts Are Containers]]></title>
    <link href="http://liggat.org/2014/06/05/accounts-are-containers/"/>
    <updated>2014-06-05T14:19:57-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://liggat.org/2014/06/05/accounts-are-containers</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Recently, I&rsquo;ve found myself explaining to some friends and family members the precise difference between a regular (i.e. non-registered) account, an RRSP account, and a TFSA account. In particular, many Canadians hold the mistaken belief that these accounts are <em>products</em> &ndash; a thing that the bank creates and sells. This is incorrect &ndash; <strong>accounts are containers</strong>, into which the same assets (cash savings, stocks, etc) can be placed. The type of the container merely specifies how its gains are taxed, nothing more.<!--more--></p>

<p><img class="center" src="http://liggat.org/images/2014/containers.png" width="600" title="'Containers'" ></p>

<blockquote><p>The type of the container merely specifies how its gains are taxed, nothing more.</p></blockquote>

<h3>Non-registered</h3>

<p>A non-registered account is simply an ordinary container with no special tax treatment. It can hold cash savings, stocks, bonds, ETFs, mutual funds, etc. A vanilla savings account is one such example, but a stock trading account could qualify also. Any &lsquo;gains&rsquo; from the assets in this container are subject to taxation, though it&rsquo;s worth noting that the various types of &lsquo;gain&rsquo; (e.g. interest, Canadian dividends, foreign dividends, capital gains) are each handled in their own special way &ndash; this is where the unfortunate complexity of the tax code rears its head. Regardless, bottom line: <strong>you pay tax on any gains in a non-registered account</strong>.</p>

<h3>RRSP</h3>

<p>An RRSP account is a container designed with retirement needs in mind. Like the non-registered account, it may hold a variety of asset types. It is taxed in a notable manner: when you <em>contribute</em> money to this account, you actually receive a reduction in your tax-payable for the year, today<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" rel="footnote">1</a></sup>. However, when you <em>withdraw</em> money, usually in retirement, that money is treated as if it were salary income &ndash; and taxed accordingly. In the meantime, the assets in the container grow <em>tax-free</em> through the usual means (interest, dividends, capital gains).</p>

<p><a href="http://www.michaeljamesonmoney.com/2014/03/cra-your-rrsp-partners-whether-you-want.html">Michael James</a> has documented an excellent way to think of this transaction: in exchange for a reduction in this year&rsquo;s taxes, you grant the <a href="http://www.cra-arc.gc.ca/menu-eng.html">CRA</a> an ownership stake in the future value of your RRSP container. This turns out to be a beneficial manoeuvre so long as the <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tax_rate#Marginal">marginal</a> tax rate on the contributed money is higher than the <em>[unknowable but presumably and hopefully lower]</em> marginal tax rate at retirement. Bottom line: <strong>in an RRSP, you get a reduction in taxes today in exchange for granting the CRA a stake in the container&rsquo;s eventual disbursements</strong>.</p>

<h3>TFSA</h3>

<p>A TFSA is a container whose gains (interest, dividends, capital gains, etc) are <strong>never subject to taxation</strong>. Because that&rsquo;s such an attractive proposition, the government only permits adult individuals to contribute $5000 per year<sup id="fnref:2"><a href="#fn:2" rel="footnote">2</a></sup>. Assuming wise and/or fortunate investing decisions<sup id="fnref:3"><a href="#fn:3" rel="footnote">3</a></sup>, the TFSA has the potential to grow substantially over a multi-decade period, and will result in a container of assets which is not subject to any taxation. Bottom line: <strong>Any growth within a TFSA is never taxed but only a limited contribution per year is permitted</strong>.</p>

<h3>Which Should I Use?</h3>

<p>It can be complicated. There is a ton of nuance to the rules governing the above, and this is not financial advice. With these general frameworks in mind, the question for every individual to be asking themselves is: <em>&ldquo;given my tax and income situation and future plans and possible scenarios, which of these gives me the most advantage?&rdquo;</em>. Each of these has a possible role to play, though the TFSA in particular is an excellent vehicle for investing. The opportunity it represents should not be squandered, in my view.</p>

<h3>Who cares &ndash; this is boring!</h3>

<p>I&rsquo;m somewhat sympathetic to that claim. However, ignorance in the basics of this topic is very, very costly &ndash; in missed tax-saving opportunities and in selecting highly-suboptimal financial products. The price for ignorance is <em>substantial</em> personal expense. It&rsquo;s well worth a cursory knowledge of how these containers work, and how they can be used to advance one&rsquo;s freedom, happiness and life goals – which is of course the primary underlying objective of any personal finance initiative.</p>
<div class="footnotes">
<hr/>
<ol>
<li id="fn:1">
<p>i.e. usually in the form of a tax refund<a href="#fnref:1" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
<li id="fn:2">
<p>This was the figure set in 2009, and is inflation adjusted to be $5500 as of 2013. As of 2014, an eligible adult has $31,000 worth of room for contribution. The contribution room does not expire and accumulates from year to year. There are strict rules on withdrawal and re-contribution, so <strong>tread lightly</strong>!<a href="#fnref:2" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
<li id="fn:3">
<p>I&rsquo;m a fan of <a href="http://canadiancouchpotato.com/couch-potato-faq/">index investing</a>, myself.<a href="#fnref:3" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
</ol>
</div>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[A Call for Modern Banking]]></title>
    <link href="http://liggat.org/2014/04/22/a-call-for-modern-banking/"/>
    <updated>2014-04-22T06:40:07-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://liggat.org/2014/04/22/a-call-for-modern-banking</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I can scarcely walk past a bus shelter without being shown a poster by one of the big-five Canadian banks invariably touting their extended branch hours, new location(s), or magnanimous decision to remain open on Sundays. Guess what? No one under 60 cares.<!--more--> Visiting a bank branch is unnecessary for the overwhelming majority of banking interactions, and most people only do so on exceedingly rare occasions and with substantial reluctance due to the trespass upon time and the general hassle that a visit represents<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" rel="footnote">1</a></sup>.</p>

<p>What I, and undoubtedly many others, <em>would</em> like to see, however, is <strong>modern online services</strong>. I&rsquo;m actually astonished that one of these banks has not thrown a bit more investment in this direction – or if they have – it&rsquo;s not at all externally apparent. Right off the top of my head I can produce a laundry list of substantial online enhancements that I&rsquo;d like to see a bank implement &ndash; I&rsquo;d switch all my business in a heartbeat to any bank who made even a modest subset of these changes. I bet I&rsquo;m not alone.</p>

<h3>My Wish List</h3>

<ol>
<li><strong>Two Factor Authentication</strong>. My <a href="https://support.google.com/accounts/answer/180744?hl=en">email</a>, my <a href="http://blog.evernote.com/blog/2013/10/04/two-step-verification-available-to-all-users/">digital archive</a>, my <a href="https://www.dropbox.com/help/363/en">cloud storage</a>, and my <a href="https://blog.twitter.com/2013/getting-started-with-login-verification">Twitter</a> account all have two-factor authentication (<a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Two-step_verification">2FA</a>). Why doesn&rsquo;t my bank account? It&rsquo;s not like 2FA is an unfamiliar concept to either the banks or the populace &ndash; <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Chip_and_PIN">chip &amp; PIN</a> for debit and credit cards has been deployed in Canada for many years. It seriously astounds me that as I write this in 2014, this hasn&rsquo;t been rolled out on the web by any bank that I&rsquo;m aware of.</li>
<li><strong>Sensible Policies on Passwords</strong>. Canadian banks seem to have an odd philosophy on passwords. TD&rsquo;s iOS app does not appear to permit paste into password fields &ndash; needlessly hampering the usage of password managers like <a href="https://agilebits.com/onepassword/mac">1Password</a>. BMO mandates an alphanumeric password of <strong>precisely-six alphanumeric</strong> characters<sup id="fnref:2"><a href="#fn:2" rel="footnote">2</a></sup>. Why the artificial limitations? These measures are destructive, not augmentative, of online-security.</li>
<li><strong>Modern Web</strong>. The web has improved immeasurably over the past decade. With the scourge of Internet Explorer&rsquo;s worst transgressions behind us, and transformative technologies like responsive-design, web typography, CSS transforms, client-side JavaScript frameworks (i.e. <a href="http://emberjs.com/">Ember.js</a>) constantly entering the tech-zeitgeist &ndash; it&rsquo;s a golden age for the web<sup id="fnref:3"><a href="#fn:3" rel="footnote">3</a></sup>. You&rsquo;d never know it though, based on the appearance of online banking. I&rsquo;d be happy as a start with even a bit of interface-enhancing JavaScript, which is curiously absent from banking web apps &ndash; virtually unthinkable in 2014 in most other online contexts. Instead, absurdly high page latencies, an absence of responsive-design and stodgy <em>Times-New-Arial</em> typefaces<sup id="fnref:4"><a href="#fn:4" rel="footnote">4</a></sup> are the order of the day.</li>
<li><strong>Mobile apps</strong>. Curiously, most Canadian banks do have mobile apps, on iOS at least, and yet they don&rsquo;t seem to serve any real purpose beyond marketing. Utility wise, there&rsquo;s no point having a mobile app that&rsquo;s nothing but a native container for [in their case, tremendously-slow-to-render] web content. With the exception of the Tangerine<sup id="fnref:5"><a href="#fn:5" rel="footnote">5</a></sup> app&rsquo;s ability to photo-deposit cheques – a welcome, if belated arrival – none of these apps actually enable any use-case that couldn&rsquo;t be accomplished in a mobile browser. I&rsquo;d like to see authentication caching, some use of native UI components perhaps, and a robust, configurable push notification scheme for transaction/payment alerts. And, of course, their possible use as a vehicle for the aforementioned 2FA.</li>
<li><strong>Data</strong>. I want access to my data. No, not as some Quicken <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Binary_large_object">blob</a> or a poorly-formatted CSV file, but in a sane, structured format, preferably <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Json">JSON</a><sup id="fnref:6"><a href="#fn:6" rel="footnote">6</a></sup>. It remains an utter hassle to view and use historical banking data &ndash; to find a particular subset of recurring transactions for example. Better structured banking data would enable entire classes of tools, workflows, and even businesses to exist.</li>
<li><strong>API/OAuth</strong>. Relatedly, I want a programmatic method to access this data, and support for an authorization technique like OAuth to delegate <strong>revocable</strong> access to a trusted third party. This is a well-solved problem &ndash; it is a ubiquitous pattern in tech, and there is enormous demand for it to exist. Since it doesn&rsquo;t exist &ndash; horrible kludges like providing aggregation sites (e.g. <a href="https://www.mint.com/">Mint</a><sup id="fnref:7"><a href="#fn:7" rel="footnote">7</a></sup>) banking credentials are the only way to enable third-party access.</li>
</ol>


<h3>Objections</h3>

<p>I bear no illusions that a CTO or similar executive from one of these banks will even see this, much less take it seriously. Even if they did see it, I can imagine the guffaws about how unrealistic this nerd&rsquo;s demands are:</p>

<ul>
<li><em>&ldquo;We can&rsquo;t justify the cost of a massive online systems redesign!&rdquo;</em></li>
<li><em>&ldquo;Don&rsquo;t you know how complex our legacy backend is &ndash; our password policy was chosen to support that!&rdquo;</em></li>
<li><em>&ldquo;We have a myriad of customers and browsers to support &ndash; not everyone is running Safari on brand-new MacBook Pros you know!&rdquo;</em></li>
<li><em>&ldquo;The regulations we are under would never permit API access! We can&rsquo;t ever permit customer data to go to &lsquo;third parties&rsquo; &ndash; the banking regulators and the newspapers would have a field day!&rdquo;</em></li>
</ul>


<p>I&rsquo;m absolutely aware that what I&rsquo;m suggesting requires investment, that banks operate under strict regulation, that data integrity is critical in the financial system (i.e. so technological conservatism is desired). I&rsquo;m further aware that the user base is indeed large, of a wide spectrum of technical-comfort, and that the user-age-distribution is <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Skewness">negatively-skewed</a><sup id="fnref:8"><a href="#fn:8" rel="footnote">8</a></sup>.</p>

<p>So, sure – there are obstacles. But this stuff is hard to get right, not just the tech but also the product vision that goes along with it. With each passing year, the gap between online-banking and the rest of the modern web grows ever starker. I see no reason why the tech we use everyday in virtually every other aspect of life should rocket ahead in functionality, design, thoughtfulness, integration, etc &ndash; while finance/banking remains virtually the same today as in 2004.</p>

<p>If nothing else, I believe excellence in these areas will become a competitive advantage sooner than banks apparently seem to think. Does anyone really think that in ten years time, the major customer service innovation to be touted from every bus-bench will still involve the local branch in some way?</p>
<div class="footnotes">
<hr/>
<ol>
<li id="fn:1">
<p>I realize there&rsquo;s an incentive misalignment here &ndash; more branch visits implies more sales opportunities.<a href="#fnref:1" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
<li id="fn:2">
<p>Forbidding symbolic characters is a <a href="http://www.troyhunt.com/2012/09/do-you-allow-xss-in-your-passwords-you.html">misguided</a> defense against XSS or SQL-injection &ndash; passwords should be cryptographically hashed right away, anyway.<a href="#fnref:2" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
<li id="fn:3">
<p>And much software generally, <a href="http://liggat.org/2013/09/03/a-comparatively-golden-age-of-software/">as I&rsquo;ve argued</a>.<a href="#fnref:3" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
<li id="fn:4">
<p>I realize that <strong>better typography</strong> performs poorly in a DCF calculation. But then, presumably so do the potted rhododendrons festooning the lobby of every branch.<a href="#fnref:4" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
<li id="fn:5">
<p>née ING Direct.<a href="#fnref:5" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
<li id="fn:6">
<p>it&rsquo;s easy to parse and is the <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lingua_franca">lingua franca</a> of programmatic access to data over the Internet.<a href="#fnref:6" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
<li id="fn:7">
<p>However good Mint&rsquo;s security is–and I have reason to believe it is <strong>very</strong> good as I&rsquo;ve met a few of the early engineers–providing credentials to them will always be a highly inferior way to delegate access. Plus it&rsquo;s explicitly forbidden by the Terms of Service for many banks.<a href="#fnref:7" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
<li id="fn:8">
<p>I presume age and wealth correlate fairly well, which likely explains a large amount of the dogged focus on new branches and &lsquo;convenient&rsquo; hours in bank advertising.<a href="#fnref:8" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
</ol>
</div>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Name of Thrones]]></title>
    <link href="http://liggat.org/2014/04/06/the-name-of-thrones/"/>
    <updated>2014-04-06T10:37:29-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://liggat.org/2014/04/06/the-name-of-thrones</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Last summer, my better half and I spent some time in Scotland, the country of my birth. Departing from Edinburgh, and en route to Inverness, we went through Glencoe in the Scottish Highlands. Leaving aside the very real potential for bias on my part &ndash; Glencoe is a hauntingly beautiful place, with equally impactful history in its past.<!--more--></p>

<p><img class="center" src="http://liggat.org/images/2014/glencoe.jpg" width="500" title="'Glencoe'" ></p>

<p>George R.R. Martin is <a href="http://www.nerdist.com/2013/06/george-r-r-martin-explains-the-red-weddings-historical-roots/">well known</a> to have drawn inspiration for <strong>A Song of Ice and Fire</strong><sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" rel="footnote">1</a></sup> from aspects of this part of the world. Famously, the highly-significant and series-defining <em>Red Wedding</em><sup id="fnref:2"><a href="#fn:2" rel="footnote">2</a></sup> event parallels the heinous circumstances of the late-seventeenth century <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Massacre_of_Glencoe">Massacre of Glencoe</a>. Moreover, further North in Scotland is a region known as <a href="https://www.google.com/maps/search/wester+ross/@57.7018103,-5.6741077,11z">Wester Ross</a> &ndash; which bears more than a passing linguistic similarity to <em>Westeros</em>.</p>

<p>With the fourth season of <strong>Game of Thrones</strong> underway today on HBO, this is a fairly relevant time to document my theory about the original series title; i.e. why is <strong>A Song of Ice and Fire</strong> named thusly?</p>

<p>Back in 2013, in Glencoe, our tour bus stopped at a small vantage point. An educational plaque–the sort you imagine gets put in place by a local historical society and promptly forgotten–was at the head of the vantage point and explained some of the local geology. Interestingly, in one corner of the plaque was the phrase <strong>&ldquo;Of Fire &hellip; and Ice&rdquo;</strong>: used inconspicuously as a section header for a paragraph about geological time:</p>

<p><img class="center" src="http://liggat.org/images/2014/sign.jpg" width="500" title="'The Plaque'" ></p>

<p>I have no idea if George R.R. Martin has ever spoken publicly about the origin of the series title. I have no idea if he&rsquo;s seen this plaque, and even if he has, whether he remembers it or not. But he clearly has a connection to the area, and it seems plausible to me that this little detail on this unassuming plaque, whether consciously or otherwise, somehow became the core of the title of his magnum opus.</p>
<div class="footnotes">
<hr/>
<ol>
<li id="fn:1">
<p><strong>A Song of Ice and Fire</strong> is, of course, the name of the <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/A_Song_of_Ice_and_Fire">series</a> of books for which <strong>A Game of Thrones</strong> is book one. HBO evidently felt that the latter made for a more palatable TV-series name (likely correct).<a href="#fnref:1" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
<li id="fn:2">
<p>Which occurred in the penultimate episode of the third season, or within book three, <strong>A Storm of Swords</strong>, if you prefer.<a href="#fnref:2" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
</ol>
</div>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[IPv6: An Unreachable Wall?]]></title>
    <link href="http://liggat.org/2014/03/23/ipv6-an-unreachable-wall/"/>
    <updated>2014-03-23T12:55:48-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://liggat.org/2014/03/23/ipv6-an-unreachable-wall</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>In <a href="http://www.fiatlux.fm/pragmatic/16">episode 16</a> of <a href="https://twitter.com/fiatluxfm">Ben Alexander</a> and <a href="https://twitter.com/johnchidgey">John Chidgey&rsquo;s</a> excellent <a href="http://www.fiatlux.fm/pragmatic/">Pragmatic</a> podcast, the hosts touched upon the unfortunate tendency of organizations &amp; individuals to underanticipate the scale of future demands upon their designed technology.<!--more--></p>

<p>Examples of this phenomenon abound:</p>

<ul>
<li>The North American <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Public_switched_telephone_network">PSTN</a> seemed like a vast address space at the time of its inception, and yet I&rsquo;ve been through <a href="http://www.cbc.ca/news/canada/vancouver-gets-10-digit-dialing-1.275934">at least one</a> extension in my life, as fax machines and mobile phones consumed far more telephone numbers than was anticipated.</li>
<li>&ldquo;<em>640k [of computer memory] ought to be enough for anybody</em>&rdquo; &ndash; as famously attributed to Bill Gates<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" rel="footnote">1</a></sup>.</li>
<li>The ubiquitous Intel x86<sup id="fnref:2"><a href="#fn:2" rel="footnote">2</a></sup> CPU architecture use 32-bits for addressing locations in system memory; this imposes a hard theoretical 4GiB limit on memory size, which is meager by 2014 standards.</li>
<li><a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/IPv4">IPv4</a>, which uses <strong>32-bits</strong> to assign IP addresses (e.g. of the form <code>123.255.123.255</code>) to devices on the public Internet is insufficiently large of an address space to accommodate all future computing devices, and the world will need to transition<sup id="fnref:3"><a href="#fn:3" rel="footnote">3</a></sup> to <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/IPv6">IPv6</a> at some point.</li>
</ul>


<p>At some point, progress causes us to run into the limits imposed by these upper boundaries. John referred to this phenomenon as &ldquo;hitting the wall&rdquo;, and casted it as an inevitability for any technology.</p>

<p>I agree wholeheartedly, but one with one caveat. I know that history (and John Chidgey) are not on my side here<sup id="fnref:4"><a href="#fn:4" rel="footnote">4</a></sup>, but I&rsquo;m going to go on record with the following postulate: once we finally switch to it, <strong>IPv6 will be an unreachable wall; i.e. it will be sufficient indefinitely as an address space for Internet routing</strong>. That is to say &ndash; a limit exists, but humanity won&rsquo;t be able to reach it.</p>

<h3>IPv4</h3>

<p>My argument for this is strictly numerical. IPv4 uses 32-bits to uniquely identify devices<sup id="fnref:5"><a href="#fn:5" rel="footnote">5</a></sup> on the public Internet. TCP/IP was birthed into a world of expensive, rare mainframes &ndash; computers and Internet connections were scarce. Four billion unique IPs (i.e. <strong>2<sup>32</sup> = 4,294,967,296</strong>) must have seemed vastly beyond sufficient at the time. Yet as I write this in early 2014, it&rsquo;s worth noting that China alone has <a href="http://ben-evans.com/benedictevans/2014/3/12/700m-smartphones-tablets-in-china">700 million</a> active smartphones and tablets, most of which consume a IPv4 address. We&rsquo;re hitting the wall.</p>

<h3>IPv6</h3>

<p>IPv6, by contrast, skips over 64 bits and uses 128-bits for addressing. This yields <strong>2<sup>128</sup></strong> possible addresses: an unfathomably huge number. <strong>2<sup>128</sup></strong> written <a href="https://www.wolframalpha.com/input/?i=2%5E128">in full</a> has thirty-nine decimal digits, or can be abbreviated as <em>340 billion billion billion billion</em>, if you prefer.</p>

<p>While I have great faith in the ability of humanity to <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tragedy_of_the_commons">squander</a> a seemingly-endless resource, it is worth reflecting on the sheer scale of this number. The surface area of the Earth is <strong>510,072,000 km<sup>2</sup></strong>, or, less usefully, <strong>5.101 × 10<sup>20</sup> square-millimeters</strong>. <strong>2<sup>128</sup></strong> is so large that each square millimeter of area on the Earth&rsquo;s surface could <a href="https://www.wolframalpha.com/input/?i=2%5E128+%2F+5.101e20">support</a> <strong>667,000,000,000,000,000</strong> unique IPv6 addresses! Not in aggregate &ndash; that number of addresses exists for <em>each and every</em> square millimeter on the Earth, ocean and land alike!</p>

<p>Of course, in practice the IPv6 address space will likely not be allocated cleanly &ndash; various countries and corporations will likely receive an undeservedly large allocation; blocks may sit unused and reserved, etc. But it seems to me that no matter how poorly IPv6 is stewarded &ndash; its massive, planetary scale allows for truly indefinite room to grow. With IPv6<sup id="fnref:6"><a href="#fn:6" rel="footnote">6</a></sup> the wall seems, to me, to be unreachable with certainty.</p>

<p><em>(It will be especially interesting for me to read this in a decade or two.)</em></p>
<div class="footnotes">
<hr/>
<ol>
<li id="fn:1">
<p>There is apparently some <a href="http://en.wikiquote.org/wiki/Bill_Gates#Misattributed">doubt</a> as to the veracity of the actual attribution to Gates &ndash; but the point stands &ndash; everyone in tech has heard a form of this sentiment expressed.<a href="#fnref:1" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
<li id="fn:2">
<p>Well, it used to be ubiquitous (and unassailable!). The rise of <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/ARM_architecture">ARM</a> (like so much in the tech world since 2007, blame the iPhone) has been fascinating to witness.<a href="#fnref:2" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
<li id="fn:3">
<p>I&rsquo;m not too sure how the actual transition process is going. Things have seemed awfully quiet on that front since <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/World_IPv6_Day_and_World_IPv6_Launch_Day">World IPv6 Day</a> in 2011&hellip;<a href="#fnref:3" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
<li id="fn:4">
<p>Both of which should give anyone pause&hellip;<a href="#fnref:4" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
<li id="fn:5">
<p>Clever tricks such as <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Network_address_translation">NAT</a> ensure that machines in a household or business don&rsquo;t consume one public address each. As far as I&rsquo;m aware, mobile phones on a data network always consume one public address.<a href="#fnref:5" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
<li id="fn:6">
<p>Unless, of course, we decide that every <strong>N<sub>2</sub></strong> molecule on Earth needs to be addressable!<a href="#fnref:6" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
</ol>
</div>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[A Robust Photo Workflow]]></title>
    <link href="http://liggat.org/2014/03/20/a-robust-photo-workflow/"/>
    <updated>2014-03-20T18:11:09-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://liggat.org/2014/03/20/a-robust-photo-workflow</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>With the proliferation of smartphones, most people now have an excellent camera with them at all times, and are taking many more photographs per year than ever before.<!--more--></p>

<p>However, the current state of photo management on contemporary desktop and mobile operating systems is, frankly, abysmal. Apple, previously the standards-bearer in this arena through the mid-2000s with their <a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=9046oXrm7f8">digital hub</a> strategy, seems to have lost interest in maintaining iPhoto and Aperture as serious photo asset management tools<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" rel="footnote">1</a></sup>. Adobe Lightroom is expensive, complex and unnecessary for most non-professional purposes. Everpix, sadly, <a href="http://www.theverge.com/2013/11/5/5039216/everpix-life-and-death-inside-the-worlds-best-photo-startup">failed</a> to build a business around photo management.</p>

<h3>Requirements</h3>

<p>So what&rsquo;s the answer? I wanted a way to manage my past and future photos with the following characteristics:</p>

<ol>
<li>Every photo in my collection (over 10,000 and counting since 2003), and every photo I take from now on, should be preserved by default in an archive with its <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Metadata">metadata</a> intact.</li>
<li>This archive should have a robust local and offsite backup strategy &ndash; photographs are irreplaceable, and their value to the creator increases with time.</li>
<li>This archive should be as futureproof as possible &ndash; I want to be able to view my photos at any point in the future regardless of device, machine migration, etc.</li>
<li>I should have the ability to view any photo in my collection from a mobile device, i.e. my iPhone or iPad, without having it cached locally.</li>
<li>It should be painless and hassle-free to add new photos into the archive, and thus the backup process.</li>
</ol>


<p>Inspired by <a href="http://www.macstories.net/tutorials/my-photo-management-workflow-early-2014/">Federico Viticci</a>, I&rsquo;ve migrated my photo library to a new system and ongoing process that works really well for me.</p>

<h3>iPhoto => Files &amp; Directories</h3>

<p>Requirement 3, at a stroke, entirely disqualifies database-based applications<sup id="fnref:2"><a href="#fn:2" rel="footnote">2</a></sup> like iPhoto. As my accumulated photo library was sitting in the increasingly-creaky iPhoto, the first step was to export the original <code>.jpg</code> files. The archive is therefore maintained as a set of files and directories going forward, and is thus highly future-proof.</p>

<p>The single most critical piece of metadata about a photograph is its creation date. Without this, it is inordinately difficult to find a particular photo, or preserve a sense of the original chronology of a series.</p>

<p>Unfortunately, file system metadata is insufficient as a repository for this signal. Machine migrations, underlying file system changes, and general <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Software_rot">bit rot</a> conspire to render this inadequate and fragile. Therefore, it makes sense to encode a photograph&rsquo;s creation date, available in the exif data, right inside its filename.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.sno.phy.queensu.ca/~phil/exiftool/">Exiftool</a>, available in <a href="http://brew.sh/">Homebrew for OS X</a> is a great way to achieve this. After exporting from iPhoto, I was able to rename each file:</p>

<pre><code>exiftool "-FileName&lt;CreateDate" -d "%Y-%m-%d_%H-%M-%S%%-c.%%le" export
</code></pre>

<h3>Binning the Files</h3>

<p>The above operation resulted in a directory with 10,000 <code>.jpg</code> files with an <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Iso8601#General_principles">ISO8601</a>-like filename, e.g.: <code>2011-02-03_16-12-11.jpg</code>. A bit unwieldy, but chronological and consistent. The next step was to separate these files by month, which I accomplished with a simple bit of Ruby (original on <a href="https://gist.github.com/dliggat/9677631">GitHub</a>):</p>

<figure class='code'><figcaption><span>photo_bin.rb: A ruby script to bin photos by year-month directories </span></figcaption>
<div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
<span class='line-number'>3</span>
<span class='line-number'>4</span>
<span class='line-number'>5</span>
<span class='line-number'>6</span>
<span class='line-number'>7</span>
<span class='line-number'>8</span>
<span class='line-number'>9</span>
<span class='line-number'>10</span>
<span class='line-number'>11</span>
<span class='line-number'>12</span>
<span class='line-number'>13</span>
<span class='line-number'>14</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class='rb'><span class='line'><span class="no">Dir</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">glob</span> <span class="s2">&quot;</span><span class="si">#{</span><span class="n">root_dir</span><span class="si">}</span><span class="s2">/*.jpg&quot;</span> <span class="k">do</span> <span class="o">|</span><span class="n">file</span><span class="o">|</span>
</span><span class='line'>  <span class="n">match</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="sr">/.*?(\d\d\d\d)-(\d\d)-\d\d_\d\d-\d\d-\d\d.*\.jpg$/</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">match</span> <span class="n">file</span>
</span><span class='line'>  <span class="k">raise</span> <span class="no">ArgumentError</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">new</span> <span class="s2">&quot;File did not match: </span><span class="si">#{</span><span class="n">file</span><span class="si">}</span><span class="s2">&quot;</span> <span class="k">unless</span> <span class="n">match</span>
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'>  <span class="n">year</span>           <span class="o">=</span> <span class="n">match</span><span class="o">[</span><span class="mi">1</span><span class="o">]</span>
</span><span class='line'>  <span class="n">month</span>          <span class="o">=</span> <span class="n">match</span><span class="o">[</span><span class="mi">2</span><span class="o">]</span>
</span><span class='line'>  <span class="n">month_abbr</span>     <span class="o">=</span> <span class="ss">Date</span><span class="p">:</span><span class="ss">:MONTHNAMES</span><span class="o">[</span><span class="n">month</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">to_i</span><span class="o">][</span><span class="mi">0</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">.</span><span class="mi">2</span><span class="o">]</span>
</span><span class='line'>  <span class="n">photo_dir_name</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="s2">&quot;</span><span class="si">#{</span><span class="n">year</span><span class="si">}</span><span class="s2">-</span><span class="si">#{</span><span class="n">month</span><span class="si">}</span><span class="s2">-</span><span class="si">#{</span><span class="n">month_abbr</span><span class="si">}</span><span class="s2">&quot;</span>
</span><span class='line'>  <span class="n">photo_abs_dir</span>  <span class="o">=</span> <span class="no">File</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">join</span> <span class="n">root_dir</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">photo_dir_name</span>
</span><span class='line'>  <span class="n">abs_file</span>       <span class="o">=</span> <span class="no">File</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">expand_path</span> <span class="n">file</span>
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'>  <span class="no">Dir</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">mkdir</span> <span class="n">photo_abs_dir</span> <span class="k">unless</span> <span class="no">Dir</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">exist?</span> <span class="n">photo_abs_dir</span>
</span><span class='line'>  <span class="no">FileUtils</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">mv</span> <span class="n">abs_file</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">photo_abs_dir</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="k">end</span>
</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<h3>Storage, Backup, Viewing</h3>

<p>I decided that the best place to actually store this [so-far] 55GB archive was on Google Drive. This has a few benefits:</p>

<ul>
<li><strong>Cheap</strong>: At $2 per month for 100GB of storage as of the <a href="http://googleblog.blogspot.ca/2014/03/save-more-with-google-drive.html">recent price drop</a>, it&rsquo;s hard to argue with the price.</li>
<li><strong>Local and Offsite Backup</strong>: These files live locally in <code>~/GoogleDrive</code> and therefore get subsumed into my wireless home network backups, but also have a disaster-mitigating copy on the cloud.</li>
<li><strong>Mobile Viewing</strong>: The iOS Google Drive app has quietly become a really high-quality piece of iOS software. It&rsquo;s a capable photo viewing app, and easily satisfies the mobile-viewing requirement (though I&rsquo;d like to see <a href="http://unboundapp.com/">Unbound</a> support it eventually also).</li>
</ul>


<p><img class="center" src="http://liggat.org/images/2014/gd.png" width="600" title="'Google Drive'" ></p>

<h3>Dealing with New Photos</h3>

<p>All of this so far covers requirements 1 through 4 splendidly. However, it&rsquo;s all a bit pointless if new photos aren&rsquo;t subsumed into this system on a hassle-free, ongoing basis. The final puzzle piece is also the most convoluted, but so far it seems to be holding up nicely:</p>

<ol>
<li>Take advantage of Dropbox&rsquo;s Camera Upload<sup id="fnref:3"><a href="#fn:3" rel="footnote">3</a></sup> functionality to send new photos over WiFi from my iPhone to the <code>~/Dropbox/Camera Uploads</code> directory on my Mac. This will happen in the background occasionally without any intervention from me, or I can trigger it manually whenever I want. Of course, <code>.jpg</code> files from other cameras can be placed here also<sup id="fnref:4"><a href="#fn:4" rel="footnote">4</a></sup>.</li>
<li>Use <a href="http://www.noodlesoft.com/hazel">Hazel</a> to watch that directory and segregate iOS screenshots (no need to archive those) and videos (I&rsquo;m still deciding how they should be handled), and then rename all <code>.jpg</code> files to the ISO8601-style format above. In this case, given the recency, it is reasonable to rely on the file metadata to encode the creation date in the filename.</li>
<li>Again with Hazel watching that directory, send those renamed files to <code>~/GoogleDrive/Photos</code>.</li>
<li>Another Hazel rule watching <code>~/GoogleDrive/Photos</code> will &ldquo;sort into subfolders&rdquo; and place each file into its appropriate year-month directory (e.g. <code>2014-03-Mar</code>), creating that directory if necessary.</li>
</ol>


<p><img class="center" src="http://liggat.org/images/2014/hazel.png" width="600" title="'Hazel'" ></p>

<p>That&rsquo;s it! The archive is consistent, future-proof, viewable and has a strong backup-strategy &ndash; and all new photos from now on have a frictionless pathway into it.</p>

<p>While I&rsquo;m happy with this system for me (and eventually I&rsquo;ll roll it out to my family) Apple, Google, Microsoft, et al really need to solve this problem for their customers. Photos are precious, and people, as a rule, are far worse at ensuring the longevity of bits than paper.</p>
<div class="footnotes">
<hr/>
<ol>
<li id="fn:1">
<p>They were never very good, anyway.<a href="#fnref:1" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
<li id="fn:2">
<p>It is generally a bad idea to rely on these type of programs if you care about accessing your data in the distant future. It will likely be difficult, or at best inconvenient, to read a circa-2014 iPhoto library in 2024. I make an <a href="http://liggat.org/2013/07/21/paperless/">exception</a> in the case of Evernote.<a href="#fnref:2" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
<li id="fn:3">
<p>Ideally I wouldn&rsquo;t be relying on two separate cloud-storage providers, but the combination of Google Drive pricing and Dropbox functionality is compelling. Future changes will be easy, anyhow, depending on how the storage market evolves.<a href="#fnref:3" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
<li id="fn:4">
<p>So far this doesn&rsquo;t really apply, as the only camera I use is my iPhone 5s. I hung up my SLR a few years ago.<a href="#fnref:4" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
</ol>
</div>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[@liggs Is Now @dliggat]]></title>
    <link href="http://liggat.org/2014/02/20/at-liggs-is-now-at-dliggat/"/>
    <updated>2014-02-20T20:20:23-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://liggat.org/2014/02/20/at-liggs-is-now-at-dliggat</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I&rsquo;ve changed my Twitter handle from @liggs to <a href="https://twitter.com/dliggat">@dliggat</a>, as part of a general username consolidation that&rsquo;s been nagging me for a while. I figured it was worth marking the <em>occasion</em> with a site entry, given how much I use Twitter.</p>

<!--more-->


<p>In case you&rsquo;re wondering, it&rsquo;s quite easy to swap two Twitter handles with a <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Swap_(computer_science)#Using_a_temporary_variable">3-way switch</a>, so long as you control both handles.</p>

<ol>
<li>In one browser, I opened <strong>@dliggat</strong> to <a href="https://twitter.com/settings/account">https://twitter.com/settings/account</a></li>
<li>In a seperate browser (Chrome instead of Safari in my case, but a <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Privacy_mode">private browser</a> session would work also) I also opened <strong>@liggs</strong> to <a href="https://twitter.com/settings/account">https://twitter.com/settings/account</a></li>
<li>I renamed <strong>@dliggat</strong> to <em>@dliggattemp</em>. Once this is confirmed, the next two steps need to be completed as quickly as possible.</li>
<li>I renamed <strong>@liggs</strong> to <strong>@dliggat</strong>.</li>
<li>I renamed <em>@dliggattemp</em> to <strong>@liggs</strong>.</li>
</ol>


<p>It all worked out without a hitch. <a href="https://twitter.com/dliggat">@dliggat</a> it is from now on.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Taking a Stand With Work]]></title>
    <link href="http://liggat.org/2014/02/16/taking-a-stand-with-work/"/>
    <updated>2014-02-16T07:21:59-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://liggat.org/2014/02/16/taking-a-stand-with-work</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Being a so-called <em>knowledge worker</em> comes with at least one very substantial downside: there is a fundamental lack of physical activity built into the job<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" rel="footnote">1</a></sup>, and long sedentary periods are commonplace. I&rsquo;ve been very cognizant of this for a long time, and do my best to actively combat it with daily exercise, gym routines, etc. While those help substantially, they do not alter the basic reality that one tends to be sitting in a chair for many hours, staring at a screen.</p>

<!--more-->


<p>To make matters worse, there appears to be <a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2011/04/17/magazine/mag-17sitting-t.html?_r=0">growing evidence</a> that excessive sitting is pathological all on its own:</p>

<blockquote><p>Sitting, it would seem, is an independent pathology. Being sedentary for nine hours a day at the office is bad for your health whether you go home and watch television afterward or hit the gym. It is bad whether you are morbidly obese or marathon-runner thin. “Excessive sitting,” Dr. Levine says, “is a lethal activity.”</p></blockquote>

<p>Whether or not that hypothesis is even true &ndash; inherently it simply doesn&rsquo;t <em>feel</em> good to sit this much<sup id="fnref:2"><a href="#fn:2" rel="footnote">2</a></sup>. Two weeks ago, I decided to switch to a standing desk, and I don&rsquo;t think I will ever look back.</p>

<h3>The Trial Run</h3>

<p>A purpose-built <a href="http://thewirecutter.com/reviews/the-best-standing-desks/">standing desk</a> will run you around $1,000, or more. These high end models tend to be motorized and can memorize different configurations &ndash; so you can mode-switch between the ideal standing height and the ideal sitting height. While that sounds great, and while the cost can be easily justified on both amortization as well as &lsquo;mattress logic&rsquo;<sup id="fnref:3"><a href="#fn:3" rel="footnote">3</a></sup> grounds &ndash; it&rsquo;s a lot of money to drop without even knowing if it&rsquo;s a good fit. Enter, the trial run.</p>

<p>Via <a href="http://chambersdaily.com/bradleychambers/2013/11/21/building-a-standing-desk-on-the-cheap">Bradley Chambers</a>, I found <a href="http://iamnotaprogrammer.com/Ikea-Standing-desk-for-22-dollars.html">Colin Nederkoorn&rsquo;s</a> instructions for building a standing desk with $22 USD ($30 CAD up here) worth of Ikea parts. I ordered these same parts and followed Colin&rsquo;s directions to build the basic framework that sits on top of my existing desk. The result:</p>

<p><img class="center" src="http://liggat.org/images/2014/desk.jpg" width="500" title="'Homemade Standing Desk'" ></p>

<p>It&rsquo;s not the most attractive thing in the world, and does not permit a quick mode-switch between sitting and standing &ndash; but it&rsquo;s hard to argue with the cost of entry as a way to trial the experience of a standing-desk.</p>

<h3>The Result</h3>

<p>I&rsquo;ve used this now for two weeks. Without exaggeration, I cannot ever see myself going back to a standard desk arrangement. The first couple of days were a bit more tiring than usual, as my body adjusted to the change. A few days later, it feels completely natural. Quite apart from the physical benefit of standing versus sitting, I&rsquo;ve found that standing imparts a greater sense of purpose to my current task: as if I&rsquo;m subconsciously striving towards completion before fatigue can arrive.</p>

<p>In practice, I don&rsquo;t actually stand the whole day &ndash; perhaps only 75%. I have meals sitting down of course, and take a few short sitting breaks during the day &ndash; usually at periods of planning or design. This has the secondary benefit of taking me away from the keyboard to exclusively focus on design itself.</p>

<p>In the medium-term timeframe, I&rsquo;ll almost certainly switch to a &lsquo;real&rsquo; standing desk. For now, this is a great way to work.</p>

<h3>Social Norms?</h3>

<p>I work from home and have the luxury of arranging my own workspace. I could work from an inflatable rubber-dinghy if I so chose, and there would be nothing stopping me from doing so.</p>

<p>Most people are not this lucky. They work at the desk and chair that their employer provides, and it would be frankly odd to be the lone oddball standing beside the Ikea contraption<sup id="fnref:4"><a href="#fn:4" rel="footnote">4</a></sup>, as everyone else hunches over their desk. I can only hope that the dual forces of sitting-health-research, and remote-work-acceptance will drive us all towards more flexible, personal ergonomic arrangements.</p>
<div class="footnotes">
<hr/>
<ol>
<li id="fn:1">
<p>Unlike, say, an electrician or a nurse. Hat tip, little brother and little sister.<a href="#fnref:1" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
<li id="fn:2">
<p>Despite having a good Herman-Miller chair in my home office.<a href="#fnref:2" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
<li id="fn:3">
<p>&ldquo;You use this a lot so get a good one.&rdquo;<a href="#fnref:3" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
<li id="fn:4">
<p>Assuming &lsquo;Health &amp; Safety&rsquo; even let the thing in the front door, which is not necessarily probable.<a href="#fnref:4" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
</ol>
</div>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Navigating Canadian Cellular Number Portability (in 8 Easy Steps)]]></title>
    <link href="http://liggat.org/2014/01/30/navigating-canadian-cellular-number-portability/"/>
    <updated>2014-01-30T19:47:12-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://liggat.org/2014/01/30/navigating-canadian-cellular-number-portability</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Since 2007, Canadians have been afforded the right to migrate (&lsquo;port&rsquo;) their cellular <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pstn">PSTN</a> number with them when they switch to a new cellular operator. The legislation which enacted this brought to bear a small reduction in <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Switching_barriers">switching costs</a> in a &lsquo;market&rsquo;<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" rel="footnote">1</a></sup> widely reputed for hostility towards its customers, not to mention, [at the very least] <em>perceived</em> collusion among the operators themselves.<!--more--></p>

<p>Unfortunately, no matter which head of the <a href="https://www.google.ca/search?client=safari&amp;rls=en&amp;q=robelus">tripartite Cerberus</a> one ends up dealing with, this is far more hassle, and potentially more expensive, than it needs to be.</p>

<p>Cellular services are paid for one month in advance, and when you initiate a port, <em>no matter when you initiate it</em>, your current operator will attempt to bill you for one final advance month. The rationale, they say, is that they need thirty days of notice. This would be semi-reasonable if there were some official way to give that notice ahead of time. There isn&rsquo;t. The only way, in their view, to give that notice is through the port itself. So you&rsquo;re stuck paying for a month of service that cannot actually be delivered.</p>

<p>Let me repeat that: they demand thirty days of notice, but won&rsquo;t let you provide it in any way other than that which results in receiving a bill for an unnecessary month of undeliverable service. This is, obviously, bullshit. Here&rsquo;s how to get around it<sup id="fnref:2"><a href="#fn:2" rel="footnote">2</a></sup>:</p>

<ol>
<li>Ensure your contract is over, and you don&rsquo;t owe an early-termination fee for the device subsidy you likely received two or three years ago. e.g. if you signed up on <code>2010-03-13</code> with a three year contract, by <code>2013-03-14</code> you&rsquo;re definitely in the clear.</li>
<li>Work out your billing cycle. This may or may not be explicitly stated on your invoice, but it generally covers your invoice date (e.g. the 15th of the month) plus 30 days.</li>
<li>Two days before your invoice date (e.g. April 13th), phone your operator and tell them you are intending to cancel. You&rsquo;ll probably need to sit through a barrage of retention offers. <strong>It&rsquo;s important that they don&rsquo;t actually cancel right then</strong> &ndash; you may lose the service and number. Tell the retention agent that you intend to cancel, but that you will phone back if you wish to accept the retention offer. Record the agent&rsquo;s name, call reference number, and the current date/time.</li>
<li>Use your phone as normal for another month.</li>
<li>Again two days before your invoice date (e.g. now May 13th) sign up for service with your new operator (hopefully a better deal than your current one) and have them initiate a port of the number.</li>
<li>Your previous operator will receive notice of the cancellation, and will issue a final bill covering any overage plus service from May 15th plus 30 days. This is the service they cannot actually provide, yet still bill for.</li>
<li>Now the real fun begins: phone the original operator to complain about the bill for undeliverable service. They will tell you that they require thirty days of notice for cancellations. Mention your &lsquo;notice&rsquo; call &ndash; done a month ago in step (3). They will say it doesn&rsquo;t count. Escalate to a manager. Patiently explain that the company is billing for something that it cannot possibly provide (the number is gone). Prepare to be the recipient of a deeply-flawed, logically-inconsistent argument about why it makes sense to be billed for this. End the call in despair, but again, ensure to record the agent&rsquo;s name, call reference number, and the current date/time.</li>
<li>Visit the <a href="https://www.ccts-cprst.ca/en/complaints/complaint-form">CCTS</a> (the Commissioner for Complaints for Telecommunications Services). Create a new complaint. Explain the timeline<sup id="fnref:3"><a href="#fn:3" rel="footnote">3</a></sup> of events, and be sure to mention the particular timestamps and call reference numbers.</li>
</ol>


<p>In a few days time &ndash; expect to receive an incredibly cordial and understanding call from the operator&rsquo;s Office of the President or similar Ombudsman-type department. This person will explain that the other agents were mistaken, and that you are in the right. They will happily nullify the &lsquo;erroneous&rsquo; charge and graciously thank you for your time.</p>

<p>This is <strong>nuts</strong> of course &ndash; but this elaborate dance is what&rsquo;s required of you if you want to port without paying for two sets of service for a month. One could be forgiven for believing this was an isolated incident, <a href="https://www.google.ca/search?q=rogers+port+ccts&amp;oq=rogers+port+ccts">but it definitely isn&rsquo;t</a>. Hell &ndash; I learned how to do all this by piecing it together from other anecdotes online.</p>

<p>There&rsquo;s no panacea to fixing telecom in Canada<sup id="fnref:4"><a href="#fn:4" rel="footnote">4</a></sup>, but I&rsquo;m happy to accept small victories where I can.</p>
<div class="footnotes">
<hr/>
<ol>
<li id="fn:1">
<p>I use the term loosely.<a href="#fnref:1" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
<li id="fn:2">
<p>I went through this whole dance recently with Rogers, but singling them out only really serves to substantiate the fiction that these are three separate, competitive enterprises. There&rsquo;s virtually no daylight between the three operators on most issues of any import.<a href="#fnref:2" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
<li id="fn:3">
<p>Pro tip: <a href="https://evernote.com">Evernote</a> is an excellent tool for tracking things like this.<a href="#fnref:3" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
<li id="fn:4">
<p>You can remove the protectionism, but Canada&rsquo;s size, geography, and low population density guarantee it will always be a difficult country when it comes to infrastructure.<a href="#fnref:4" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
</ol>
</div>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[In Charge of Windows 9]]></title>
    <link href="http://liggat.org/2014/01/15/in-charge-of-windows-9/"/>
    <updated>2014-01-15T14:23:19-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://liggat.org/2014/01/15/in-charge-of-windows-9</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Peter, an old UBC classmate and frequent co-banterer on Twitter, randomly posed an interesting question to me earlier today:<!--more--></p>

<blockquote class="twitter-tweet" lang="en"><p><a href="https://twitter.com/liggs">@liggs</a> Serious question: if you were put in charge of Windows 9 tomorrow, what would you do with it?</p>&mdash; Peter J. Cavan (@PJCavan) <a href="https://twitter.com/PJCavan/statuses/423564952683560960">January 15, 2014</a></blockquote>


<script async src="http://liggat.org//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"></script>


<p>I immediately replied that I think this is the single most difficult strategic question in the tech industry today, moreso even than the challenge over at BlackBerry Inc. The response, assuming I can come up with one worth the bits it&rsquo;s written on, will definitely not fit into 140-characters. Hence, a blog post.</p>

<p>The unlucky soul in charge of birthing Windows 9 has the following difficult truths to contend with:</p>

<ol>
<li>Selling operating systems to OEM-device manufacturers, as a business, is essentially dying. It&rsquo;s a sustainment business at best. This is the business model on which Windows ascended, and it&rsquo;s come to the end. There are now really only two ways to make money as an OS vendor &ndash; you wrap it in aluminum and glass and sell the whole device (Apple), or you give it away and own the market for the user&rsquo;s attention (Google). Microsoft has had a few punts at the Apple approach in the form of Zune and Surface, but has yet to set the world on fire doing this.</li>
<li>Windows 8 has not been well received by its userbase, to put it mildly. I haven&rsquo;t actually used it myself, but in terms of reception, <em>Vista 2.0</em>, does not seem an unfair moniker. Aside from the bold user-interface change<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" rel="footnote">1</a></sup>, apparently unloved by many, the RT/Pro distinction is <em>confusing as hell</em>.</li>
<li>Mobile and tablets happened. Anyone still rattling on that iOS (or Android) is unsuitable for <em>real work™</em> is missing the point &ndash; mobile devices unbundle the Internet from the PC. Ten years ago, it was axiomatic that if you wanted to participate in online activities &ndash; Facebook, email and so on &ndash; you needed a PC, and that usually meant a Windows PC. <em>Tons</em> of PC use cases are being chipped away by more personal mobile devices, and that trend is only going to increase.</li>
<li>All of that might not be so bad if Microsoft was a major player in mobile &ndash; but it isn&rsquo;t. Mobile as it stands is a duopoly between iOS and Android, and I&rsquo;m far from convinced there&rsquo;s room for a third stack. The undoubted merits of Microsoft&rsquo;s mobile and tablet efforts in the form of Windows Phone and Surface notwithstanding &ndash; these are not yet products with a non-trivial market-share, let alone mind-share.</li>
<li>Anyone doubting any of the above need only refer to <a href="http://ben-evans.com/benedictevans/2013/7/20/the-irrelevance-of-microsoft">Microsoft&rsquo;s share</a> of Internet-connected devices: 90% down to 20% in just a few years.</li>
</ol>


<p>So what&rsquo;s a chief product manager of Windows 9 to do? I can&rsquo;t begin to do Peter&rsquo;s question justice, but I can offer a few humble suggestions:</p>

<ul>
<li>Windows 8 was a noble though misguided attempt to be all things to all people: multiple concepts all resident within a single device. However, we live in a <a href="http://mattgemmell.com/the-unacknowledged-compromise/">multi-device</a> world now. The machine one uses for AutoCAD design work with a mouse and keyboard needn&rsquo;t also be the same one that has a touch-enabled Twitter client in another layer. Windows 9 should therefore build upon the best parts of the generally-well-liked Windows 7, in the same way that, say, OS X Mavericks iterated upon OS X Mountain Lion &ndash; <em>without</em> attempting to change the paradigm. Better power-management, UI refinement, etc is the order of the day here.</li>
<li>Forget touch. Windows has always been about keyboard/mouse input devices, and grafting a touch layer on top is pointless. No one wants to use touch on a laptop, or God-forbid, a desktop, anyway.</li>
<li>Office remains an important business for Microsoft, and an important tool<sup id="fnref:2"><a href="#fn:2" rel="footnote">2</a></sup> for a ton of people. They are leaving a lot of money and future relevance on the table by not porting a first-class version to iOS (and Android), but even if they do &ndash; Windows should exist to provide a preeminent environment for complex applications like Office, and play to its keyboard/mouse/file-system strengths.</li>
<li>This really shouldn&rsquo;t need to be said, but native PDF viewing in Windows is an idea whose time has come.</li>
</ul>


<p>Whoever ends up driving this project has my well wishes (and sympathies). From where I stand, it&rsquo;s hard not to see it as a <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sisyphus">Sisyphean</a> task.</p>
<div class="footnotes">
<hr/>
<ol>
<li id="fn:1">
<p>I applauded the vision when Metro was first announced, but it was clear from the beginning that the outcome would either be spectacularly good or spectacularly bad, with very little room for an outcome in the middle.<a href="#fnref:1" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
<li id="fn:2">
<p>Well Excel is peerless anyway; I&rsquo;m less certain that anything other than organizational inertia keeps Word and PowerPoint in such widespread use.<a href="#fnref:2" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
</ol>
</div>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Criticize Real-World NOOPs]]></title>
    <link href="http://liggat.org/2014/01/08/criticize-real-world-noops/"/>
    <updated>2014-01-08T20:37:42-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://liggat.org/2014/01/08/criticize-real-world-noops</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>In the world of computation, a <em>NOOP</em> (<em>No-Op</em>eration) is an instruction that has zero effect on the state of the machine. The term originally hails from the esoteric world of CPU-architecture and instruction-sets<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" rel="footnote">1</a></sup>, but the term is also used semi-colloquially as programmer shorthand for <strong>&lsquo;this achieves nothing&rsquo;</strong>.<!--more--></p>

<p>A very simple example in code might be in setting a variable to the difference of itself and zero (<code>x = x - 0</code>), but they tend, as a rule, to not be so obvious. On first glance, they <em>look</em> like useful work.</p>

<p>Programmers regard NOOPs with suspicion. Good code reviewers will identify them, question their existence, and  demand exceptional justification for their continued presence. They are unwelcome in quality software not for their outcome &ndash; they do nothing after all &ndash; but because they <em>sow confusion</em>. On first glance, they appear to have a purpose; they subconsciously assuage concerns that might otherwise have been raised in their absence. Many a pernicious bug can be traced back to a NOOP that misled its programmers. A NOOP is a facade: an illusion of real work being performed.</p>

<p>Lately I&rsquo;ve been thinking that the term might be applicable in the real-world also. Consider this story:</p>

<h4><a href="http://rt.com/news/france-google-fine-privacy-339/">France hands down data privacy fine to Google</a></h4>

<blockquote><p>French data protection watchdog CNIL fined Google 150,000 euros ($204,000) for ignoring its three-month deadline to align its
practice of tracking and storing user information with the country’s law.</p></blockquote>

<p>I&rsquo;m not commenting on<sup id="fnref:2"><a href="#fn:2" rel="footnote">2</a></sup>, or even particularly interested in this French legal ruling. That&rsquo;s for France and Google Inc to work out.</p>

<p>But it seems to me that regardless of the fine&rsquo;s merit &ndash; imposing a €150,000 fine on a company which earns that amount in revenue every <em>two minutes</em><sup id="fnref:3"><a href="#fn:3" rel="footnote">3</a></sup>, very closely fits the definition of a NOOP. It is the act of doing nothing masquerading as the act of doing something of significance. To an extremely close approximation, it is the judicial equivalent of subtracting zero from an integer.</p>

<p>In its article, RT makes no effort to contextualize this, and it&rsquo;s not just a failing of theirs &ndash; it&rsquo;s frankly rare in news media. This is precisely the opposite of the programmer mentality: NOOPs are always to be identified as such, and their presence criticized. The world would greatly benefit from a culture that does a better job in <strong>pointing out pointlessness</strong>.</p>
<div class="footnotes">
<hr/>
<ol>
<li id="fn:1">
<p>An idle CPU can&rsquo;t actually do nothing, so they would traditionally just repeatedly execute the NOOP instruction in the absence of actual work to do. I suspect that&rsquo;s an oversimplification circa-2014 with the vast amounts of research that have gone into processor energy-efficiency.<a href="#fnref:1" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
<li id="fn:2">
<p>Disclosure: I&rsquo;m an ex-Google employee (departed on highly-amicable terms to pursue a Masters) and a long-time admirer of the firm, pre and post employment.<a href="#fnref:2" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
<li id="fn:3">
<p>Google has <a href="http://investor.google.com/financial/tables.html">yearly revenues</a> on the order of <code>$50,000,000,000</code>. There are <code>365 * 24 * 60 = 525,600</code> minutes per year. <code>$50B / 525.6k ~= $95k ~= €68k</code>. Two minutes revenue <code>~= €150k</code>.<a href="#fnref:3" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
</ol>
</div>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[A New Design]]></title>
    <link href="http://liggat.org/2013/12/24/a-new-design/"/>
    <updated>2013-12-24T18:14:09-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://liggat.org/2013/12/24/a-new-design</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I&rsquo;ve been using <a href="http://octopress.org">Octopress</a> as a blogging platform for over six months now, and can&rsquo;t recommend it enough for tech capable (or curious) writers. However, I&rsquo;ve never been fully happy with my minor adaptations to the default style. I finally got around to implementing an improved design.<!--more--></p>

<h3>Original</h3>

<p>My site started off looking like this:
<img class="center" src="http://liggat.org/images/2013/old-octopress-style.png" width="700" title="'Old'" ></p>

<p>It was by all means serviceable, but I was starting to tire of the excess <em>chrome</em> &ndash; the prominent header, the large nav-bar, and the unnecessary <em>Recent Posts</em> sidebar. Morever, despite numerous tweaks to the layout, colouring, and typography &ndash; it still instantly <em>looked</em> like an Octopress site<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" rel="footnote">1</a></sup>.</p>

<h3>Design Objectives</h3>

<p>I&rsquo;m not a UI designer, either by trade or by realistic-aspiration<sup id="fnref:2"><a href="#fn:2" rel="footnote">2</a></sup>. Still, I had a pretty good idea in mind what I wanted my home on the web to look like.</p>

<ul>
<li><strong>Content Focus</strong>: This site exists for one purpose &ndash; a place to store material that I write. Anything that&rsquo;s not written content distracts from that objective. Among other things, that means the large, colourful header needs to go.</li>
<li><strong>De-Octopress the UI</strong>: Octopress is the infrastructure for this site, and will be for the far-foreseeable future. That doesn&rsquo;t mean I need to rely on its default UI styling, and in fact, I&rsquo;d greatly prefer it didn&rsquo;t <em>look</em> like an Octopress site. I still want to rely on the basic Octopress layout though, as well as its <a href="http://coding.smashingmagazine.com/2011/01/12/guidelines-for-responsive-web-design/">responsive design</a>.</li>
<li><strong>Better Typography</strong>: I&rsquo;ve long been a little too zealous in observing the &lsquo;rule&rsquo; that <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sans-serif">sans-serif</a> headers should be paired with <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Serif">serif</a> body text. Accordingly, I initially used the serif Google Font <a href="https://www.google.com/fonts/specimen/Lora">Lora</a> for the body, but was never quite happy with the choice. Many blogs I read eschew serifs entirely, and the effect is well-suited to the content<sup id="fnref:3"><a href="#fn:3" rel="footnote">3</a></sup>.</li>
<li><strong>Better Footnote Styling</strong>: Chris Suave&rsquo;s excellent <a href="http://cmsauve.com/labs/bigfoot/">Bigfoot</a> footnote implementation is far superior to numeric in-page anchors. I wanted to replace the latter with the former (or similar).</li>
</ul>


<h3>Result</h3>

<p>With a bit of spare time over Christmas 2013, I hacked away at my blog&rsquo;s <a href="https://github.com/dliggat/dliggat.github.io">git repo</a> to shape the design. I&rsquo;m pretty happy with how it&rsquo;s turned out:</p>

<h4>Desktop Layout:</h4>

<p><img class="center" src="http://liggat.org/images/2013/new-octopress-style.png" width="700" title="'New'" ></p>

<h4>Mobile Layout:</h4>

<p><img class="center" src="http://liggat.org/images/2013/new-octopress-style-mobile.png" width="350" title="'New'" ></p>

<p>I&rsquo;m still a bit ambivalent about having comments at all, but otherwise, I&rsquo;m happy with how it looks. It&rsquo;ll be interesting to review these design decisions down the line.</p>
<div class="footnotes">
<hr/>
<ol>
<li id="fn:1">
<p>This style is instantly recognizable around various corners of the web &ndash; all deriving from the design on <a href="http://octopress.org">octopress.org</a> itself. The gradient and text-shadow on the nav-bar is a dead giveaway.<a href="#fnref:1" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
<li id="fn:2">
<p>I have <em>just</em> enough design knowledge to overcome the <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dunning%E2%80%93Kruger_effect">Dunning-Kruger effect</a>.<a href="#fnref:2" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
<li id="fn:3">
<p>i.e., we&rsquo;re not writing the New York Times here.<a href="#fnref:3" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
</ol>
</div>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Canadian Housing: Noting for Posterity]]></title>
    <link href="http://liggat.org/2013/12/15/canadian-housing-noting-for-posterity/"/>
    <updated>2013-12-15T08:52:00-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://liggat.org/2013/12/15/canadian-housing-noting-for-posterity</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I&rsquo;m posting the following chart from <a href="http://blog.bcaresearch.com/canadian-housing-the-bubble-debate">BCA Research</a> not for the purposes of persuasion, but rather, for posterity.<!--more--></p>

<p><img class="center http://www.google.ca" src="http://liggat.org/images/2013/Canada-Housing.gif" title="'Canada Housing'" ></p>

<p>If you have a sense of the historical economic similarity between Canada and the United States, understand the computation and significance of <code>price:rent</code> and <code>price:income</code> as housing valuation metrics, and yet still don&rsquo;t feel <em>even a flutter of anxiety</em> about the future of the Canadian housing market, and more importantly, the downstream economic and societal implications of a <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Regression_toward_the_mean">reversion to the mean</a> &ndash; then you&rsquo;re far beyond the power of my rhetoric to change your mind<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" rel="footnote">1</a></sup>.</p>

<p>As I write this, in late 2013, <a href="http://www.theglobeandmail.com/report-on-business/top-business-stories/canadas-housing-market-most-overvalued-in-the-world-deutsche-bank-says/article15878166/">Deutsche Bank</a> joins a growing list of spectators whose ranks include <a href="http://www.economist.com/news/finance-and-economics/21584361-america-surges-much-europe-sinks-mixed-messages">The Economist</a>, <a href="http://www.cnbc.com/id/101150382">Goldman-Sachs</a>, <a href="http://business.financialpost.com/2012/09/21/canada-heading-into-a-slow-motion-version-of-the-u-s-housing-bust-robert-shiller/">Robert Shiller</a>, the <a href="http://business.financialpost.com/2013/11/27/according-to-the-imf-canada-has-the-most-overvalued-housing-market-in-the-world/">IMF</a>, <a href="http://www.theglobeandmail.com/report-on-business/top-business-stories/nouriel-roubini-aka-dr-doom-warns-of-frothy-canadian-housing-market/article15807846/">Nouriel Roubini</a>, and <a href="http://ca.finance.yahoo.com/blogs/balance-sheet/paul-krugman-warns-canada-vulnerable-big-deleveraging-shock-183728127.html">Paul Krugman</a> &ndash; all of whom have expressed incredulity and/or concern in one form or another about the stratospheric valuations in the Canadian housing market.</p>

<p>My opinion, irrelevant and disinterested<sup id="fnref:2"><a href="#fn:2" rel="footnote">2</a></sup> though it may be, is very straightforward, and has been unchanged for several years now: <strong>this will end badly</strong>, for the <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Leverage_(finance)">leveraged</a> and unleveraged, alike. Just ask anyone from the Republic of Ireland. Or look a little closer to home &ndash; below the 49th Parallel.</p>

<p>Feel free to disagree with me<sup id="fnref:3"><a href="#fn:3" rel="footnote">3</a></sup>. Most Canadians do, at least as a default position. But if you do disagree, surely it&rsquo;s at least partially concerning to witness all this opposing consensus among weighty, if not necessarily clairvoyant, external parties?</p>
<div class="footnotes">
<hr/>
<ol>
<li id="fn:1">
<p>Or, quite possibly, you&rsquo;re subject to the phenomenon, originally noted by Upton Sinclair, that <em>it is difficult to get a man to understand something, when his salary depends on his not understanding it</em>.<a href="#fnref:1" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
<li id="fn:2">
<p>I really mean this &ndash; I&rsquo;m <a href="http://www.dailywritingtips.com/disinterested-not-the-same-as-uninterested">disinterested</a> (but not <em>uninterested</em> clearly, as all of this is deeply fascinating to me &ndash; in a train-wreck sort of way). I have no real stake in whether or not there&rsquo;s a massive housing bubble in Canada, other than the stake of preferring not to live in a country captured by the fallacious belief that trading real estate is the preeminent way to generate wealth.<a href="#fnref:2" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
<li id="fn:3">
<p>Keep in mind: it&rsquo;s possible to simultaneously {own property | need to buy it soon} and {find the status quo very concerning}.<a href="#fnref:3" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
</ol>
</div>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[A Minor Rant on Package Tracking]]></title>
    <link href="http://liggat.org/2013/11/30/a-minor-rant-on-package-tracking/"/>
    <updated>2013-11-30T23:11:00-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://liggat.org/2013/11/30/a-minor-rant-on-package-tracking</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I do a fair bit of online shopping<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" rel="footnote">1</a></sup>, and have done so for pretty much my entire credit-card-wielding life. It&rsquo;s a familiar ritual: every time, shortly after I&rsquo;ve clicked <code>Purchase</code>, an email arrives containing a linked phrase with roughly the following copy: <em>Click here to track your shipment</em>. <!--more-->And every time I receive that email, I dutifully click that link, only to be met with the following 404-esque response:</p>

<p><img class="center" src="http://liggat.org/images/2013/tracking.png" width="600" title="'tracking'" ></p>

<p>It does not seem to matter whether the year is 2005 or 2013, and whether the logistics handler in question is Canada Post, USPS, UPS, etc &ndash; this is invariably the experience. This is a minor but absolutely-nagging annoyance if you know anything about software. It does not need to be this way.</p>

<p>Subsequent to the buyer&rsquo;s order, the seller and the logistics handler must perform an asynchronous (with respect to the buyer) transaction in which, among other things, data is exchanged regarding the delivery to be executed. At some point in this process, the seller is provided with a tracking number for that delivery, which they happily relay to the buyer in the aforesaid email. Therefore, when the buyer excitedly clicks on the tracking link, they are performing a lookup of <strong>a record that is certain to exist somewhere on the logistics handler&rsquo;s systems</strong>, and yet are <em>told</em> it doesn&rsquo;t exist.</p>

<p>I imagine that at this point, given the opportunity, the CTO of one of these logistics handler outfits might loudly interject <em>&ldquo;Well, of course &ndash; but the consumer web frontend and the logistics backend are entirely separate systems that we need to batch transfer over, and because of our legacy&hellip; and because of our storage requirements&hellip; and because of our load balancing&hellip; and because of Sarbanes-Oxley&hellip; and&hellip;.&rdquo;</em></p>

<p>And I&rsquo;m sure these would all be perfectly justified reasons, within the infrastructure team of that firm. The point is though, I don&rsquo;t care <strong>why</strong> the tracker was <em>unable to find any results</em>. And neither does any other user. This is a bad experience, and they can, and should do better. A few suggestions, in increasing order of implementation complexity:</p>

<ol>
<li>Make a better <em>unable to find any results</em> page. Acknowledge that this is a new tracking number, and will be in the systems shortly. Provide a timeframe. Differentiate between new numbers, and erroneous ones (use a <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Checksum">checksumming</a> scheme in the numbers themselves if necessary).</li>
<li>Coordinate with the seller. Don&rsquo;t fire out emails containing tracking links until both the seller and the logistics handler agree that the delivery will be performed, a tracking number exists, and the tracking number is queryable. I don&rsquo;t want an email with a link that I can&rsquo;t use until some unspecified period has passed.</li>
<li>Build better infrastructure. It is well within the ability of humanity&rsquo;s current software engineering to run systems without such absurd temporal lags within a single organization&rsquo;s infrastructure. This is not an especially complex technical problem. If your logistics and web-query systems are entirely separate, and they take 6 hours to propagate records &ndash; get that 6 down to 5. Then to 4. Then to 3. Etc.</li>
</ol>


<p>Clearly, this is not an important concern in the grand scheme of the universe. Invariably, the links start working eventually, and the packages arrive. But the triviality is no reason to not demand a modicum of progress.</p>
<div class="footnotes">
<hr/>
<ol>
<li id="fn:1">
<p>I did even more when I lived in the USA. The selection and swiftness of delivery of online purchasing there is nothing short of remarkable, especially under Amazon Prime.<a href="#fnref:1" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
</ol>
</div>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
