<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Liggat.org]]></title>
  <link href="http://liggat.org/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://liggat.org/"/>
  <updated>2014-04-06T23:28:13-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://liggat.org/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Dave Liggat]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Name of Thrones]]></title>
    <link href="http://liggat.org/2014/04/06/the-name-of-thrones/"/>
    <updated>2014-04-06T13:37:29-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://liggat.org/2014/04/06/the-name-of-thrones</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Last summer, my better half and I spent some time in Scotland, the country of my birth. Departing from Edinburgh, and en route to Inverness, we went through Glencoe in the Scottish Highlands. Leaving aside the very real potential for bias on my part &ndash; Glencoe is a hauntingly beautiful place, with equally impactful history in its past.<!--more--></p>

<p><img class="center" src="http://liggat.org/images/2014/glencoe.jpg" width="500" title="'Glencoe'" ></p>

<p>George R.R. Martin is <a href="http://www.nerdist.com/2013/06/george-r-r-martin-explains-the-red-weddings-historical-roots/">well known</a> to have drawn inspiration for <strong>A Song of Ice and Fire</strong><sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" rel="footnote">1</a></sup> from aspects of this part of the world. Famously, the highly-significant and series-defining <em>Red Wedding</em><sup id="fnref:2"><a href="#fn:2" rel="footnote">2</a></sup> event parallels the heinous circumstances of the late-seventeenth century <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Massacre_of_Glencoe">Massacre of Glencoe</a>. Moreover, further North in Scotland is a region known as <a href="https://www.google.com/maps/search/wester+ross/@57.7018103,-5.6741077,11z">Wester Ross</a>.</p>

<p>With the fourth season of <strong>Game of Thrones</strong> underway today on HBO, this is a fairly relevant time to document my theory about the original series title; i.e. why is <strong>A Song of Ice and Fire</strong> named thusly?</p>

<p>Back in 2013, in Glencoe, our tour bus stopped at a small vantage point. An educational plaque–the sort you imagine gets put in place by a local historical society and promptly forgotten–was at the head of the vantage point and explained some of the local geology. Interestingly, in one corner of the plaque was the phrase <strong>&ldquo;Of Fire &hellip; and Ice&rdquo;</strong>: used inconspicuously as a section header for a paragraph about geological time:</p>

<p><img class="center" src="http://liggat.org/images/2014/sign.jpg" width="500" title="'The Plaque'" ></p>

<p>I have no idea if George R.R. Martin has ever spoken publicly about the origin of the series title. I have no idea if he&rsquo;s seen this plaque, and even if he has, whether he remembers it or not. But he clearly has a connection to the area, and it seems plausible to me that this little detail on this unassuming plaque, whether consciously or otherwise, somehow became the core of the title of his magnum opus.</p>
<div class="footnotes">
<hr/>
<ol>
<li id="fn:1">
<p><strong>A Song of Ice and Fire</strong> is, of course, the name of the <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/A_Song_of_Ice_and_Fire">series</a> of books for which <strong>A Game of Thrones</strong> is book one. HBO evidently felt that the latter made for a more palatable TV-series name (likely correct).<a href="#fnref:1" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
<li id="fn:2">
<p>Which occurred in the penultimate episode of the third season, or within book three, <strong>A Storm of Swords</strong>, if you prefer.<a href="#fnref:2" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
</ol>
</div>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Backup Strategy]]></title>
    <link href="http://liggat.org/2014/03/28/backup-strategy/"/>
    <updated>2014-03-28T10:40:39-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://liggat.org/2014/03/28/backup-strategy</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[IPv6: An Unreachable Wall?]]></title>
    <link href="http://liggat.org/2014/03/23/ipv6-an-unreachable-wall/"/>
    <updated>2014-03-23T15:55:48-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://liggat.org/2014/03/23/ipv6-an-unreachable-wall</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>In <a href="http://www.fiatlux.fm/pragmatic/16">episode 16</a> of <a href="https://twitter.com/fiatluxfm">Ben Alexander</a> and <a href="https://twitter.com/johnchidgey">John Chidgey&rsquo;s</a> excellent <a href="http://www.fiatlux.fm/pragmatic/">Pragmatic</a> podcast, the hosts touched upon the unfortunate tendency of organizations &amp; individuals to underanticipate the scale of future demands upon their designed technology.<!--more--></p>

<p>Examples of this phenomenon abound:</p>

<ul>
<li>The North American <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Public_switched_telephone_network">PSTN</a> seemed like a vast address space at the time of its inception, and yet I&rsquo;ve been through <a href="http://www.cbc.ca/news/canada/vancouver-gets-10-digit-dialing-1.275934">at least one</a> extension in my life, as fax machines and mobile phones consumed far more telephone numbers than was anticipated.</li>
<li>&ldquo;<em>640k [of computer memory] ought to be enough for anybody</em>&rdquo; &ndash; as famously attributed to Bill Gates<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" rel="footnote">1</a></sup>.</li>
<li>The ubiquitous Intel x86<sup id="fnref:2"><a href="#fn:2" rel="footnote">2</a></sup> CPU architecture use 32-bits for addressing locations in system memory; this imposes a hard theoretical 4GiB limit on memory size, which is meager by 2014 standards.</li>
<li><a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/IPv4">IPv4</a>, which uses <strong>32-bits</strong> to assign IP addresses (e.g. of the form <code>123.255.123.255</code>) to devices on the public Internet is insufficiently large of an address space to accommodate all future computing devices, and the world will need to transition<sup id="fnref:3"><a href="#fn:3" rel="footnote">3</a></sup> to <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/IPv6">IPv6</a> at some point.</li>
</ul>


<p>At some point, progress causes us to run into the limits imposed by these upper boundaries. John referred to this phenomenon as &ldquo;hitting the wall&rdquo;, and casted it as an inevitability for any technology.</p>

<p>I agree wholeheartedly, but one with one caveat. I know that history (and John Chidgey) are not on my side here<sup id="fnref:4"><a href="#fn:4" rel="footnote">4</a></sup>, but I&rsquo;m going to go on record with the following postulate: once we finally switch to it, <strong>IPv6 will be an unreachable wall; i.e. it will be sufficient indefinitely as an address space for Internet routing</strong>. That is to say &ndash; a limit exists, but humanity won&rsquo;t be able to reach it.</p>

<h3>IPv4</h3>

<p>My argument for this is strictly numerical. IPv4 uses 32-bits to uniquely identify devices<sup id="fnref:5"><a href="#fn:5" rel="footnote">5</a></sup> on the public Internet. TCP/IP was birthed into a world of expensive, rare mainframes &ndash; computers and Internet connections were scarce. Four billion unique IPs (i.e. <strong>2<sup>32</sup> = 4,294,967,296</strong>) must have seemed vastly beyond sufficient at the time. Yet as I write this in early 2014, it&rsquo;s worth noting that China alone has <a href="http://ben-evans.com/benedictevans/2014/3/12/700m-smartphones-tablets-in-china">700 million</a> active smartphones and tablets, most of which consume a IPv4 address. We&rsquo;re hitting the wall.</p>

<h3>IPv6</h3>

<p>IPv6, by contrast, skips over 64 bits and uses 128-bits for addressing. This yields <strong>2<sup>128</sup></strong> possible addresses: an unfathomably huge number. <strong>2<sup>128</sup></strong> written <a href="https://www.wolframalpha.com/input/?i=2%5E128">in full</a> has thirty-nine decimal digits, or can be abbreviated as <em>340 billion billion billion billion</em>, if you prefer.</p>

<p>While I have great faith in the ability of humanity to <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tragedy_of_the_commons">squander</a> a seemingly-endless resource, it is worth reflecting on the sheer scale of this number. The surface area of the Earth is <strong>510,072,000 km<sup>2</sup></strong>, or, less usefully, <strong>5.101 × 10<sup>20</sup> square-millimeters</strong>. <strong>2<sup>128</sup></strong> is so large that each square millimeter of area on the Earth&rsquo;s surface could <a href="https://www.wolframalpha.com/input/?i=2%5E128+%2F+5.101e20">support</a> <strong>667,000,000,000,000,000</strong> unique IPv6 addresses! Not in aggregate &ndash; that number of addresses exists for <em>each and every</em> square millimeter on the Earth, ocean and land alike!</p>

<p>Of course, in practice the IPv6 address space will likely not be allocated cleanly &ndash; various countries and corporations will likely receive an undeservedly large allocation; blocks may sit unused and reserved, etc. But it seems to me that no matter how poorly IPv6 is stewarded &ndash; its massive, planetary scale allows for truly indefinite room to grow. With IPv6<sup id="fnref:6"><a href="#fn:6" rel="footnote">6</a></sup> the wall seems, to me, to be unreachable with certainty.</p>

<p><em>(It will be especially interesting for me to read this in a decade or two.)</em></p>
<div class="footnotes">
<hr/>
<ol>
<li id="fn:1">
<p>There is apparently some <a href="http://en.wikiquote.org/wiki/Bill_Gates#Misattributed">doubt</a> as to the veracity of the actual attribution to Gates &ndash; but the point stands &ndash; everyone in tech has heard a form of this sentiment expressed.<a href="#fnref:1" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
<li id="fn:2">
<p>Well, it used to be ubiquitous (and unassailable!). The rise of <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/ARM_architecture">ARM</a> (like so much in the tech world since 2007, blame the iPhone) has been fascinating to witness.<a href="#fnref:2" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
<li id="fn:3">
<p>I&rsquo;m not too sure how the actual transition process is going. Things have seemed awfully quiet on that front since <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/World_IPv6_Day_and_World_IPv6_Launch_Day">World IPv6 Day</a> in 2011&hellip;<a href="#fnref:3" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
<li id="fn:4">
<p>Both of which should give anyone pause&hellip;<a href="#fnref:4" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
<li id="fn:5">
<p>Clever tricks such as <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Network_address_translation">NAT</a> ensure that machines in a household or business don&rsquo;t consume one public address each. As far as I&rsquo;m aware, mobile phones on a data network always consume one public address.<a href="#fnref:5" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
<li id="fn:6">
<p>Unless, of course, we decide that every <strong>N<sub>2</sub></strong> molecule on Earth needs to be addressable!<a href="#fnref:6" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
</ol>
</div>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[A Robust Photo Workflow]]></title>
    <link href="http://liggat.org/2014/03/20/a-robust-photo-workflow/"/>
    <updated>2014-03-20T21:11:09-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://liggat.org/2014/03/20/a-robust-photo-workflow</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>With the proliferation of smartphones, most people now have an excellent camera with them at all times, and are taking many more photographs per year than ever before.<!--more--></p>

<p>However, the current state of photo management on contemporary desktop and mobile operating systems is, frankly, abysmal. Apple, previously the standards-bearer in this arena through the mid-2000s with their <a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=9046oXrm7f8">digital hub</a> strategy, seems to have lost interest in maintaining iPhoto and Aperture as serious photo asset management tools<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" rel="footnote">1</a></sup>. Adobe Lightroom is expensive, complex and unnecessary for most non-professional purposes. Everpix, sadly, <a href="http://www.theverge.com/2013/11/5/5039216/everpix-life-and-death-inside-the-worlds-best-photo-startup">failed</a> to build a business around photo management.</p>

<h3>Requirements</h3>

<p>So what&rsquo;s the answer? I wanted a way to manage my past and future photos with the following characteristics:</p>

<ol>
<li>Every photo in my collection (over 10,000 and counting since 2003), and every photo I take from now on, should be preserved by default in an archive with its <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Metadata">metadata</a> intact.</li>
<li>This archive should have a robust local and offsite backup strategy &ndash; photographs are irreplaceable, and their value to the creator increases with time.</li>
<li>This archive should be as futureproof as possible &ndash; I want to be able to view my photos at any point in the future regardless of device, machine migration, etc.</li>
<li>I should have the ability to view any photo in my collection from a mobile device, i.e. my iPhone or iPad, without having it cached locally.</li>
<li>It should be painless and hassle-free to add new photos into the archive, and thus the backup process.</li>
</ol>


<p>Inspired by <a href="http://www.macstories.net/tutorials/my-photo-management-workflow-early-2014/">Federico Viticci</a>, I&rsquo;ve migrated my photo library to a new system and ongoing process that works really well for me.</p>

<h3>iPhoto => Files &amp; Directories</h3>

<p>Requirement 3, at a stroke, entirely disqualifies database-based applications<sup id="fnref:2"><a href="#fn:2" rel="footnote">2</a></sup> like iPhoto. As my accumulated photo library was sitting in the increasingly-creaky iPhoto, the first step was to export the original <code>.jpg</code> files. The archive is therefore maintained as a set of files and directories going forward, and is thus highly future-proof.</p>

<p>The single most critical piece of metadata about a photograph is its creation date. Without this, it is inordinately difficult to find a particular photo, or preserve a sense of the original chronology of a series.</p>

<p>Unfortunately, file system metadata is insufficient as a repository for this signal. Machine migrations, underlying file system changes, and general <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Software_rot">bit rot</a> conspire to render this inadequate and fragile. Therefore, it makes sense to encode a photograph&rsquo;s creation date, available in the exif data, right inside its filename.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.sno.phy.queensu.ca/~phil/exiftool/">Exiftool</a>, available in <a href="http://brew.sh/">Homebrew for OS X</a> is a great way to achieve this. After exporting from iPhoto, I was able to rename each file:</p>

<pre><code>exiftool "-FileName&lt;CreateDate" -d "%Y-%m-%d_%H-%M-%S%%-c.%%le" export
</code></pre>

<h3>Binning the Files</h3>

<p>The above operation resulted in a directory with 10,000 <code>.jpg</code> files with an <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Iso8601#General_principles">ISO8601</a>-like filename, e.g.: <code>2011-02-03_16-12-11.jpg</code>. A bit unwieldy, but chronological and consistent. The next step was to separate these files by month, which I accomplished with a simple bit of Ruby (original on <a href="https://gist.github.com/dliggat/9677631">GitHub</a>):</p>

<figure class='code'><figcaption><span>photo_bin.rb: A ruby script to bin photos by year-month directories </span></figcaption>
<div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
<span class='line-number'>3</span>
<span class='line-number'>4</span>
<span class='line-number'>5</span>
<span class='line-number'>6</span>
<span class='line-number'>7</span>
<span class='line-number'>8</span>
<span class='line-number'>9</span>
<span class='line-number'>10</span>
<span class='line-number'>11</span>
<span class='line-number'>12</span>
<span class='line-number'>13</span>
<span class='line-number'>14</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class='rb'><span class='line'><span class="no">Dir</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">glob</span> <span class="s2">&quot;</span><span class="si">#{</span><span class="n">root_dir</span><span class="si">}</span><span class="s2">/*.jpg&quot;</span> <span class="k">do</span> <span class="o">|</span><span class="n">file</span><span class="o">|</span>
</span><span class='line'>  <span class="n">match</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="sr">/.*?(\d\d\d\d)-(\d\d)-\d\d_\d\d-\d\d-\d\d.*\.jpg$/</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">match</span> <span class="n">file</span>
</span><span class='line'>  <span class="k">raise</span> <span class="no">ArgumentError</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">new</span> <span class="s2">&quot;File did not match: </span><span class="si">#{</span><span class="n">file</span><span class="si">}</span><span class="s2">&quot;</span> <span class="k">unless</span> <span class="n">match</span>
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'>  <span class="n">year</span>           <span class="o">=</span> <span class="n">match</span><span class="o">[</span><span class="mi">1</span><span class="o">]</span>
</span><span class='line'>  <span class="n">month</span>          <span class="o">=</span> <span class="n">match</span><span class="o">[</span><span class="mi">2</span><span class="o">]</span>
</span><span class='line'>  <span class="n">month_abbr</span>     <span class="o">=</span> <span class="ss">Date</span><span class="p">:</span><span class="ss">:MONTHNAMES</span><span class="o">[</span><span class="n">month</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">to_i</span><span class="o">][</span><span class="mi">0</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">.</span><span class="mi">2</span><span class="o">]</span>
</span><span class='line'>  <span class="n">photo_dir_name</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="s2">&quot;</span><span class="si">#{</span><span class="n">year</span><span class="si">}</span><span class="s2">-</span><span class="si">#{</span><span class="n">month</span><span class="si">}</span><span class="s2">-</span><span class="si">#{</span><span class="n">month_abbr</span><span class="si">}</span><span class="s2">&quot;</span>
</span><span class='line'>  <span class="n">photo_abs_dir</span>  <span class="o">=</span> <span class="no">File</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">join</span> <span class="n">root_dir</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">photo_dir_name</span>
</span><span class='line'>  <span class="n">abs_file</span>       <span class="o">=</span> <span class="no">File</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">expand_path</span> <span class="n">file</span>
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'>  <span class="no">Dir</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">mkdir</span> <span class="n">photo_abs_dir</span> <span class="k">unless</span> <span class="no">Dir</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">exist?</span> <span class="n">photo_abs_dir</span>
</span><span class='line'>  <span class="no">FileUtils</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">mv</span> <span class="n">abs_file</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">photo_abs_dir</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="k">end</span>
</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<h3>Storage, Backup, Viewing</h3>

<p>I decided that the best place to actually store this [so-far] 55GB archive was on Google Drive. This has a few benefits:</p>

<ul>
<li><strong>Cheap</strong>: At $2 per month for 100GB of storage as of the <a href="http://googleblog.blogspot.ca/2014/03/save-more-with-google-drive.html">recent price drop</a>, it&rsquo;s hard to argue with the price.</li>
<li><strong>Local and Offsite Backup</strong>: These files live locally in <code>~/GoogleDrive</code> and therefore get subsumed into my wireless home network backups, but also have a disaster-mitigating copy on the cloud.</li>
<li><strong>Mobile Viewing</strong>: The iOS Google Drive app has quietly become a really high-quality piece of iOS software. It&rsquo;s a capable photo viewing app, and easily satisfies the mobile-viewing requirement (though I&rsquo;d like to see <a href="http://unboundapp.com/">Unbound</a> support it eventually also).</li>
</ul>


<p><img class="center" src="http://liggat.org/images/2014/gd.png" width="600" title="'Google Drive'" ></p>

<h3>Dealing with New Photos</h3>

<p>All of this so far covers requirements 1 through 4 splendidly. However, it&rsquo;s all a bit pointless if new photos aren&rsquo;t subsumed into this system on a hassle-free, ongoing basis. The final puzzle piece is also the most convoluted, but so far it seems to be holding up nicely:</p>

<ol>
<li>Take advantage of Dropbox&rsquo;s Camera Upload<sup id="fnref:3"><a href="#fn:3" rel="footnote">3</a></sup> functionality to send new photos over WiFi from my iPhone to the <code>~/Dropbox/Camera Uploads</code> directory on my Mac. This will happen in the background occasionally without any intervention from me, or I can trigger it manually whenever I want. Of course, <code>.jpg</code> files from other cameras can be placed here also<sup id="fnref:4"><a href="#fn:4" rel="footnote">4</a></sup>.</li>
<li>Use <a href="http://www.noodlesoft.com/hazel">Hazel</a> to watch that directory and segregate iOS screenshots (no need to archive those) and videos (I&rsquo;m still deciding how they should be handled), and then rename all <code>.jpg</code> files to the ISO8601-style format above. In this case, given the recency, it is reasonable to rely on the file metadata to encode the creation date in the filename.</li>
<li>Again with Hazel watching that directory, send those renamed files to <code>~/GoogleDrive/Photos</code>.</li>
<li>Another Hazel rule watching <code>~/GoogleDrive/Photos</code> will &ldquo;sort into subfolders&rdquo; and place each file into its appropriate year-month directory (e.g. <code>2014-03-Mar</code>), creating that directory if necessary.</li>
</ol>


<p><img class="center" src="http://liggat.org/images/2014/hazel.png" width="600" title="'Hazel'" ></p>

<p>That&rsquo;s it! The archive is consistent, future-proof, viewable and has a strong backup-strategy &ndash; and all new photos from now on have a frictionless pathway into it.</p>

<p>While I&rsquo;m happy with this system for me (and eventually I&rsquo;ll roll it out to my family) Apple, Google, Microsoft, et al really need to solve this problem for their customers. Photos are precious, and people, as a rule, are far worse at ensuring the longevity of bits than paper.</p>
<div class="footnotes">
<hr/>
<ol>
<li id="fn:1">
<p>They were never very good, anyway.<a href="#fnref:1" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
<li id="fn:2">
<p>It is generally a bad idea to rely on these type of programs if you care about accessing your data in the distant future. It will likely be difficult, or at best inconvenient, to read a circa-2014 iPhoto library in 2024. I make an <a href="http://liggat.org/2013/07/21/paperless/">exception</a> in the case of Evernote.<a href="#fnref:2" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
<li id="fn:3">
<p>Ideally I wouldn&rsquo;t be relying on two separate cloud-storage providers, but the combination of Google Drive pricing and Dropbox functionality is compelling. Future changes will be easy, anyhow, depending on how the storage market evolves.<a href="#fnref:3" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
<li id="fn:4">
<p>So far this doesn&rsquo;t really apply, as the only camera I use is my iPhone 5s. I hung up my SLR a few years ago.<a href="#fnref:4" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
</ol>
</div>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[@liggs Is Now @dliggat]]></title>
    <link href="http://liggat.org/2014/02/20/at-liggs-is-now-at-dliggat/"/>
    <updated>2014-02-20T23:20:23-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://liggat.org/2014/02/20/at-liggs-is-now-at-dliggat</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I&rsquo;ve changed my Twitter handle from @liggs to <a href="https://twitter.com/dliggat">@dliggat</a>, as part of a general username consolidation that&rsquo;s been nagging me for a while. I figured it was worth marking the <em>occasion</em> with a site entry, given how much I use Twitter.</p>

<!--more-->


<p>In case you&rsquo;re wondering, it&rsquo;s quite easy to swap two Twitter handles with a <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Swap_(computer_science)#Using_a_temporary_variable">3-way switch</a>, so long as you control both handles.</p>

<ol>
<li>In one browser, I opened <strong>@dliggat</strong> to <a href="https://twitter.com/settings/account">https://twitter.com/settings/account</a></li>
<li>In a seperate browser (Chrome instead of Safari in my case, but a <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Privacy_mode">private browser</a> session would work also) I also opened <strong>@liggs</strong> to <a href="https://twitter.com/settings/account">https://twitter.com/settings/account</a></li>
<li>I renamed <strong>@dliggat</strong> to <em>@dliggattemp</em>. Once this is confirmed, the next two steps need to be completed as quickly as possible.</li>
<li>I renamed <strong>@liggs</strong> to <strong>@dliggat</strong>.</li>
<li>I renamed <em>@dliggattemp</em> to <strong>@liggs</strong>.</li>
</ol>


<p>It all worked out without a hitch. <a href="https://twitter.com/dliggat">@dliggat</a> it is from now on.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Taking a Stand With Work]]></title>
    <link href="http://liggat.org/2014/02/16/taking-a-stand-with-work/"/>
    <updated>2014-02-16T10:21:59-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://liggat.org/2014/02/16/taking-a-stand-with-work</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Being a so-called <em>knowledge worker</em> comes with at least one very substantial downside: there is a fundamental lack of physical activity built into the job<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" rel="footnote">1</a></sup>, and long sedentary periods are commonplace. I&rsquo;ve been very cognizant of this for a long time, and do my best to actively combat it with daily exercise, gym routines, etc. While those help substantially, they do not alter the basic reality that one tends to be sitting in a chair for many hours, staring at a screen.</p>

<!--more-->


<p>To make matters worse, there appears to be <a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2011/04/17/magazine/mag-17sitting-t.html?_r=0">growing evidence</a> that excessive sitting is pathological all on its own:</p>

<blockquote><p>Sitting, it would seem, is an independent pathology. Being sedentary for nine hours a day at the office is bad for your health whether you go home and watch television afterward or hit the gym. It is bad whether you are morbidly obese or marathon-runner thin. “Excessive sitting,” Dr. Levine says, “is a lethal activity.”</p></blockquote>

<p>Whether or not that hypothesis is even true &ndash; inherently it simply doesn&rsquo;t <em>feel</em> good to sit this much<sup id="fnref:2"><a href="#fn:2" rel="footnote">2</a></sup>. Two weeks ago, I decided to switch to a standing desk, and I don&rsquo;t think I will ever look back.</p>

<h3>The Trial Run</h3>

<p>A purpose-built <a href="http://thewirecutter.com/reviews/the-best-standing-desks/">standing desk</a> will run you around $1,000, or more. These high end models tend to be motorized and can memorize different configurations &ndash; so you can mode-switch between the ideal standing height and the ideal sitting height. While that sounds great, and while the cost can be easily justified on both amortization as well as &lsquo;mattress logic&rsquo;<sup id="fnref:3"><a href="#fn:3" rel="footnote">3</a></sup> grounds &ndash; it&rsquo;s a lot of money to drop without even knowing if it&rsquo;s a good fit. Enter, the trial run.</p>

<p>Via <a href="http://chambersdaily.com/bradleychambers/2013/11/21/building-a-standing-desk-on-the-cheap">Bradley Chambers</a>, I found <a href="http://iamnotaprogrammer.com/Ikea-Standing-desk-for-22-dollars.html">Colin Nederkoorn&rsquo;s</a> instructions for building a standing desk with $22 USD ($30 CAD up here) worth of Ikea parts. I ordered these same parts and followed Colin&rsquo;s directions to build the basic framework that sits on top of my existing desk. The result:</p>

<p><img class="center" src="http://liggat.org/images/2014/desk.jpg" width="500" title="'Homemade Standing Desk'" ></p>

<p>It&rsquo;s not the most attractive thing in the world, and does not permit a quick mode-switch between sitting and standing &ndash; but it&rsquo;s hard to argue with the cost of entry as a way to trial the experience of a standing-desk.</p>

<h3>The Result</h3>

<p>I&rsquo;ve used this now for two weeks. Without exaggeration, I cannot ever see myself going back to a standard desk arrangement. The first couple of days were a bit more tiring than usual, as my body adjusted to the change. A few days later, it feels completely natural. Quite apart from the physical benefit of standing versus sitting, I&rsquo;ve found that standing imparts a greater sense of purpose to my current task: as if I&rsquo;m subconsciously striving towards completion before fatigue can arrive.</p>

<p>In practice, I don&rsquo;t actually stand the whole day &ndash; perhaps only 75%. I have meals sitting down of course, and take a few short sitting breaks during the day &ndash; usually at periods of planning or design. This has the secondary benefit of taking me away from the keyboard to exclusively focus on design itself.</p>

<p>In the medium-term timeframe, I&rsquo;ll almost certainly switch to a &lsquo;real&rsquo; standing desk. For now, this is a great way to work.</p>

<h3>Social Norms?</h3>

<p>I work from home and have the luxury of arranging my own workspace. I could work from an inflatable rubber-dinghy if I so chose, and there would be nothing stopping me from doing so.</p>

<p>Most people are not this lucky. They work at the desk and chair that their employer provides, and it would be frankly odd to be the lone oddball standing beside the Ikea contraption<sup id="fnref:4"><a href="#fn:4" rel="footnote">4</a></sup>, as everyone else hunches over their desk. I can only hope that the dual forces of sitting-health-research, and remote-work-acceptance will drive us all towards more flexible, personal ergonomic arrangements.</p>
<div class="footnotes">
<hr/>
<ol>
<li id="fn:1">
<p>Unlike, say, an electrician or a nurse. Hat tip, little brother and little sister.<a href="#fnref:1" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
<li id="fn:2">
<p>Despite having a good Herman-Miller chair in my home office.<a href="#fnref:2" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
<li id="fn:3">
<p>&ldquo;You use this a lot so get a good one.&rdquo;<a href="#fnref:3" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
<li id="fn:4">
<p>Assuming &lsquo;Health &amp; Safety&rsquo; even let the thing in the front door, which is not necessarily probable.<a href="#fnref:4" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
</ol>
</div>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Navigating Canadian Cellular Number Portability (in 8 Easy Steps)]]></title>
    <link href="http://liggat.org/2014/01/30/navigating-canadian-cellular-number-portability/"/>
    <updated>2014-01-30T22:47:12-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://liggat.org/2014/01/30/navigating-canadian-cellular-number-portability</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Since 2007, Canadians have been afforded the right to migrate (&lsquo;port&rsquo;) their cellular <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pstn">PSTN</a> number with them when they switch to a new cellular operator. The legislation which enacted this brought to bear a small reduction in <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Switching_barriers">switching costs</a> in a &lsquo;market&rsquo;<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" rel="footnote">1</a></sup> widely reputed for hostility towards its customers, not to mention, [at the very least] <em>perceived</em> collusion among the operators themselves.<!--more--></p>

<p>Unfortunately, no matter which head of the <a href="https://www.google.ca/search?client=safari&amp;rls=en&amp;q=robelus">tripartite Cerberus</a> one ends up dealing with, this is far more hassle, and potentially more expensive, than it needs to be.</p>

<p>Cellular services are paid for one month in advance, and when you initiate a port, <em>no matter when you initiate it</em>, your current operator will attempt to bill you for one final advance month. The rationale, they say, is that they need thirty days of notice. This would be semi-reasonable if there were some official way to give that notice ahead of time. There isn&rsquo;t. The only way, in their view, to give that notice is through the port itself. So you&rsquo;re stuck paying for a month of service that cannot actually be delivered.</p>

<p>Let me repeat that: they demand thirty days of notice, but won&rsquo;t let you provide it in any way other than that which results in receiving a bill for an unnecessary month of undeliverable service. This is, obviously, bullshit. Here&rsquo;s how to get around it<sup id="fnref:2"><a href="#fn:2" rel="footnote">2</a></sup>:</p>

<ol>
<li>Ensure your contract is over, and you don&rsquo;t owe an early-termination fee for the device subsidy you likely received two or three years ago. e.g. if you signed up on <code>2010-03-13</code> with a three year contract, by <code>2013-03-14</code> you&rsquo;re definitely in the clear.</li>
<li>Work out your billing cycle. This may or may not be explicitly stated on your invoice, but it generally covers your invoice date (e.g. the 15th of the month) plus 30 days.</li>
<li>Two days before your invoice date (e.g. April 13th), phone your operator and tell them you are intending to cancel. You&rsquo;ll probably need to sit through a barrage of retention offers. <strong>It&rsquo;s important that they don&rsquo;t actually cancel right then</strong> &ndash; you may lose the service and number. Tell the retention agent that you intend to cancel, but that you will phone back if you wish to accept the retention offer. Record the agent&rsquo;s name, call reference number, and the current date/time.</li>
<li>Use your phone as normal for another month.</li>
<li>Again two days before your invoice date (e.g. now May 13th) sign up for service with your new operator (hopefully a better deal than your current one) and have them initiate a port of the number.</li>
<li>Your previous operator will receive notice of the cancellation, and will issue a final bill covering any overage plus service from May 15th plus 30 days. This is the service they cannot actually provide, yet still bill for.</li>
<li>Now the real fun begins: phone the original operator to complain about the bill for undeliverable service. They will tell you that they require thirty days of notice for cancellations. Mention your &lsquo;notice&rsquo; call &ndash; done a month ago in step (3). They will say it doesn&rsquo;t count. Escalate to a manager. Patiently explain that the company is billing for something that it cannot possibly provide (the number is gone). Prepare to be the recipient of a deeply-flawed, logically-inconsistent argument about why it makes sense to be billed for this. End the call in despair, but again, ensure to record the agent&rsquo;s name, call reference number, and the current date/time.</li>
<li>Visit the <a href="https://www.ccts-cprst.ca/en/complaints/complaint-form">CCTS</a> (the Commissioner for Complaints for Telecommunications Services). Create a new complaint. Explain the timeline<sup id="fnref:3"><a href="#fn:3" rel="footnote">3</a></sup> of events, and be sure to mention the particular timestamps and call reference numbers.</li>
</ol>


<p>In a few days time &ndash; expect to receive an incredibly cordial and understanding call from the operator&rsquo;s Office of the President or similar Ombudsman-type department. This person will explain that the other agents were mistaken, and that you are in the right. They will happily nullify the &lsquo;erroneous&rsquo; charge and graciously thank you for your time.</p>

<p>This is <strong>nuts</strong> of course &ndash; but this elaborate dance is what&rsquo;s required of you if you want to port without paying for two sets of service for a month. One could be forgiven for believing this was an isolated incident, <a href="https://www.google.ca/search?q=rogers+port+ccts&amp;oq=rogers+port+ccts">but it definitely isn&rsquo;t</a>. Hell &ndash; I learned how to do all this by piecing it together from other anecdotes online.</p>

<p>There&rsquo;s no panacea to fixing telecom in Canada<sup id="fnref:4"><a href="#fn:4" rel="footnote">4</a></sup>, but I&rsquo;m happy to accept small victories where I can.</p>
<div class="footnotes">
<hr/>
<ol>
<li id="fn:1">
<p>I use the term loosely.<a href="#fnref:1" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
<li id="fn:2">
<p>I went through this whole dance recently with Rogers, but singling them out only really serves to substantiate the fiction that these are three separate, competitive enterprises. There&rsquo;s virtually no daylight between the three operators on most issues of any import.<a href="#fnref:2" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
<li id="fn:3">
<p>Pro tip: <a href="https://evernote.com">Evernote</a> is an excellent tool for tracking things like this.<a href="#fnref:3" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
<li id="fn:4">
<p>You can remove the protectionism, but Canada&rsquo;s size, geography, and low population density guarantee it will always be a difficult country when it comes to infrastructure.<a href="#fnref:4" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
</ol>
</div>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[In Charge of Windows 9]]></title>
    <link href="http://liggat.org/2014/01/15/in-charge-of-windows-9/"/>
    <updated>2014-01-15T17:23:19-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://liggat.org/2014/01/15/in-charge-of-windows-9</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Peter, an old UBC classmate and frequent co-banterer on Twitter, randomly posed an interesting question to me earlier today:<!--more--></p>

<blockquote class="twitter-tweet" lang="en"><p><a href="https://twitter.com/liggs">@liggs</a> Serious question: if you were put in charge of Windows 9 tomorrow, what would you do with it?</p>&mdash; Peter J. Cavan (@PJCavan) <a href="https://twitter.com/PJCavan/statuses/423564952683560960">January 15, 2014</a></blockquote>


<script async src="http://liggat.org//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"></script>


<p>I immediately replied that I think this is the single most difficult strategic question in the tech industry today, moreso even than the challenge over at BlackBerry Inc. The response, assuming I can come up with one worth the bits it&rsquo;s written on, will definitely not fit into 140-characters. Hence, a blog post.</p>

<p>The unlucky soul in charge of birthing Windows 9 has the following difficult truths to contend with:</p>

<ol>
<li>Selling operating systems to OEM-device manufacturers, as a business, is essentially dying. It&rsquo;s a sustainment business at best. This is the business model on which Windows ascended, and it&rsquo;s come to the end. There are now really only two ways to make money as an OS vendor &ndash; you wrap it in aluminum and glass and sell the whole device (Apple), or you give it away and own the market for the user&rsquo;s attention (Google). Microsoft has had a few punts at the Apple approach in the form of Zune and Surface, but has yet to set the world on fire doing this.</li>
<li>Windows 8 has not been well received by its userbase, to put it mildly. I haven&rsquo;t actually used it myself, but in terms of reception, <em>Vista 2.0</em>, does not seem an unfair moniker. Aside from the bold user-interface change<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" rel="footnote">1</a></sup>, apparently unloved by many, the RT/Pro distinction is <em>confusing as hell</em>.</li>
<li>Mobile and tablets happened. Anyone still rattling on that iOS (or Android) is unsuitable for <em>real work™</em> is missing the point &ndash; mobile devices unbundle the Internet from the PC. Ten years ago, it was axiomatic that if you wanted to participate in online activities &ndash; Facebook, email and so on &ndash; you needed a PC, and that usually meant a Windows PC. <em>Tons</em> of PC use cases are being chipped away by more personal mobile devices, and that trend is only going to increase.</li>
<li>All of that might not be so bad if Microsoft was a major player in mobile &ndash; but it isn&rsquo;t. Mobile as it stands is a duopoly between iOS and Android, and I&rsquo;m far from convinced there&rsquo;s room for a third stack. The undoubted merits of Microsoft&rsquo;s mobile and tablet efforts in the form of Windows Phone and Surface notwithstanding &ndash; these are not yet products with a non-trivial market-share, let alone mind-share.</li>
<li>Anyone doubting any of the above need only refer to <a href="http://ben-evans.com/benedictevans/2013/7/20/the-irrelevance-of-microsoft">Microsoft&rsquo;s share</a> of Internet-connected devices: 90% down to 20% in just a few years.</li>
</ol>


<p>So what&rsquo;s a chief product manager of Windows 9 to do? I can&rsquo;t begin to do Peter&rsquo;s question justice, but I can offer a few humble suggestions:</p>

<ul>
<li>Windows 8 was a noble though misguided attempt to be all things to all people: multiple concepts all resident within a single device. However, we live in a <a href="http://mattgemmell.com/the-unacknowledged-compromise/">multi-device</a> world now. The machine one uses for AutoCAD design work with a mouse and keyboard needn&rsquo;t also be the same one that has a touch-enabled Twitter client in another layer. Windows 9 should therefore build upon the best parts of the generally-well-liked Windows 7, in the same way that, say, OS X Mavericks iterated upon OS X Mountain Lion &ndash; <em>without</em> attempting to change the paradigm. Better power-management, UI refinement, etc is the order of the day here.</li>
<li>Forget touch. Windows has always been about keyboard/mouse input devices, and grafting a touch layer on top is pointless. No one wants to use touch on a laptop, or God-forbid, a desktop, anyway.</li>
<li>Office remains an important business for Microsoft, and an important tool<sup id="fnref:2"><a href="#fn:2" rel="footnote">2</a></sup> for a ton of people. They are leaving a lot of money and future relevance on the table by not porting a first-class version to iOS (and Android), but even if they do &ndash; Windows should exist to provide a preeminent environment for complex applications like Office, and play to its keyboard/mouse/file-system strengths.</li>
<li>This really shouldn&rsquo;t need to be said, but native PDF viewing in Windows is an idea whose time has come.</li>
</ul>


<p>Whoever ends up driving this project has my well wishes (and sympathies). From where I stand, it&rsquo;s hard not to see it as a <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sisyphus">Sisyphean</a> task.</p>
<div class="footnotes">
<hr/>
<ol>
<li id="fn:1">
<p>I applauded the vision when Metro was first announced, but it was clear from the beginning that the outcome would either be spectacularly good or spectacularly bad, with very little room for an outcome in the middle.<a href="#fnref:1" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
<li id="fn:2">
<p>Well Excel is peerless anyway; I&rsquo;m less certain that anything other than organizational inertia keeps Word and PowerPoint in such widespread use.<a href="#fnref:2" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
</ol>
</div>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Criticize Real-World NOOPs]]></title>
    <link href="http://liggat.org/2014/01/08/criticize-real-world-noops/"/>
    <updated>2014-01-08T23:37:42-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://liggat.org/2014/01/08/criticize-real-world-noops</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>In the world of computation, a <em>NOOP</em> (<em>No-Op</em>eration) is an instruction that has zero effect on the state of the machine. The term originally hails from the esoteric world of CPU-architecture and instruction-sets<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" rel="footnote">1</a></sup>, but the term is also used semi-colloquially as programmer shorthand for <strong>&lsquo;this achieves nothing&rsquo;</strong>.<!--more--></p>

<p>A very simple example in code might be in setting a variable to the difference of itself and zero (<code>x = x - 0</code>), but they tend, as a rule, to not be so obvious. On first glance, they <em>look</em> like useful work.</p>

<p>Programmers regard NOOPs with suspicion. Good code reviewers will identify them, question their existence, and  demand exceptional justification for their continued presence. They are unwelcome in quality software not for their outcome &ndash; they do nothing after all &ndash; but because they <em>sow confusion</em>. On first glance, they appear to have a purpose; they subconsciously assuage concerns that might otherwise have been raised in their absence. Many a pernicious bug can be traced back to a NOOP that misled its programmers. A NOOP is a facade: an illusion of real work being performed.</p>

<p>Lately I&rsquo;ve been thinking that the term might be applicable in the real-world also. Consider this story:</p>

<h4><a href="http://rt.com/news/france-google-fine-privacy-339/">France hands down data privacy fine to Google</a></h4>

<blockquote><p>French data protection watchdog CNIL fined Google 150,000 euros ($204,000) for ignoring its three-month deadline to align its
practice of tracking and storing user information with the country’s law.</p></blockquote>

<p>I&rsquo;m not commenting on<sup id="fnref:2"><a href="#fn:2" rel="footnote">2</a></sup>, or even particularly interested in this French legal ruling. That&rsquo;s for France and Google Inc to work out.</p>

<p>But it seems to me that regardless of the fine&rsquo;s merit &ndash; imposing a €150,000 fine on a company which earns that amount in revenue every <em>two minutes</em><sup id="fnref:3"><a href="#fn:3" rel="footnote">3</a></sup>, very closely fits the definition of a NOOP. It is the act of doing nothing masquerading as the act of doing something of significance. To an extremely close approximation, it is the judicial equivalent of subtracting zero from an integer.</p>

<p>In its article, RT makes no effort to contextualize this, and it&rsquo;s not just a failing of theirs &ndash; it&rsquo;s frankly rare in news media. This is precisely the opposite of the programmer mentality: NOOPs are always to be identified as such, and their presence criticized. The world would greatly benefit from a culture that does a better job in <strong>pointing out pointlessness</strong>.</p>
<div class="footnotes">
<hr/>
<ol>
<li id="fn:1">
<p>An idle CPU can&rsquo;t actually do nothing, so they would traditionally just repeatedly execute the NOOP instruction in the absence of actual work to do. I suspect that&rsquo;s an oversimplification circa-2014 with the vast amounts of research that have gone into processor energy-efficiency.<a href="#fnref:1" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
<li id="fn:2">
<p>Disclosure: I&rsquo;m an ex-Google employee (departed on highly-amicable terms to pursue a Masters) and a long-time admirer of the firm, pre and post employment.<a href="#fnref:2" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
<li id="fn:3">
<p>Google has <a href="http://investor.google.com/financial/tables.html">yearly revenues</a> on the order of <code>$50,000,000,000</code>. There are <code>365 * 24 * 60 = 525,600</code> minutes per year. <code>$50B / 525.6k ~= $95k ~= €68k</code>. Two minutes revenue <code>~= €150k</code>.<a href="#fnref:3" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
</ol>
</div>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[A New Design]]></title>
    <link href="http://liggat.org/2013/12/24/a-new-design/"/>
    <updated>2013-12-24T21:14:09-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://liggat.org/2013/12/24/a-new-design</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I&rsquo;ve been using <a href="http://octopress.org">Octopress</a> as a blogging platform for over six months now, and can&rsquo;t recommend it enough for tech capable (or curious) writers. However, I&rsquo;ve never been fully happy with my minor adaptations to the default style. I finally got around to implementing an improved design.<!--more--></p>

<h3>Original</h3>

<p>My site started off looking like this:
<img class="center" src="http://liggat.org/images/2013/old-octopress-style.png" width="700" title="'Old'" ></p>

<p>It was by all means serviceable, but I was starting to tire of the excess <em>chrome</em> &ndash; the prominent header, the large nav-bar, and the unnecessary <em>Recent Posts</em> sidebar. Morever, despite numerous tweaks to the layout, colouring, and typography &ndash; it still instantly <em>looked</em> like an Octopress site<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" rel="footnote">1</a></sup>.</p>

<h3>Design Objectives</h3>

<p>I&rsquo;m not a UI designer, either by trade or by realistic-aspiration<sup id="fnref:2"><a href="#fn:2" rel="footnote">2</a></sup>. Still, I had a pretty good idea in mind what I wanted my home on the web to look like.</p>

<ul>
<li><strong>Content Focus</strong>: This site exists for one purpose &ndash; a place to store material that I write. Anything that&rsquo;s not written content distracts from that objective. Among other things, that means the large, colourful header needs to go.</li>
<li><strong>De-Octopress the UI</strong>: Octopress is the infrastructure for this site, and will be for the far-foreseeable future. That doesn&rsquo;t mean I need to rely on its default UI styling, and in fact, I&rsquo;d greatly prefer it didn&rsquo;t <em>look</em> like an Octopress site. I still want to rely on the basic Octopress layout though, as well as its <a href="http://coding.smashingmagazine.com/2011/01/12/guidelines-for-responsive-web-design/">responsive design</a>.</li>
<li><strong>Better Typography</strong>: I&rsquo;ve long been a little too zealous in observing the &lsquo;rule&rsquo; that <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sans-serif">sans-serif</a> headers should be paired with <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Serif">serif</a> body text. Accordingly, I initially used the serif Google Font <a href="https://www.google.com/fonts/specimen/Lora">Lora</a> for the body, but was never quite happy with the choice. Many blogs I read eschew serifs entirely, and the effect is well-suited to the content<sup id="fnref:3"><a href="#fn:3" rel="footnote">3</a></sup>.</li>
<li><strong>Better Footnote Styling</strong>: Chris Suave&rsquo;s excellent <a href="http://cmsauve.com/labs/bigfoot/">Bigfoot</a> footnote implementation is far superior to numeric in-page anchors. I wanted to replace the latter with the former (or similar).</li>
</ul>


<h3>Result</h3>

<p>With a bit of spare time over Christmas 2013, I hacked away at my blog&rsquo;s <a href="https://github.com/dliggat/dliggat.github.io">git repo</a> to shape the design. I&rsquo;m pretty happy with how it&rsquo;s turned out:</p>

<h4>Desktop Layout:</h4>

<p><img class="center" src="http://liggat.org/images/2013/new-octopress-style.png" width="700" title="'New'" ></p>

<h4>Mobile Layout:</h4>

<p><img class="center" src="http://liggat.org/images/2013/new-octopress-style-mobile.png" width="350" title="'New'" ></p>

<p>I&rsquo;m still a bit ambivalent about having comments at all, but otherwise, I&rsquo;m happy with how it looks. It&rsquo;ll be interesting to review these design decisions down the line.</p>
<div class="footnotes">
<hr/>
<ol>
<li id="fn:1">
<p>This style is instantly recognizable around various corners of the web &ndash; all deriving from the design on <a href="http://octopress.org">octopress.org</a> itself. The gradient and text-shadow on the nav-bar is a dead giveaway.<a href="#fnref:1" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
<li id="fn:2">
<p>I have <em>just</em> enough design knowledge to overcome the <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dunning%E2%80%93Kruger_effect">Dunning-Kruger effect</a>.<a href="#fnref:2" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
<li id="fn:3">
<p>i.e., we&rsquo;re not writing the New York Times here.<a href="#fnref:3" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
</ol>
</div>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Canadian Housing: Noting for Posterity]]></title>
    <link href="http://liggat.org/2013/12/15/canadian-housing-noting-for-posterity/"/>
    <updated>2013-12-15T08:52:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://liggat.org/2013/12/15/canadian-housing-noting-for-posterity</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I&rsquo;m posting the following chart from <a href="http://blog.bcaresearch.com/canadian-housing-the-bubble-debate">BCA Research</a> not for the purposes of persuasion, but rather, for posterity.<!--more--></p>

<p><img class="center http://www.google.ca" src="http://liggat.org/images/2013/Canada-Housing.gif" title="'Canada Housing'" ></p>

<p>If you have a sense of the historical economic similarity between Canada and the United States, understand the computation and significance of <code>price:rent</code> and <code>price:income</code> as housing valuation metrics, and yet still don&rsquo;t feel <em>even a flutter of anxiety</em> about the future of the Canadian housing market, and more importantly, the downstream economic and societal implications of a <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Regression_toward_the_mean">reversion to the mean</a> &ndash; then you&rsquo;re far beyond the power of my rhetoric to change your mind<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" rel="footnote">1</a></sup>.</p>

<p>As I write this, in late 2013, <a href="http://www.theglobeandmail.com/report-on-business/top-business-stories/canadas-housing-market-most-overvalued-in-the-world-deutsche-bank-says/article15878166/">Deutsche Bank</a> joins a growing list of spectators whose ranks include <a href="http://www.economist.com/news/finance-and-economics/21584361-america-surges-much-europe-sinks-mixed-messages">The Economist</a>, <a href="http://www.cnbc.com/id/101150382">Goldman-Sachs</a>, <a href="http://business.financialpost.com/2012/09/21/canada-heading-into-a-slow-motion-version-of-the-u-s-housing-bust-robert-shiller/">Robert Shiller</a>, the <a href="http://business.financialpost.com/2013/11/27/according-to-the-imf-canada-has-the-most-overvalued-housing-market-in-the-world/">IMF</a>, <a href="http://www.theglobeandmail.com/report-on-business/top-business-stories/nouriel-roubini-aka-dr-doom-warns-of-frothy-canadian-housing-market/article15807846/">Nouriel Roubini</a>, and <a href="http://ca.finance.yahoo.com/blogs/balance-sheet/paul-krugman-warns-canada-vulnerable-big-deleveraging-shock-183728127.html">Paul Krugman</a> &ndash; all of whom have expressed incredulity and/or concern in one form or another about the stratospheric valuations in the Canadian housing market.</p>

<p>My opinion, irrelevant and disinterested<sup id="fnref:2"><a href="#fn:2" rel="footnote">2</a></sup> though it may be, is very straightforward, and has been unchanged for several years now: <strong>this will end badly</strong>, for the <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Leverage_(finance)">leveraged</a> and unleveraged, alike. Just ask anyone from the Republic of Ireland. Or look a little closer to home &ndash; below the 49th Parallel.</p>

<p>Feel free to disagree with me<sup id="fnref:3"><a href="#fn:3" rel="footnote">3</a></sup>. Most Canadians do, at least as a default position. But if you do disagree, surely it&rsquo;s at least partially concerning to witness all this opposing consensus among weighty, if not necessarily clairvoyant, external parties?</p>
<div class="footnotes">
<hr/>
<ol>
<li id="fn:1">
<p>Or, quite possibly, you&rsquo;re subject to the phenomenon, originally noted by Upton Sinclair, that <em>it is difficult to get a man to understand something, when his salary depends on his not understanding it</em>.<a href="#fnref:1" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
<li id="fn:2">
<p>I really mean this &ndash; I&rsquo;m <a href="http://www.dailywritingtips.com/disinterested-not-the-same-as-uninterested">disinterested</a> (but not <em>uninterested</em> clearly, as all of this is deeply fascinating to me &ndash; in a train-wreck sort of way). I have no real stake in whether or not there&rsquo;s a massive housing bubble in Canada, other than the stake of preferring not to live in a country captured by the fallacious belief that trading real estate is the preeminent way to generate wealth.<a href="#fnref:2" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
<li id="fn:3">
<p>Keep in mind: it&rsquo;s possible to simultaneously {own property | need to buy it soon} and {find the status quo very concerning}.<a href="#fnref:3" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
</ol>
</div>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[A Minor Rant on Package Tracking]]></title>
    <link href="http://liggat.org/2013/11/30/a-minor-rant-on-package-tracking/"/>
    <updated>2013-11-30T23:11:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://liggat.org/2013/11/30/a-minor-rant-on-package-tracking</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I do a fair bit of online shopping<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" rel="footnote">1</a></sup>, and have done so for pretty much my entire credit-card-wielding life. It&rsquo;s a familiar ritual: every time, shortly after I&rsquo;ve clicked <code>Purchase</code>, an email arrives containing a linked phrase with roughly the following copy: <em>Click here to track your shipment</em>. <!--more-->And every time I receive that email, I dutifully click that link, only to be met with the following 404-esque response:</p>

<p><img class="center" src="http://liggat.org/images/2013/tracking.png" width="600" title="'tracking'" ></p>

<p>It does not seem to matter whether the year is 2005 or 2013, and whether the logistics handler in question is Canada Post, USPS, UPS, etc &ndash; this is invariably the experience. This is a minor but absolutely-nagging annoyance if you know anything about software. It does not need to be this way.</p>

<p>Subsequent to the buyer&rsquo;s order, the seller and the logistics handler must perform an asynchronous (with respect to the buyer) transaction in which, among other things, data is exchanged regarding the delivery to be executed. At some point in this process, the seller is provided with a tracking number for that delivery, which they happily relay to the buyer in the aforesaid email. Therefore, when the buyer excitedly clicks on the tracking link, they are performing a lookup of <strong>a record that is certain to exist somewhere on the logistics handler&rsquo;s systems</strong>, and yet are <em>told</em> it doesn&rsquo;t exist.</p>

<p>I imagine that at this point, given the opportunity, the CTO of one of these logistics handler outfits might loudly interject <em>&ldquo;Well, of course &ndash; but the consumer web frontend and the logistics backend are entirely separate systems that we need to batch transfer over, and because of our legacy&hellip; and because of our storage requirements&hellip; and because of our load balancing&hellip; and because of Sarbanes-Oxley&hellip; and&hellip;.&rdquo;</em></p>

<p>And I&rsquo;m sure these would all be perfectly justified reasons, within the infrastructure team of that firm. The point is though, I don&rsquo;t care <strong>why</strong> the tracker was <em>unable to find any results</em>. And neither does any other user. This is a bad experience, and they can, and should do better. A few suggestions, in increasing order of implementation complexity:</p>

<ol>
<li>Make a better <em>unable to find any results</em> page. Acknowledge that this is a new tracking number, and will be in the systems shortly. Provide a timeframe. Differentiate between new numbers, and erroneous ones (use a <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Checksum">checksumming</a> scheme in the numbers themselves if necessary).</li>
<li>Coordinate with the seller. Don&rsquo;t fire out emails containing tracking links until both the seller and the logistics handler agree that the delivery will be performed, a tracking number exists, and the tracking number is queryable. I don&rsquo;t want an email with a link that I can&rsquo;t use until some unspecified period has passed.</li>
<li>Build better infrastructure. It is well within the ability of humanity&rsquo;s current software engineering to run systems without such absurd temporal lags within a single organization&rsquo;s infrastructure. This is not an especially complex technical problem. If your logistics and web-query systems are entirely separate, and they take 6 hours to propagate records &ndash; get that 6 down to 5. Then to 4. Then to 3. Etc.</li>
</ol>


<p>Clearly, this is not an important concern in the grand scheme of the universe. Invariably, the links start working eventually, and the packages arrive. But the triviality is no reason to not demand a modicum of progress.</p>
<div class="footnotes">
<hr/>
<ol>
<li id="fn:1">
<p>I did even more when I lived in the USA. The selection and swiftness of delivery of online purchasing there is nothing short of remarkable, especially under Amazon Prime.<a href="#fnref:1" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
</ol>
</div>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Static Hosting on Amazon S3]]></title>
    <link href="http://liggat.org/2013/11/03/static-hosting-on-amazon-s3/"/>
    <updated>2013-11-03T13:13:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://liggat.org/2013/11/03/static-hosting-on-amazon-s3</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I&rsquo;ve had an outstanding <strong>todo</strong> for quite some time to migrate my basic and essentially-static <a href="http://www.factorialsystems.ca">business website</a> off of <a href="http://www.squarespace.com">Squarespace</a>. I ended up replacing it with a combination of <a href="http://octopress.org">Octopress</a> and Amazon Simple Storage Service (<a href="http://aws.amazon.com/s3">S3</a>), which, it turns out, are a fantastic duo.<!--more--></p>

<h3>Prelude</h3>

<p>A brief prelude: Squarespace is fantastic, and should be the first port of call for anyone, especially a business, who needs a website. I can&rsquo;t even enumerate the number of ostensibly well-run restaurants and businesses who either don&rsquo;t have a website, or if they do, it&rsquo;s some horrid Flash-payload thing that won&rsquo;t run on the primary device customers tend to be using at the point of need: their phones! Squarespace isn&rsquo;t free, but is totally worth the small monthly cost for pretty much anyone.</p>

<p>I started my business site there due to a combination of being overwhelmingly-busy at the time, as well as generally curious about the service&hellip; but it eventually became time for me to move on<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" rel="footnote">1</a></sup>.</p>

<h3>Octopress</h3>

<p>I&rsquo;ve become quite enamoured with Octopress &ndash; the blogging engine that I use for this site (and host on GitHub). I like to think of it as the anti-Wordpress &ndash; it produces good, old-fashioned directory trees of HTML pages from <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Markdown">markdown</a>-formatted source files and <a href="http://sass-lang.com/">SASS</a> style sheets. No application server or database, and the attendant care and feeding, required &ndash; just a plain old web server serving files<sup id="fnref:2"><a href="#fn:2" rel="footnote">2</a></sup>. This is a perfect choice, it turns out, for a basic company site. It has all the necessary infrastructure for blogging, should that become necessary, and has built-in responsive design and other niceties.</p>

<h3>Hosting</h3>

<p>S3 is Amazon Web Services&#8217; online file storage service (distributed, redundant, RESTful, etc). It is purportedly used as the persistence backend for <a href="http://dropbox.com">Dropbox</a>, among others. My needs are considerably more modest &ndash; I just want it to store and serve my site content. It turns out it has an option for exactly this purpose:</p>

<p><img class="center" src="http://liggat.org/images/2013/s3.png" width="600" title="'S3 Static Website Hosting'" ></p>

<p>Thus, a static website with Octopress and S3 requires that you simply:</p>

<ol>
<li>create content within an Octopress repository</li>
<li>execute Octopress&#8217; <code>bundle exec rake generate</code> to produce static HTML</li>
<li>deploy the output to an S3 bucket (<code>bundle exec rake deploy</code>)</li>
</ol>


<h3>Deploying</h3>

<p>Out of the box, Octopress does not know how to deploy to S3. That&rsquo;s easily remedied via an extension to the <code>Rakefile</code> that I found via this <a href="http://www.jerome-bernard.com/blog/2011/08/20/quick-tip-for-easily-deploying-octopress-blog-on-amazon-s3/">blog post</a>. With that <code>s3</code> rake task added, and S3 bucket variables defined, it&rsquo;s simply a matter of running <code>bundle exec rake deploy</code>. to deploy new content. The underlying <code>s3cmd</code> is, obviously, smart enough to only send content deltas to the S3 bucket.</p>

<h3>Cost</h3>

<p>At the time of writing, Amazon charges 9.5¢ per Gigabyte-month for the first 1TB of storage (cheaper thereafter), plus 0.5¢ per 1000 RESTful (GET, PUT, etc) operations, plus some minimal data transfer charge. One reasonable way to describe this might be: <strong>extremely inexpensive</strong>!</p>

<h3>So Far, So Good</h3>

<p>Thus far, I&rsquo;m really happy with this setup. My personal blog, this site, is currently hosted on <a href="http://pages.github.com">GitHub Pages</a><sup id="fnref:3"><a href="#fn:3" rel="footnote">3</a></sup>, but I&rsquo;ll probably move this over to S3 also. Obviously, the static site constraint remains &ndash; I can&rsquo;t, for instance, have a page with a form, or an XHR endpoint, etc. But if those should become necessary &ndash; it&rsquo;s very easy to upgrade to an EC2 instance with Rails, and remain within the Amazon ecosystem. I guess that&rsquo;s how they get you&hellip;</p>
<div class="footnotes">
<hr/>
<ol>
<li id="fn:1">
<p>Squarespace is definitely overkill for a static site if you have the time, knowledge and inclination to host it elsewhere. But many website-needing entities do not possess the intersection of those properties &ndash; hence the genius of Squarespace as a product itself.<a href="#fnref:1" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
<li id="fn:2">
<p>This resultant simplicity has an inherent appeal &ndash; not dissimilar to that, for me, of iOS vs OS X. The former trades possibility for simplicity &ndash; a desirable exchange in many (but obviously not all) scenarios.<a href="#fnref:2" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
<li id="fn:3">
<p>GitHub Pages hosts static sites for free &ndash; not wishing to trespass on GitHub&rsquo;s awesomeness, I reasoned that I should probably pay for the business site&rsquo;s hosting. All 68¢ of it, or whatever the final bill ends up being.<a href="#fnref:3" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
</ol>
</div>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Walter White, Art Aficionado]]></title>
    <link href="http://liggat.org/2013/10/15/walter-white/"/>
    <updated>2013-10-15T10:41:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://liggat.org/2013/10/15/walter-white</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I&rsquo;ve been re-watching <em>Breaking Bad</em>, one of my favourite television dramas, ever. Yesterday, midway through an early second season episode, I noticed a connection to a much later point in the story that I haven&rsquo;t seen discussed anywhere else.</p>

<!--more-->


<p><em>Don&rsquo;t read this if you&rsquo;re keen to avoid Breaking Bad plot details.</em></p>

<h3>The Painting</h3>

<p>By the midpoint of season five<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" rel="footnote">1</a></sup>, Walter is at the height of his Heisenberg-persona hubris. He&rsquo;s built his own drug empire, defeated his enemies &ndash; notably Fring, and still gone unnoticed by law enforcement. He&rsquo;s invincible. As if to telegraph this &ndash; while Uncle Jack and his band of Nazis are struggling over the minutiae of their planned murderous rampage at three separate Albuquerque jails &ndash; Walt stares at a painting in the motel room, uninterested in the conversation around him.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="http://liggat.org/images/2013/painting_second.jpg" width="500" title="Painting in the Motel" ></p>

<p>He idly speculates: <em>Where do you suppose these come from? I&rsquo;ve seen this one before. I wonder &ndash; are they all in some giant warehouse someplace?</em>, and invites the ire of Uncle Jack &ndash; incredulous at his lack of focus on planning the operation.</p>

<h3>First Appearance</h3>

<p>It turns out that this same painting featured much earlier in the story<sup id="fnref:2"><a href="#fn:2" rel="footnote">2</a></sup>. A browbeaten Walt was finishing up a chemotherapy session, and spent a moment staring at a print of it on the hospital wall. The camera lingers at what is surely an instance of symbolism: the painting is of a man, rowing <em>away</em> from his family on the shore towards a waiting ship.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="http://liggat.org/images/2013/painting_first.jpg" width="500" title="Painting in the Hospital" ></p>

<p>Walt&rsquo;s comment is therefore made with the recognition that he&rsquo;s noticed at least two of these things in the wild. Virtually the only constant between these two moments in the <em>Breaking Bad</em> story is the notion of that warehouse somewhere, churning out an endless supply of mediocre stock art.</p>

<p>The inclusion of, and callback to, this painting is just one more in another long line of fantastic touches by the show&rsquo;s creators.</p>
<div class="footnotes">
<hr/>
<ol>
<li id="fn:1">
<p>These events occurred in the fifth season episode, <em>Gliding all Over</em>.<a href="#fnref:1" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
<li id="fn:2">
<p>This was visible in the second season episode <em>Bit by Dead Bee</em>. Walt had just completed implementing his not-altogether-plausible &lsquo;fugue state&rsquo; alibi, and was back in chemo.<a href="#fnref:2" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
</ol>
</div>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Simulating the Birthday Paradox]]></title>
    <link href="http://liggat.org/2013/10/13/simulating-the-birthday-paradox/"/>
    <updated>2013-10-13T10:59:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://liggat.org/2013/10/13/simulating-the-birthday-paradox</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Probability theory is a pretty special branch of mathematics in the sense that it is (1) highly applicable to daily life; (2) many of its results are easily comprehensible to most people; and yet despite this (3) it remains a profoundly complex area of mathematical inquiry<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" rel="footnote">1</a></sup>.<!--more--></p>

<p>An example which perfectly encapsulates this is the <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Birthday_paradox">birthday paradox</a>. In short, it can be represented by the question:</p>

<blockquote><p>With a group of <code>N</code> randomly chosen people, how large does <code>N</code> need to be so that there&rsquo;s a 50% chance of a shared birthday within the group?</p></blockquote>

<p>The birthday paradox is a great opportunity to use some basic computation as an exploratory tool. I think more people should have the ability to use this.</p>

<h3>Finding N</h3>

<p>The group size is clearly less than or equal to 365. Above 365, we know with 100% certainty that there&rsquo;s a shared birthday somewhere<sup id="fnref:2"><a href="#fn:2" rel="footnote">2</a></sup>. Intuition (or at least my intuition before I knew the answer) usually suggests that the 50% probability threshold value for N is probably at or around the 100-150 mark. In other words, we might guess that you need 100-150 people in the group before the probability of a shared birthday is equal to a coin flip.</p>

<p>It turns out that&rsquo;s a gross overestimate. The actual value is <strong>staggeringly lower</strong> than people tend to guess:</p>

<blockquote><p>With a group size of 23 people, the probability that two people share a birthday is ~= 50.36%.</p></blockquote>

<p>This is a pretty astonishing result. It is, of course, provably true by an <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Birthday_paradox#Calculating_the_probability">analytical argument</a>, but it is actually far easier to convince oneself of its trueness with a simple computational exercise (full version on <a href="https://gist.github.com/dliggat/6963840">GitHub</a>):</p>

<figure class='code'><figcaption><span>birthday.rb: Simulate the birthday paradox </span></figcaption>
<div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
<span class='line-number'>3</span>
<span class='line-number'>4</span>
<span class='line-number'>5</span>
<span class='line-number'>6</span>
<span class='line-number'>7</span>
<span class='line-number'>8</span>
<span class='line-number'>9</span>
<span class='line-number'>10</span>
<span class='line-number'>11</span>
<span class='line-number'>12</span>
<span class='line-number'>13</span>
<span class='line-number'>14</span>
<span class='line-number'>15</span>
<span class='line-number'>16</span>
<span class='line-number'>17</span>
<span class='line-number'>18</span>
<span class='line-number'>19</span>
<span class='line-number'>20</span>
<span class='line-number'>21</span>
<span class='line-number'>22</span>
<span class='line-number'>23</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class='rb'><span class='line'><span class="c1">#!/usr/bin/env ruby</span>
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'><span class="k">def</span> <span class="nf">shared_birthday?</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">group_size</span><span class="p">)</span>
</span><span class='line'>  <span class="c1"># Generate an array with size `group_size`, and randomly assign every member a birthday.</span>
</span><span class='line'>  <span class="c1"># Return true if two members share a birthday; else return false.</span>
</span><span class='line'>  <span class="n">counter</span>   <span class="o">=</span> <span class="no">Hash</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">new</span> <span class="mi">0</span>
</span><span class='line'>  <span class="n">birthdays</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="n">group_size</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">times</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">map</span> <span class="p">{</span> <span class="nb">rand</span> <span class="mi">365</span> <span class="p">}</span>
</span><span class='line'>  <span class="n">birthdays</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">each</span> <span class="k">do</span> <span class="o">|</span><span class="n">birthday</span><span class="o">|</span>
</span><span class='line'>    <span class="n">counter</span><span class="o">[</span><span class="n">birthday</span><span class="o">]</span> <span class="o">+=</span> <span class="mi">1</span>
</span><span class='line'>    <span class="k">return</span> <span class="kp">true</span> <span class="k">if</span> <span class="n">counter</span><span class="o">[</span><span class="n">birthday</span><span class="o">]</span> <span class="o">&gt;</span> <span class="mi">1</span>
</span><span class='line'>  <span class="k">end</span>
</span><span class='line'>  <span class="kp">false</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="k">end</span>
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'><span class="k">def</span> <span class="nf">run_birthday_trials</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">group_size</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">trial_count</span><span class="p">)</span>
</span><span class='line'>  <span class="c1"># Run the shared_birthday? experiment `trial_count` times.</span>
</span><span class='line'>  <span class="c1"># Return the number of experiments which resulted in a shared birthday.</span>
</span><span class='line'>  <span class="n">successes</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="mi">0</span>
</span><span class='line'>  <span class="n">trial_count</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">times</span> <span class="p">{</span> <span class="n">successes</span> <span class="o">+=</span> <span class="mi">1</span> <span class="k">if</span> <span class="n">shared_birthday?</span> <span class="n">group_size</span> <span class="p">}</span>
</span><span class='line'>  <span class="n">successes</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="k">end</span>
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'><span class="n">run_birthday_trials</span> <span class="mi">23</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="mi">1000</span>
</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p>This very simple code runs a series of birthday-paradox experiments &ndash; within each trial, it generates a group of people, and tests for the presence of a shared birthday. By doing this repeatedly, a thousand times in this case, we can approximate the actual probability of a shared birthday with a particular group size.</p>

<h3>Why Bother Sharing This?</h3>

<p>To any mildly-capable programmer<sup id="fnref:3"><a href="#fn:3" rel="footnote">3</a></sup>, none of this is particularly interesting or novel. Many of us in this line of work have a pretty decent mathematical background, and have done all sorts of these little simulation exercises in the past, both academically and professionally.</p>

<p>However, it is my firm belief that a great many people could stand to benefit if the ability to use basic computational principles and tools were more widely disseminated. Windows and OS X machines ship with browsers with full JavaScript runtimes; Ruby and Python runtimes <em>ship</em> with OS X, and can easily be added to Windows. The tools of exploratory computation are everywhere &ndash; but very few people were ever given the knowledge to use them. This could be easily remedied by offering basic Computer Science in high school, either on its own, or as part of a math or science class. This might be the case today for all I know, but my own experience on that front was not encouraging<sup id="fnref:4"><a href="#fn:4" rel="footnote">4</a></sup>.</p>

<p>To anyone even moderately interested in the vast possibilities that are unlocked with a bit of computational knowledge, I strongly encourage you to check out <a href="http://www.codecademy.com/">Code Academy</a> or <a href="http://projecteuler.net">Project Euler</a>. Of all of Steve Jobs&#8217; various witty and insightful aphorisms, the notion that a computer is a <em>bicycle for the mind</em> has always struck me as especially apt.</p>
<div class="footnotes">
<hr/>
<ol>
<li id="fn:1">
<p>Unlike, say, <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Real_analysis">real analysis</a>, which has zero applicability to daily life and is not comprehensible by most people, including myself.<a href="#fnref:1" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
<li id="fn:2">
<p>By the <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pigeonhole_principle">pigeonhole principle</a>: If we have 365 pigeonholes into which we place 366 objects, at least one pigeonhole must contain more than one object.<a href="#fnref:2" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
<li id="fn:3">
<p><a href="http://www.codinghorror.com/blog/2007/02/why-cant-programmers-program.html">FizzBuzz</a>, as ever, remains a cautionary tale about our industry.<a href="#fnref:3" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
<li id="fn:4">
<p>Around the time I was in grade 11 and 12, Computer Science was <em>dropped</em> as an offering at my high school. Yes, <em>dropped</em>. Lack of demand; lack of staff to teach it. University was thus my first opportunity to gain exposure to computation as an academic/professional field.<a href="#fnref:4" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
</ol>
</div>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[On Boredom]]></title>
    <link href="http://liggat.org/2013/09/25/on-boredom/"/>
    <updated>2013-09-25T09:32:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://liggat.org/2013/09/25/on-boredom</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://teamcoco.com/video/louis-ck-springsteen-cell-phone">Another</a> of Louis C.K.&rsquo;s hilarious talk-show interview diatribes is being widely circulated on the web and Twitter right now &ndash; this time about smartphones, and why he won&rsquo;t let his children have one. It&rsquo;s well worth a watch, but his argument essentially boils down to the observation that smartphones provide a constant stream of distraction that removes the condition, boredom, that is arguably necessary for healthy self-reflection.<!--more--></p>

<p>Humour aside, I think he&rsquo;s really onto something here. Speaking personally, boredom, at least how I understood the term pre-Internet, has essentially disappeared from my life. Very few of my waking hours are spent without mental stimulation of one form or another. If I&rsquo;m waiting in a lineup, on public transport, unable to sleep, or killing time in an airport &ndash; out comes my phone, and the usual suspects <a href="http://tapbots.com/software/tweetbot/">Tweetbot</a> or <a href="http://instapaper.com">Instapaper</a> will occupy me for the duration of that transitory event. Even when I&rsquo;m cooking, cycling, exercising, or walking the dog, I&rsquo;m spared from any possible exposure to boredom through a now-years-old tendency to listen to podcasts<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" rel="footnote">1</a></sup> or audiobooks whenever my hands are occupied.</p>

<p>As a technophile and enthusiast-for-non-boredom, it&rsquo;s hard for me to know how I should feel about this state of affairs. It&rsquo;s fairly easy to reason that since happiness may only exist in a world with sadness, then perhaps excitement and boredom share a similar, inextricable, symbiosis? I certainly don&rsquo;t currently <em>feel</em> like my life: work, personal or otherwise, lacks excitement &ndash; far from it. But this is 2013 &ndash; what about 2033 when we have <em>{insert your favourite prediction about technology two decades out<sup id="fnref:2"><a href="#fn:2" rel="footnote">2</a></sup>}</em>?</p>

<p>Kids born in the recent past seem to be genuinely puzzled when they encounter a display which is not touch-sensitive, and I find it likely that this will be their response at the very notion of boredom as a concept in the years to come. I feel privileged to have grown up during that big epoch-defining<sup id="fnref:3"><a href="#fn:3" rel="footnote">3</a></sup> transition from pre-Internet to our now permanent state of connectedness. I have vivid memories of what it was like to have only four TV channels and a few toys and books as the sole available vehicles for entertainment; and still more vivid memories of the initial realizations that I now had the power to answer virtually any question I could conceive of with just a few keystrokes.</p>

<p>I don&rsquo;t think the significance of this shift has been truly internalized by many people yet. Other than Louis C.K., of course.</p>
<div class="footnotes">
<hr/>
<ol>
<li id="fn:1">
<p>I love podcasts, but my subscriptions have grown well beyond the point of my ability to actually listen to them all.<a href="#fnref:1" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
<li id="fn:2">
<p>Visible screens inscribed on contact lenses?<a href="#fnref:2" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
<li id="fn:3">
<p>I am convinced that historians will have a well-defined name for this period in decades/centuries to come.<a href="#fnref:3" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
</ol>
</div>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Farewell, Old Friend]]></title>
    <link href="http://liggat.org/2013/09/09/farewell-old-friend/"/>
    <updated>2013-09-09T15:39:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://liggat.org/2013/09/09/farewell-old-friend</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>iOS 7<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" rel="footnote">1</a></sup> and a new iPhone are imminent. <!--more--> Tomorrow is Apple Christmas Morning.</p>

<p>It&rsquo;s the end of the road for <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Iphone_4s">you</a>, my old friend.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="http://liggat.org/images/2013/iphone_4s.png" width="400" title="'iPhone 4S'" ></p>
<div class="footnotes">
<hr/>
<ol>
<li id="fn:1">
<p>I fully expect this screenshot to look hilariously out of date once iOS 7 is rolled out everywhere and the new aesthetic is &lsquo;normal&rsquo; and not at all novel. I won&rsquo;t miss stitched leather one bit.<a href="#fnref:1" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
</ol>
</div>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Efficient Currency Conversion]]></title>
    <link href="http://liggat.org/2013/09/06/efficient-currency-conversion/"/>
    <updated>2013-09-06T09:52:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://liggat.org/2013/09/06/efficient-currency-conversion</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I&rsquo;m willing to bet that Canadians, on average, do more foreign exchange (forex) transactions than citizens of many other countries. This is an obvious consequence of the significant shopping and investing opportunities south of the <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/49th_parallel_north#The_Canada_.E2.80.93_United_States_border">49th parallel</a>. Moreover, plenty of Canadian software contractors such as myself find themselves billing in American dollars (<span class="money usd">USD</span>) occasionally.</p>

<!--more-->


<p>Unfortunately, currency conversion to and from Canadian dollars (<span class="money cad">CAD</span>) is no exception to that frequently-bemoaned axiom of Canadian life: it&rsquo;s expensive, and domestic vendors extract a cosy profit margin (i.e. banks in this case). This phenomenon is perennially annoying<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" rel="footnote">1</a></sup> in general, but especially so when we&rsquo;re talking about <em>bits in a database</em>, which is all money really is at this point.</p>

<p>However, it turns out there&rsquo;s a neat trick you can pull off to convert <span class="money cad">CAD</span> ⇔ <span class="money usd">USD</span> [almost] optimally called <strong>Norbert&rsquo;s Gambit</strong>. There are plenty of <a href="http://canadiancouchpotato.com/2013/07/09/norberts-gambit-at-cibc/">other</a> <a href="http://www.canadiancapitalist.com/a-foolproof-method-to-convert-canadian-dollars-into-us-dollars/">blog</a> <a href="http://www.michaeljamesonmoney.com/2012/03/trying-norbert-gambit-at-bmo.html">posts</a> out there explaining this &ndash; I thought I&rsquo;d throw my hat into the ring also by documenting my experience. <em>This hopefully goes without saying, but this is a personal record of events by a layman of finance, not the provision of financial advice. Your mileage may vary &ndash; do your own research.</em></p>

<p><a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wikipedia:Too_long;_didn't_read">tl; dr</a> version:</p>

<blockquote><p>In conversion rate terms, this is a gain of $138.25 CAD over what the bank offered on the $5,000.00 USD conversion.</p></blockquote>

<h3>Background</h3>

<p><img class="right" src="http://liggat.org/images/forex.jpg" width="325" title="'Forex'" >
For the sake of completeness, it is worth mentioning the concept of the <strong>mid-market rate</strong> in forex. Although we tend to think of a unit of currency having a fixed, reversible value in a different currency (e.g. <span class="money usd price">$1.00 USD</span> = <span class="money cad price">$1.05 CAD</span>), generally no one will sell you the opposite currency at that rate. Currency conversion boards seen in train stations and airports illustrate this concept; they show <em>two rates</em> &ndash; vendors will transact in the opposite currency at a higher or lower rate, depending on whether you wish to buy or sell, respectively. The difference, of course, is their profit<sup id="fnref:2"><a href="#fn:2" rel="footnote">2</a></sup>.</p>

<p>The mid-market rate is theoretically equidistant between the two rates, and it&rsquo;s the rate we would ideally achieve when we participate in a forex transaction. Mid-market rates for currency pairs are reported on <a href="http://finance.google.com">Google Finance</a>, <a href="http://xe.com">XE</a>, etc.</p>

<h3>Objective</h3>

<p>My objective on the morning of <strong>2013-09-05</strong> was to convert <span class="money usd price">$5,000.00 USD</span> to <span class="money cad">CAD</span> as efficiently as possible. The value of that sum of money, in <span class="money cad">CAD</span>, implied by the mid-market rate at the time was <span class="money cad price">$5,252.15 CAD</span>. In optimization terms, this is a clear <em>upper bound</em> on the quantity I&rsquo;m trying to maximize.</p>

<h5>Option A: Bank Transfer</h5>

<p>As far as I&rsquo;m aware, most Canadian banks allow for a immediate conversion of <span class="money cad">CAD</span> ⇔ <span class="money usd">USD</span> online from a <span class="money cad">CAD</span>-denominated account to a <span class="money usd">USD</span>-denominated account or vice-versa. In a matter of seconds, one can perform this transaction. The price for this convenience, however, is the suboptimal forex rate that they apply<sup id="fnref:3"><a href="#fn:3" rel="footnote">3</a></sup>. My bank offered me <span class="money cad price">$5,112.50 CAD</span> in exchange for <span class="money usd price">$5,000.00 USD</span> on <strong>2013-09-05</strong>. Easy, and hassle-free &ndash; but we can do better.</p>

<h5>Option B: Third Party Currency Trader</h5>

<p>Rather than use the functionality built into online banking, we can outsource the conversion to an outfit like <a href="http://xe.com">XE</a>. It&rsquo;s a bit of a hassle to set up, and the website is straight out of 2002, but that aside, it does exactly what it says on the tin. You book a trade; money gets withdrawn in one currency (e.g. <span class="money cad">CAD</span>) and shows up a few days later, converted, in the other currency (e.g. <span class="money usd">USD</span>). I&rsquo;ve used XE on very seldom occasions across a duration of many years and it has always worked out great. On the morning of <strong>2013-09-05</strong>, they quoted a rate of <span class="money cad price">$5,186.72 CAD</span> in exchange for <span class="money usd price">$5,000.00 USD</span>. Not quite the mid-market rate, but this is already an improvement of <span class="money cad price">$74.22 CAD</span> over Option A.</p>

<h3>Option C: Norbert&rsquo;s Gambit</h3>

<p>The process for doing even better relies on what I understand to be the following approximate logic:</p>

<ul>
<li>Start with money in a given currency, say, <span class="money usd">USD</span>.</li>
<li>Use that money to purchase units of a security that lists on both the NYSE and TSX. Through the magic of <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Arbitrage">arbitrage</a>, the security on both markets will tend towards an identical price (even if traded in different currencies).</li>
<li>Once you own it on the NYSE, ask your broker to swap it for equivalent units on the TSX.</li>
<li>Sell those TSX-listed units of the security, now denominated in <span class="money cad">CAD</span>.</li>
<li>Congratulations &ndash; all going well, you just converted <span class="money usd ">USD</span> to <span class="money cad">CAD</span> at essentially the mid-market rate. Provided, of course, the security didn&rsquo;t fluctuate much in value between the two trades.</li>
</ul>


<h3>Outcome</h3>

<p>In practice, it seems you don&rsquo;t need to worry too much about the price fluctuation between trades. An <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Exchange-traded_fund">ETF</a> with symbol <a href="http://www.horizonsetfs.com/pub/en/etfs/?etf=DLR&amp;">DLR</a> was apparently created as a stable vehicle for precisely this manoeuvre. I followed <a href="http://www.michaeljamesonmoney.com/2012/03/trying-norbert-gambit-at-bmo.html">these instructions</a> closely and it worked out exactly as described. On <strong>2013-09-05</strong>, I phoned the broker<sup id="fnref:4"><a href="#fn:4" rel="footnote">4</a></sup>, bought DLR.U with <span class="money usd">USD</span>, exchanged it for DLR, and immediately sold to receive <span class="money cad">CAD</span>.</p>

<p>In actual numeric terms, I bought <span class="money usd">502 DLR.U × $9.97 USD/DLR.U</span> = <span class="money usd price">$5,004.94 USD</span> and subsequently sold <span class="money cad">502 DLR × $10.47 CAD/DLR</span> = <span class="money cad price">$5,255.94 CAD</span>. In conversion rate terms, this is a gain of <span class="money cad price">$138.25 CAD</span> over what the bank offered on the <span class="money usd price">$5,000.00 USD</span> conversion, and the achieved rate <em>is</em> the mid-market rate to three decimal places.</p>

<h4>But wait! There&rsquo;s More</h4>

<p>We can&rsquo;t just call this a <span class="money cad price">$138.25 CAD</span> job well done though. I had to execute two trades&hellip; and trading has transaction costs. Depending on your bank/broker, and various policies, etc, this could be anywhere from $5.00 to $30.00 each direction. So the savings realized in this scenario is actually: <span class="money cad price">$138.25 CAD &ndash; 2 × { cost per trade }</span>. Still, it&rsquo;s a pretty good outcome for doing basically nothing but a bit of one-time research. And the savings scale in proportion to the amount converted!</p>

<p>This is part of the reason<sup id="fnref:5"><a href="#fn:5" rel="footnote">5</a></sup> why banks are so ludicrously profitable. It&rsquo;s all just bits in a database&hellip; but the act of flipping those bits can come at a higher or lower cost depending on how you tell the bank to manipulate them.</p>

<h4>Summary of Implied Rates</h4>

<p>Here&rsquo;s the various rates summarized. Note that the Norbert&rsquo;s Gambit result <strong>does not</strong> include the cost of the trades, which must be accounted for in practice.</p>

<div class="summary">
  <table>
    <thead>
      <tr>
        <td>Method</td>
        <td>Starting Value</td>
        <td>Resulting Value</td>
      </tr>
    </thead>
    <tbody>
      <tr>
        <td>Bank Transfer</td>
        <td><span class="money usd">$5,000.00 USD</span></td>
        <td><span class="money cad">$5,112.50 CAD</span></td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>Third Party Conversion</td>
        <td><span class="money usd">$5,000.00 USD</span></td>
        <td><span class="money cad">$5,186.72 CAD</span></td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>Norbert&#8217;s Gambit</td>
        <td><span class="money usd">$5,000.00 USD</span></td>
        <td><span class="money cad">$5,250.75 CAD</span></td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>Theoretical Mid-Market Optimum</td>
        <td><span class="money usd">$5,000.00 USD</span></td>
        <td><span class="money cad">$5,252.15 CAD</span></td>
      </tr>
    </tbody>
  </table>
</div>


<p>One last remark: it&rsquo;s probably wise to be circumspect within any dealings with your bank when setting up accounts for this or actually executing the trade. Norbert&rsquo;s Gambit<sup id="fnref:6"><a href="#fn:6" rel="footnote">6</a></sup> is a perfectly legitimate operation, but it&rsquo;s pretty easy to imagine banks getting upset at this reduction in their effortless-profit, and potentially erecting obstacles.</p>
<div class="footnotes">
<hr/>
<ol>
<li id="fn:1">
<p>Especially to a Scotsman.<a href="#fnref:1" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
<li id="fn:2">
<p>Sometimes these airport outfits add an extra &lsquo;fee&rsquo; on top, as if getting to charge a spread that they pick isn&rsquo;t already a &lsquo;fee&rsquo;.<a href="#fnref:2" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
<li id="fn:3">
<p>Even if the rate is bad, for smaller amounts of money, the convenience is worth it. It&rsquo;s only well into the four-digit zone does this start to become a worthwhile consideration.<a href="#fnref:3" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
<li id="fn:4">
<p>I had to phone rather than do this over the web because apparently the bank&rsquo;s online systems can&rsquo;t handle DLR.U. I don&rsquo;t imagine there&rsquo;s a sound technical reason for this outside of &ldquo;banks being banks&rdquo;, but the guy on the phone was super polite and efficient at getting it done, and didn&rsquo;t charge any extra for the phone service over what it normally costs to transact online.<a href="#fnref:4" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
<li id="fn:5">
<p>Other reasons include real and artificial barriers to entry, and riskless profits thanks to taxpayer guarantees on various loans issued, but all of that is a rant for another day.<a href="#fnref:5" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
<li id="fn:6">
<p>New bucket list item &ndash; invent a thing that comes to be known as <strong>Liggat&rsquo;s Gambit</strong>. How cool would it be to have a <em>gambit</em> to your name&hellip;<a href="#fnref:6" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
</ol>
</div>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[A Golden Age of Software]]></title>
    <link href="http://liggat.org/2013/09/03/a-comparatively-golden-age-of-software/"/>
    <updated>2013-09-03T17:57:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://liggat.org/2013/09/03/a-comparatively-golden-age-of-software</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>As someone to whom pessimism and cynicism come naturally, I&rsquo;m often more inclined to complain about things than sit and reflect on positivity. However, I think it&rsquo;s worth taking a moment to acknowledge one thing: we live in a golden age of software right now, at least relative to any point in the past.</p>

<!--more-->


<p>This is not to suggest there aren&rsquo;t problems. For example &ndash; I&rsquo;m incredulous to the point of <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Facepalm">speechlessness</a> whenever I use a television set with any current digital TV product at just how universally terrible it all is. I&rsquo;m not at all interested in live TV or any sports or the various trappings, and thus am not in the target market &ndash; but I can scarcely believe people willingly buy these altars of frustration. Just consider, for a moment, the breathtaking lack of product and user-focus that this on-screen prompt represents:</p>

<blockquote><p>This programming is also available in High-Definition. Would you prefer to switch to that instead?</p></blockquote>

<p>All the way from product development, through system design and implementation, to QA, and finally deployment, with presumably a good few boardroom demos along the way &ndash; apparently no one thought about the absurdity of <em>even bothering to ask</em> if HD is preferable to the viewer over SD<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" rel="footnote">1</a></sup>. I could rant all day about examples like this. Clearly humanity&rsquo;s grand experiment with software has not yet reached its zenith.</p>

<p>However, when I reflect on my career in software &ndash; now close to entering its tenth year &ndash; the progress of that period from <code>2003</code> to <code>now</code>, just in terms of my own personal &lsquo;software environment&rsquo;, is truly staggering to behold:</p>

<ul>
<li><strong>Operating System</strong>: I used to get work done in Windows XP, which, on good days, would manage to not kernel panic. Linux was around, but &ndash; only if you didn&rsquo;t care about digital cameras or WiFi, and enjoyed endless tinkering with device drivers. For all of Unix&rsquo;s enduring importance from the seventies onwards &ndash; Windows &amp; Microsoft were the absolute ironclad conduit between most people and computation. Compare that to today &ndash; it&rsquo;s worlds apart.</li>
<li><strong>Productivity</strong>: It used to be that if it had words it went into a <code>.doc</code>, and if it had numbers it went into a <code>.xls</code>. End of story. Now, I have very little real need for an office suite &ndash; all the various little uses cases have been unbundled into more suitable specialized tools. Notes go into Evernote. <a href="http://www.acqualia.com/soulver/">Soulver</a> and <a href="http://www.alfredapp.com/">Alfred</a> for impromptu calculations. Google Docs (and soon, iWork for iCloud) for persisted spreadsheets. <a href="http://www.freshbooks.com/">Freshbooks</a> for accounting. <a href="http://www.goodiware.com/goodreader.html">GoodReader</a> for annotating PDFs. Etc. Excel remains a peerless tool at the high end &ndash; but it overserves most people&rsquo;s, or at least my, needs in the vast majority of cases.</li>
<li><strong>Email</strong>: I have vivid memories of the days when an email account was tightly coupled to a single physical computer, almost by axiom. No web access, no multi-gigabyte, searchable, hosted backing store, and certainly no IMAP, push notifications, or synchronized read state between multiple devices. Mail host storage was a jealously guarded commodity &ndash; and shunted off their systems to your <em>sole</em> machine with haste.</li>
<li><strong>Version Control</strong>: God help you if you attempted a merge and got it wrong with early (and hell, probably current, if they still make it) versions of Source Safe. And branches? Forget it. There&rsquo;s no terror quite like the terror of a computer-science co-op student who is pretty sure he just fouled up the company VSS repository (me; circa 2004). Today, git, especially used within <a href="http://github.com">GitHub</a>, verges on perfection for covering the problem space of &lsquo;version control&rsquo;. I&rsquo;m not sure I can name a piece of software more powerful, or useful, or robust, or complete at doing the job it was designed to do.</li>
<li><strong>Programming Languages</strong>: Dynamic, strongly-typed, ultra-expressive languages like <code>ruby</code> and <code>python</code> have a rich history, but they&rsquo;ve only really come into widespread use in the latter portion of the 2000s. I learned to program in <code>C++</code>, and looking back, I&rsquo;m surprised that didn&rsquo;t put me off the whole enterprise<sup id="fnref:2"><a href="#fn:2" rel="footnote">2</a></sup>. <code>Java</code> is worse &ndash; the hideous jargon endemic to its ecosystem and infuriating toolchains for starters, let alone the needlessly-verbose language itself.</li>
<li><strong>Writing Code</strong>: Visual Studio or Eclipse<sup id="fnref:3"><a href="#fn:3" rel="footnote">3</a></sup> versus <a href="http://www.sublimetext.com/2">Sublime Text 2</a> &ndash; enough said. IDEs still have a role to be sure, especially for developing native software, but I dislike using them, and I&rsquo;m glad I mostly don&rsquo;t have to.</li>
</ul>


<p>In writing this, I&rsquo;ve basically deduced what are actually two pretty obvious observations:</p>

<ol>
<li>Current software which already had a predecessor equivalent in the past has gotten <em>profoundly</em> better.</li>
<li>Devices/objects which weren&rsquo;t software driven in the past and now are (e.g. TVs, cars) need to, and presumably will, improve drastically.</li>
</ol>


<p>It&rsquo;ll be fun to revisit this post in another ten years and opine, hopefully, about how good television<sup id="fnref:4"><a href="#fn:4" rel="footnote">4</a></sup> software is and that it has since joined the ranks of productivity, email, version control, etc. I sure hope so.</p>

<p>In the meantime, get rid of the damn HD prompt, <em>please</em>.</p>
<div class="footnotes">
<hr/>
<ol>
<li id="fn:1">
<p>Honestly, this was on a shipping digital TV unit that I used.<a href="#fnref:1" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
<li id="fn:2">
<p>To be fair, I did hate the first half of UBC&rsquo;s <code>C++</code>-based CPSC 152 until things started to click about two-thirds in. And I do think new programmers should be exposed to the world of pointers and manual memory management &ndash; but I would argue that <code>C</code> is a better environment than <code>C++</code> for that.<a href="#fnref:2" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
<li id="fn:3">
<p>Apparently people still use this. Oh, the humanity.<a href="#fnref:3" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
<li id="fn:4">
<p>Assuming &lsquo;television&rsquo; is even a relevant concept in 10 years. I would not be at all surprised if 100% of the software and network functionality moves to phones and tablets, and TVs become nothing more than dumb wireless output devices for their content. Initiatives like AirPlay, locked thought it is to the Apple ecosystem, are a pretty big step in this direction.<a href="#fnref:4" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
</ol>
</div>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Automate All the Things]]></title>
    <link href="http://liggat.org/2013/08/06/automate-all-the-things/"/>
    <updated>2013-08-06T13:04:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://liggat.org/2013/08/06/automate-all-the-things</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I&rsquo;ve spent much of my career in software with automation an implicit and often explicit goal: in testing, in environment creation and deployments, in backups, etc. A conspicuous absence from this list has been the actual development machines I spend many hours each day using, which for me are my Mac desktop and laptop, and occasionally a VM or two. Traditionally, these have ended up at their working state through hours upon hours of gentle tinkering. It&rsquo;s a case of the cobbler&rsquo;s children having no shoes<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" rel="footnote">1</a></sup>, I suppose.</p>

<!--more-->


<p>To correct this error, I&rsquo;ve spent a portion of the past few weeks getting up to speed with GitHub Inc&rsquo;s excellent Puppet-based <a href="https://boxen.github.com">Boxen</a> tool for provisioning their own internal OS X 10.8 Mountain Lion machines. Although the learning curve is not exactly shallow, and the documentation sparse at times &ndash; the payoff has been tremendous. You can use it to script absolutely every aspect of your development machine(s), resulting in the same degree of repeatability and auditability that we normally reserve for production servers.</p>

<h3>My Boxen</h3>

<p>From a clean install<sup id="fnref:2"><a href="#fn:2" rel="footnote">2</a></sup>, I&rsquo;ve now got a fully-specified, version-controlled, <a href="https://github.com/dliggat/boxen">boxen instance</a> that, at a stroke can:</p>

<ul>
<li>Set up, and store my GitHub credentials<sup id="fnref:3"><a href="#fn:3" rel="footnote">3</a></sup> for convenient push/pull to authorized repositories</li>
<li>Install system-wide versions of git, node.js, and rubies (1.8.7, 1.9.3, 2.0.0)<sup id="fnref:4"><a href="#fn:4" rel="footnote">4</a></sup></li>
<li>Install standard apps like Dropbox, Chrome, iTerm and even VMWare Fusion</li>
<li>Set my fussy OS X system preferences for the Dock, Dashboard, Trackpad, etc</li>
<li>Clone my <a href="https://github.com/dliggat/dotfiles">dotfile repository</a> and define various symlinks from <code>~</code> into that repo; e.g. <code>~/.bashrc -&gt; /Users/daveliggat/git/dotfiles/bashrc</code>, plus define any other symlinks or environment variables that I might want to have</li>
<li>Install system-wide gems (e.g. <code>pry</code>) and homebrew packages (e.g. <code>sqlite</code>, <code>markdown</code>)</li>
<li>Define and spin-up resources needed on a per project basis, which for a rails app likely includes local MySQL or PostgreSQL instances, a cloned git repository, and a redis server</li>
<li>Set up my text editor of choice, <a href="http://www.sublimetext.com/2">Sublime Text 2</a>, and install the plethora of plugins and preferences that I use</li>
</ul>


<figure class='code'><figcaption><span>Boxen/Puppet allows encapsulation of automation areas into &#8216;classes&#8217; </span></figcaption>
<div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
<span class='line-number'>3</span>
<span class='line-number'>4</span>
<span class='line-number'>5</span>
<span class='line-number'>6</span>
<span class='line-number'>7</span>
<span class='line-number'>8</span>
<span class='line-number'>9</span>
<span class='line-number'>10</span>
<span class='line-number'>11</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class='rb'><span class='line'><span class="k">class</span> <span class="ss">people</span><span class="p">:</span><span class="ss">:dliggat</span> <span class="p">{</span>
</span><span class='line'>  <span class="n">notify</span> <span class="p">{</span> <span class="s1">&#39;class people::dliggat declared&#39;</span><span class="p">:</span> <span class="p">}</span>
</span><span class='line'>  <span class="kp">include</span> <span class="ss">people</span><span class="p">:</span><span class="ss">:dliggat</span><span class="o">::</span><span class="n">apps</span>
</span><span class='line'>  <span class="kp">include</span> <span class="ss">people</span><span class="p">:</span><span class="ss">:dliggat</span><span class="o">::</span><span class="n">dotfiles</span>
</span><span class='line'>  <span class="kp">include</span> <span class="ss">people</span><span class="p">:</span><span class="ss">:dliggat</span><span class="o">::</span><span class="n">git</span>
</span><span class='line'>  <span class="kp">include</span> <span class="ss">people</span><span class="p">:</span><span class="ss">:dliggat</span><span class="o">::</span><span class="n">homebrew</span>
</span><span class='line'>  <span class="kp">include</span> <span class="ss">people</span><span class="p">:</span><span class="ss">:dliggat</span><span class="o">::</span><span class="n">symlinks</span>
</span><span class='line'>  <span class="kp">include</span> <span class="ss">people</span><span class="p">:</span><span class="ss">:dliggat</span><span class="o">::</span><span class="n">loginitems</span>
</span><span class='line'>  <span class="kp">include</span> <span class="ss">people</span><span class="p">:</span><span class="ss">:dliggat</span><span class="o">::</span><span class="n">osx</span>
</span><span class='line'>  <span class="kp">include</span> <span class="ss">people</span><span class="p">:</span><span class="ss">:dliggat</span><span class="o">::</span><span class="n">sublime_text_2</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="p">}</span>
</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p>Assuming you&rsquo;re inclined to care about things like this, it&rsquo;s hard to overstate the satisfaction of kicking off this script and coming back to a fully-provisioned machine a couple of hours later. Best of all, Boxen is cumulative and <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Idempotence">idempotent</a>, so changes can be made to my Boxen install (and then always specified and available in future) and re-run without worrying about it blowing up because it encounters its own previous completions.</p>

<p>If anything, everything I&rsquo;ve written here <em>understates</em> how capable Boxen is. I&rsquo;m presently using it for a couple of machines in a home office &ndash; GitHub uses it for their <em>entire</em> corporate fleet of MacBook Pros. Eventually the plan is that this becomes a centerpiece of the &lsquo;onboarding&rsquo; experience at <a href="http://plyfe.com">Plyfe</a>, so new people can be productive instantly without messing around with <code>rvm</code> or <code>redis-server</code> or whatever else.</p>

<h3>tl;dr &ndash; Automation Rules!</h3>

<p><a href="https://plus.google.com/+BrunoOliveira">Bruno Oliveira</a> captured the essence of why automation is so great in a widely circulated <a href="https://plus.google.com/+BrunoOliveira/posts/MGxauXypb1Y">chart</a> a year or so ago:</p>

<p><img class="fancybox center" src="http://liggat.org/images/geeks.png" width="550" title="'Geeks'" ></p>

<h3>Appendix, or Why I like OS X</h3>

<p>Occasionally I&rsquo;m asked why I like OS X so much. There&rsquo;s a certain subset of the tech population that still thinks, apparently with genuine conviction, that Apple only makes toys. It&rsquo;s a bizarre and/or myopic belief in a world where Google Inc is known to be one of the largest institutional buyers of MacBook Pros (and I know from first-hand experience they certainly aren&rsquo;t buying them to mess about with GarageBand), but it persists.</p>

<p>Anyway, the very existence of projects like Boxen is just about the best answer I can give in response. There&rsquo;s so much cool stuff going on in software these days, and a huge portion of it is done with OS X. I might be moving in the wrong circles, but I simply don&rsquo;t see this level of innovation going on in the Windows world. And given how inherently less scriptable Windows is than anything Unix-based, it&rsquo;s hard to imagine an equal Windows-based peer of Boxen emerging anytime soon.</p>

<p>I like to think of OS X as having the best of both worlds of Windows and Linux: user-facing conveniences, plus a modern UI, plus a high degree of scriptability, plus access to forty-years worth of Unix utilities, <strong>minus</strong> the interminable and recurrent headaches with video card drivers, etc that you (or at least I) get with Linux. If I&rsquo;m restricted to buying Apple gear to get that combination for now, so be it.</p>
<div class="footnotes">
<hr/>
<ol>
<li id="fn:1">
<p>As also remarked by Gary Larizza in what turned out to be a <a href="http://garylarizza.com/blog/2013/02/15/puppet-plus-github-equals-laptop-love/">highly useful Boxen primer</a>.<a href="#fnref:1" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
<li id="fn:2">
<p>Via the Mac App Store to install the Xcode developer tools which provide the system ruby and git binaries necessary for Boxen to bootstrap itself.<a href="#fnref:2" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
<li id="fn:3">
<p>Using the method of https repository access and the OS X system keychain, not ssh keys.<a href="#fnref:3" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
<li id="fn:4">
<p>A happy side benefit to letting boxen manage ruby versions is the obviation of somewhat horrible kludges like <code>.rvmrc</code> files in ruby project directories.<a href="#fnref:4" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
</ol>
</div>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
