<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Twitter | Liggat.org]]></title>
  <link href="http://liggat.org/blog/categories/twitter/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://liggat.org/"/>
  <updated>2014-05-09T16:41:17-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://liggat.org/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Dave Liggat]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[@liggs Is Now @dliggat]]></title>
    <link href="http://liggat.org/2014/02/20/at-liggs-is-now-at-dliggat/"/>
    <updated>2014-02-20T23:20:23-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://liggat.org/2014/02/20/at-liggs-is-now-at-dliggat</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I&rsquo;ve changed my Twitter handle from @liggs to <a href="https://twitter.com/dliggat">@dliggat</a>, as part of a general username consolidation that&rsquo;s been nagging me for a while. I figured it was worth marking the <em>occasion</em> with a site entry, given how much I use Twitter.</p>

<!--more-->


<p>In case you&rsquo;re wondering, it&rsquo;s quite easy to swap two Twitter handles with a <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Swap_(computer_science)#Using_a_temporary_variable">3-way switch</a>, so long as you control both handles.</p>

<ol>
<li>In one browser, I opened <strong>@dliggat</strong> to <a href="https://twitter.com/settings/account">https://twitter.com/settings/account</a></li>
<li>In a seperate browser (Chrome instead of Safari in my case, but a <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Privacy_mode">private browser</a> session would work also) I also opened <strong>@liggs</strong> to <a href="https://twitter.com/settings/account">https://twitter.com/settings/account</a></li>
<li>I renamed <strong>@dliggat</strong> to <em>@dliggattemp</em>. Once this is confirmed, the next two steps need to be completed as quickly as possible.</li>
<li>I renamed <strong>@liggs</strong> to <strong>@dliggat</strong>.</li>
<li>I renamed <em>@dliggattemp</em> to <strong>@liggs</strong>.</li>
</ol>


<p>It all worked out without a hitch. <a href="https://twitter.com/dliggat">@dliggat</a> it is from now on.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Tweet Archive]]></title>
    <link href="http://liggat.org/2013/05/07/tweet-archive/"/>
    <updated>2013-05-07T09:55:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://liggat.org/2013/05/07/tweet-archive</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>When Twitter announced in late 2012 that its users could download their tweet archive, it had a begrudging whiff about it. Given the company’s recent heavy-handedness with API access for not only 3rd-party clients but also complementary services such as Flipboard, I was somewhat surprised it even arrived as promised months earlier. <!--more--> I have no insight into the machinations of Twitter Inc. whatsoever, but for some reason I imagine an executive suite very reluctant to relinquish sole ownership of the veritable treasure trove of historical tweets. However, the constant haranguing by their power users, as well as a general environment that frowns upon overtly blatant lock-in (Google Takeout and the Data Liberation Front do a pretty good job setting a decent industry standard here) probably swung the balance.</p>

<p>This leads me to speculate that Twitter didn’t foresee what an incredible enhancement to their product that Tweet Archive actually is. To look back at previous tweets, retweets and favourites is like a time machine for visiting my own personality in the past. It is truly fascinating to see what I was interested in <code>$X $TIME_UNITS</code> ago, and consequently, I’m tweeting, retweeting, and favouriting more now &ndash; just for the pure whimsical pleasure of viewing this data in the future. Twitter has relinquished a measure of control over its service, and has consequently ‘locked-in’, at least me, ever more. This feels like a nice all-around dynamic &ndash; they’ve given me more control over my data, and have managed to bring me closer into the fold as a user as a result.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
