<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Tech_societal | Liggat.org]]></title>
  <link href="http://liggat.org/blog/categories/tech-societal/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://liggat.org/"/>
  <updated>2014-12-16T14:39:38-08:00</updated>
  <id>http://liggat.org/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Dave Liggat]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Everyone Should Use Twitter]]></title>
    <link href="http://liggat.org/2014/08/27/everyone-should-use-twitter/"/>
    <updated>2014-08-27T15:20:45-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://liggat.org/2014/08/27/everyone-should-use-twitter</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Twitter&rsquo;s role in the public sphere is a contradictory one. It is at once ubiquious – adorning all manner of billboards and signs, not to mention the lower fifth of the screen of cable news broadcasts – and yet almost entirely foreign to those who do not use it. That last clause verges on the tautological, but the emphasis is on <em>foreign</em>; I submit that Twitter is <em>bizarre</em> and outright <em>strange</em> to its non-users to a much greater extent than is true in the case of Facebook or just about any of the other prominent social web services.<!--more--></p>

<p>Although Twitter&rsquo;s ubiquity ensures that just about everyone has <em>heard</em> of it, and may even be aware that it has developed into a substantial forum for worldwide discourse, I get the sense that most people have never been shown a single, compelling reason why they might personally trouble to open an account.</p>

<p>As a devoted, adoring user of the service<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" rel="footnote">1</a></sup>, this strikes me as a mild tragedy. It is understandable why many people might feel this way; bootstrapping an account from naught to useful is not an especially easy task, and is fraught with several meaningful obstacles:</p>

<ul>
<li><strong>The Bootstrapping Problem</strong>: Twitter gets more interesting with each additional account you discover and follow<sup id="fnref:2"><a href="#fn:2" rel="footnote">2</a></sup>. However, at the dawn of an account – with zero follows – Twitter&rsquo;s &lsquo;interestingness&rsquo; is at a minimum, as low as it will ever be. This is not encouraging to a newcomer.</li>
<li><strong>Utility</strong>: As a consequence, it is not at all clear to a newcomer what possible utility they might receive from this new account. Moreover, newcomers seem to believe that the primary purpose of Twitter is in <em>tweeting</em><sup id="fnref:3"><a href="#fn:3" rel="footnote">3</a></sup>, when in actual fact, <em>reading the timeline</em> is the main reason it&rsquo;s worth having an account. To be sure, it&rsquo;s fun to participate in conversations once in a while, but one can receive an enormous amount of value from Twitter simply by following a set of interesting accounts, reading their updates, and perhaps never once sending a tweet.</li>
<li><strong>Esotericism</strong>: Twitter pioneered, or at least greatly popularized, several new dynamics such as the asymmetric follower/following relationship and <code>@</code>-mentioning. It also has its own conventions which are opaque from the outset<sup id="fnref:4"><a href="#fn:4" rel="footnote">4</a></sup>. Although all of this is well understood by regular users, I get the impression it is intimidating to start with.</li>
</ul>


<p>Twitter has visibly attempted to address these issues<sup id="fnref:5"><a href="#fn:5" rel="footnote">5</a></sup>, though not satisfactorially I would argue. The onboarding process addresses the bootstrapping problem to a degree, but that&rsquo;s only useful once a newcomer has been convinced to sign up. Prior to that point, Twitter has done a poor job communicating the message that, <strong>if you like reading stuff on the web, and most people do, after all; then you would almost certainly enjoy having a Twitter account</strong>.</p>

<p>That is exactly my position. I posit that the intersection of people who (a) currently like reading the internet and (b) would enjoy Twitter with a sufficiently-well-constructed following-list is one and the same.</p>

<p>If you&rsquo;re reading this, and don&rsquo;t have a Twitter account, I <em>implore</em> you to give it a try.</p>

<ol>
<li>Open an account. Using your real name or having the account be associated in any way with your real identity is strictly optional.</li>
<li>Pick some people to follow. See the end of this page for some suggestions.</li>
<li>Have a look at the timeline several times a day. It&rsquo;s not a corporate email inbox – to be doggedly read to completion, but rather, a river of interesting things for perusal and sampling at any time.</li>
</ol>


<p>With a judiciously selected follow-list, Twitter has the potential to become a fascinating window onto the world, tailored to your own interests. It is truly fantastic, and you should give it a try if you haven&rsquo;t already.</p>

<h3>Addendum: Some Follow Suggestions</h3>

<p>Here&rsquo;s a few suggestions of worthwhile accounts to follow<sup id="fnref:6"><a href="#fn:6" rel="footnote">6</a></sup> based on my own interests (the categories are overly-simplistic, of course):</p>

<ul>
<li>Canadian-focus <a href="https://twitter.com/acoyne">@acoyne</a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/MikePMoffatt">@MikePMoffatt</a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/stephenfgordon">@stephenfgordon</a></li>
<li>News <a href="https://twitter.com/guardian">@guardian</a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/BreakingNews">@BreakingNews</a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/CBCNews">@CBCNews</a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/BBCNews">@BBCNews</a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/TheTyee">@TheTyee</a></li>
<li>Economics <a href="https://twitter.com/TheEconomist">@TheEconomist</a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/TimHarford">@TimHarford</a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/Pricenomics">@Pricenomics</a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/planetmoney">@planetmoney</a></li>
<li>Finance <a href="https://twitter.com/felixsalmon">@felixsalmon</a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/dealbook">@dealbook</a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/CdnCouchPotato">@CdnCouchPotato</a></li>
<li>Tech <a href="https://twitter.com/pmarca">@pmarca</a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/BenedictEvans">@BenedictEvans</a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/monkbent">@monkbent</a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/fmanjoo">@fmanjoo</a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/gruber">@gruber</a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/troyhunt">@troyhunt</a></li>
<li>Urbanism <a href="https://twitter.com/StrongTowns">@StrongTowns</a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/neil21">@neil21</a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/modacitylife">@modacitylife</a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/copenhagenize">@copenhagenize</a></li>
<li>Miscellaneous <a href="https://twitter.com/mathbabedotorg">@mathbabedotorg</a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/TheOnion">@TheOnion</a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/StatFact">@StatFact</a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/RealTimeWWII">@RealTimeWWII</a></li>
</ul>

<div class="footnotes">
<hr/>
<ol>
<li id="fn:1">
<p>Twitter is quite possibly <em>my favourite thing</em> about our modern, connected, mobile world &ndash; and I include my iPhone in that list.<a href="#fnref:1" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
<li id="fn:2">
<p>Unlike Facebook, which I contend gets less interesting with each additional friend (beyond a minimal set of close contacts).<a href="#fnref:2" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
<li id="fn:3">
<p>What a tweet even <em>is</em> seems to cause some degree of consternation initially, with many newcomers believing that the act of tweeting is predominantly a way to share breakfast photographs, express inane self-indulgences, or bolster your public persona if you happen to be Ashton Kutcher – all things that no right-thinking individual should engage in.<a href="#fnref:3" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
<li id="fn:4">
<p>e.g. 140-char limit, <code>@</code>-replies <a href="https://support.twitter.com/articles/119138-types-of-tweets-and-where-they-appear">only appear</a> in the timelines of mutual follows.<a href="#fnref:4" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
<li id="fn:5">
<p>As I write this, in August 2014, there has been word of Twitter monkeying with what shows up in timelines; heretofore this was strictly determined by one&rsquo;s followed accounts. This is <strong>not</strong> the way to solve the utility problem, and I hope they see sense.<a href="#fnref:5" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
<li id="fn:6">
<p>Following does not imply endorsement, but it does imply <em>interest</em>.<a href="#fnref:6" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
</ol>
</div>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[A Call for Modern Banking]]></title>
    <link href="http://liggat.org/2014/04/22/a-call-for-modern-banking/"/>
    <updated>2014-04-22T06:40:07-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://liggat.org/2014/04/22/a-call-for-modern-banking</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I can scarcely walk past a bus shelter without being shown a poster by one of the big-five Canadian banks invariably touting their extended branch hours, new location(s), or magnanimous decision to remain open on Sundays. Guess what? No one under 60 cares.<!--more--> Visiting a bank branch is unnecessary for the overwhelming majority of banking interactions, and most people only do so on exceedingly rare occasions and with substantial reluctance due to the trespass upon time and the general hassle that a visit represents<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" rel="footnote">1</a></sup>.</p>

<p>What I, and undoubtedly many others, <em>would</em> like to see, however, is <strong>modern online services</strong>. I&rsquo;m actually astonished that one of these banks has not thrown a bit more investment in this direction – or if they have – it&rsquo;s not at all externally apparent. Right off the top of my head I can produce a laundry list of substantial online enhancements that I&rsquo;d like to see a bank implement &ndash; I&rsquo;d switch all my business in a heartbeat to any bank who made even a modest subset of these changes. I bet I&rsquo;m not alone.</p>

<h3>My Wish List</h3>

<ol>
<li><strong>Two Factor Authentication</strong>. My <a href="https://support.google.com/accounts/answer/180744?hl=en">email</a>, my <a href="http://blog.evernote.com/blog/2013/10/04/two-step-verification-available-to-all-users/">digital archive</a>, my <a href="https://www.dropbox.com/help/363/en">cloud storage</a>, and my <a href="https://blog.twitter.com/2013/getting-started-with-login-verification">Twitter</a> account all have two-factor authentication (<a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Two-step_verification">2FA</a>). Why doesn&rsquo;t my bank account? It&rsquo;s not like 2FA is an unfamiliar concept to either the banks or the populace &ndash; <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Chip_and_PIN">chip &amp; PIN</a> for debit and credit cards has been deployed in Canada for many years. It seriously astounds me that as I write this in 2014, this hasn&rsquo;t been rolled out on the web by any bank that I&rsquo;m aware of.</li>
<li><strong>Sensible Policies on Passwords</strong>. Canadian banks seem to have an odd philosophy on passwords. TD&rsquo;s iOS app does not appear to permit paste into password fields &ndash; needlessly hampering the usage of password managers like <a href="https://agilebits.com/onepassword/mac">1Password</a>. BMO mandates an alphanumeric password of <strong>precisely-six alphanumeric</strong> characters<sup id="fnref:2"><a href="#fn:2" rel="footnote">2</a></sup>. Why the artificial limitations? These measures are destructive, not augmentative, of online-security.</li>
<li><strong>Modern Web</strong>. The web has improved immeasurably over the past decade. With the scourge of Internet Explorer&rsquo;s worst transgressions behind us, and transformative technologies like responsive-design, web typography, CSS transforms, client-side JavaScript frameworks (i.e. <a href="http://emberjs.com/">Ember.js</a>) constantly entering the tech-zeitgeist &ndash; it&rsquo;s a golden age for the web<sup id="fnref:3"><a href="#fn:3" rel="footnote">3</a></sup>. You&rsquo;d never know it though, based on the appearance of online banking. I&rsquo;d be happy as a start with even a bit of interface-enhancing JavaScript, which is curiously absent from banking web apps &ndash; virtually unthinkable in 2014 in most other online contexts. Instead, absurdly high page latencies, an absence of responsive-design and stodgy <em>Times-New-Arial</em> typefaces<sup id="fnref:4"><a href="#fn:4" rel="footnote">4</a></sup> are the order of the day.</li>
<li><strong>Mobile apps</strong>. Curiously, most Canadian banks do have mobile apps, on iOS at least, and yet they don&rsquo;t seem to serve any real purpose beyond marketing. Utility wise, there&rsquo;s no point having a mobile app that&rsquo;s nothing but a native container for [in their case, tremendously-slow-to-render] web content. With the exception of the Tangerine<sup id="fnref:5"><a href="#fn:5" rel="footnote">5</a></sup> app&rsquo;s ability to photo-deposit cheques – a welcome, if belated arrival – none of these apps actually enable any use-case that couldn&rsquo;t be accomplished in a mobile browser. I&rsquo;d like to see authentication caching, some use of native UI components perhaps, and a robust, configurable push notification scheme for transaction/payment alerts. And, of course, their possible use as a vehicle for the aforementioned 2FA.</li>
<li><strong>Data</strong>. I want access to my data. No, not as some Quicken <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Binary_large_object">blob</a> or a poorly-formatted CSV file, but in a sane, structured format, preferably <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Json">JSON</a><sup id="fnref:6"><a href="#fn:6" rel="footnote">6</a></sup>. It remains an utter hassle to view and use historical banking data &ndash; to find a particular subset of recurring transactions for example. Better structured banking data would enable entire classes of tools, workflows, and even businesses to exist.</li>
<li><strong>API/OAuth</strong>. Relatedly, I want a programmatic method to access this data, and support for an authorization technique like OAuth to delegate <strong>revocable</strong> access to a trusted third party. This is a well-solved problem &ndash; it is a ubiquitous pattern in tech, and there is enormous demand for it to exist. Since it doesn&rsquo;t exist &ndash; horrible kludges like providing aggregation sites (e.g. <a href="https://www.mint.com/">Mint</a><sup id="fnref:7"><a href="#fn:7" rel="footnote">7</a></sup>) banking credentials are the only way to enable third-party access.</li>
</ol>


<h3>Objections</h3>

<p>I bear no illusions that a CTO or similar executive from one of these banks will even see this, much less take it seriously. Even if they did see it, I can imagine the guffaws about how unrealistic this nerd&rsquo;s demands are:</p>

<ul>
<li><em>&ldquo;We can&rsquo;t justify the cost of a massive online systems redesign!&rdquo;</em></li>
<li><em>&ldquo;Don&rsquo;t you know how complex our legacy backend is &ndash; our password policy was chosen to support that!&rdquo;</em></li>
<li><em>&ldquo;We have a myriad of customers and browsers to support &ndash; not everyone is running Safari on brand-new MacBook Pros you know!&rdquo;</em></li>
<li><em>&ldquo;The regulations we are under would never permit API access! We can&rsquo;t ever permit customer data to go to &lsquo;third parties&rsquo; &ndash; the banking regulators and the newspapers would have a field day!&rdquo;</em></li>
</ul>


<p>I&rsquo;m absolutely aware that what I&rsquo;m suggesting requires investment, that banks operate under strict regulation, that data integrity is critical in the financial system (i.e. so technological conservatism is desired). I&rsquo;m further aware that the user base is indeed large, of a wide spectrum of technical-comfort, and that the user-age-distribution is <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Skewness">negatively-skewed</a><sup id="fnref:8"><a href="#fn:8" rel="footnote">8</a></sup>.</p>

<p>So, sure – there are obstacles. But this stuff is hard to get right, not just the tech but also the product vision that goes along with it. With each passing year, the gap between online-banking and the rest of the modern web grows ever starker. I see no reason why the tech we use everyday in virtually every other aspect of life should rocket ahead in functionality, design, thoughtfulness, integration, etc &ndash; while finance/banking remains virtually the same today as in 2004.</p>

<p>If nothing else, I believe excellence in these areas will become a competitive advantage sooner than banks apparently seem to think. Does anyone really think that in ten years time, the major customer service innovation to be touted from every bus-bench will still involve the local branch in some way?</p>
<div class="footnotes">
<hr/>
<ol>
<li id="fn:1">
<p>I realize there&rsquo;s an incentive misalignment here &ndash; more branch visits implies more sales opportunities.<a href="#fnref:1" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
<li id="fn:2">
<p>Forbidding symbolic characters is a <a href="http://www.troyhunt.com/2012/09/do-you-allow-xss-in-your-passwords-you.html">misguided</a> defense against XSS or SQL-injection &ndash; passwords should be cryptographically hashed right away, anyway.<a href="#fnref:2" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
<li id="fn:3">
<p>And much software generally, <a href="http://liggat.org/2013/09/03/a-comparatively-golden-age-of-software/">as I&rsquo;ve argued</a>.<a href="#fnref:3" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
<li id="fn:4">
<p>I realize that <strong>better typography</strong> performs poorly in a DCF calculation. But then, presumably so do the potted rhododendrons festooning the lobby of every branch.<a href="#fnref:4" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
<li id="fn:5">
<p>née ING Direct.<a href="#fnref:5" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
<li id="fn:6">
<p>it&rsquo;s easy to parse and is the <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lingua_franca">lingua franca</a> of programmatic access to data over the Internet.<a href="#fnref:6" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
<li id="fn:7">
<p>However good Mint&rsquo;s security is–and I have reason to believe it is <strong>very</strong> good as I&rsquo;ve met a few of the early engineers–providing credentials to them will always be a highly inferior way to delegate access. Plus it&rsquo;s explicitly forbidden by the Terms of Service for many banks.<a href="#fnref:7" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
<li id="fn:8">
<p>I presume age and wealth correlate fairly well, which likely explains a large amount of the dogged focus on new branches and &lsquo;convenient&rsquo; hours in bank advertising.<a href="#fnref:8" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
</ol>
</div>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[On Boredom]]></title>
    <link href="http://liggat.org/2013/09/25/on-boredom/"/>
    <updated>2013-09-25T09:32:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://liggat.org/2013/09/25/on-boredom</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://teamcoco.com/video/louis-ck-springsteen-cell-phone">Another</a> of Louis C.K.&rsquo;s hilarious talk-show interview diatribes is being widely circulated on the web and Twitter right now &ndash; this time about smartphones, and why he won&rsquo;t let his children have one. It&rsquo;s well worth a watch, but his argument essentially boils down to the observation that smartphones provide a constant stream of distraction that removes the condition, boredom, that is arguably necessary for healthy self-reflection.<!--more--></p>

<p>Humour aside, I think he&rsquo;s really onto something here. Speaking personally, boredom, at least how I understood the term pre-Internet, has essentially disappeared from my life. Very few of my waking hours are spent without mental stimulation of one form or another. If I&rsquo;m waiting in a lineup, on public transport, unable to sleep, or killing time in an airport &ndash; out comes my phone, and the usual suspects <a href="http://tapbots.com/software/tweetbot/">Tweetbot</a> or <a href="http://instapaper.com">Instapaper</a> will occupy me for the duration of that transitory event. Even when I&rsquo;m cooking, cycling, exercising, or walking the dog, I&rsquo;m spared from any possible exposure to boredom through a now-years-old tendency to listen to podcasts<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" rel="footnote">1</a></sup> or audiobooks whenever my hands are occupied.</p>

<p>As a technophile and enthusiast-for-non-boredom, it&rsquo;s hard for me to know how I should feel about this state of affairs. It&rsquo;s fairly easy to reason that since happiness may only exist in a world with sadness, then perhaps excitement and boredom share a similar, inextricable, symbiosis? I certainly don&rsquo;t currently <em>feel</em> like my life: work, personal or otherwise, lacks excitement &ndash; far from it. But this is 2013 &ndash; what about 2033 when we have <em>{insert your favourite prediction about technology two decades out<sup id="fnref:2"><a href="#fn:2" rel="footnote">2</a></sup>}</em>?</p>

<p>Kids born in the recent past seem to be genuinely puzzled when they encounter a display which is not touch-sensitive, and I find it likely that this will be their response at the very notion of boredom as a concept in the years to come. I feel privileged to have grown up during that big epoch-defining<sup id="fnref:3"><a href="#fn:3" rel="footnote">3</a></sup> transition from pre-Internet to our now permanent state of connectedness. I have vivid memories of what it was like to have only four TV channels and a few toys and books as the sole available vehicles for entertainment; and still more vivid memories of the initial realizations that I now had the power to answer virtually any question I could conceive of with just a few keystrokes.</p>

<p>I don&rsquo;t think the significance of this shift has been truly internalized by many people yet. Other than Louis C.K., of course.</p>
<div class="footnotes">
<hr/>
<ol>
<li id="fn:1">
<p>I love podcasts, but my subscriptions have grown well beyond the point of my ability to actually listen to them all.<a href="#fnref:1" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
<li id="fn:2">
<p>Visible screens inscribed on contact lenses?<a href="#fnref:2" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
<li id="fn:3">
<p>I am convinced that historians will have a well-defined name for this period in decades/centuries to come.<a href="#fnref:3" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
</ol>
</div>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
