<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Breaking_bad | Liggat.org]]></title>
  <link href="http://liggat.org/blog/categories/breaking-bad/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://liggat.org/"/>
  <updated>2014-09-14T12:12:20-07:00</updated>
  <id>http://liggat.org/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Dave Liggat]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Walter White, Art Aficionado]]></title>
    <link href="http://liggat.org/2013/10/15/walter-white/"/>
    <updated>2013-10-15T10:41:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://liggat.org/2013/10/15/walter-white</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I&rsquo;ve been re-watching <em>Breaking Bad</em>, one of my favourite television dramas, ever. Yesterday, midway through an early second season episode, I noticed a connection to a much later point in the story that I haven&rsquo;t seen discussed anywhere else.</p>

<!--more-->


<p><em>Don&rsquo;t read this if you&rsquo;re keen to avoid Breaking Bad plot details.</em></p>

<h3>The Painting</h3>

<p>By the midpoint of season five<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" rel="footnote">1</a></sup>, Walter is at the height of his Heisenberg-persona hubris. He&rsquo;s built his own drug empire, defeated his enemies &ndash; notably Fring, and still gone unnoticed by law enforcement. He&rsquo;s invincible. As if to telegraph this &ndash; while Uncle Jack and his band of Nazis are struggling over the minutiae of their planned murderous rampage at three separate Albuquerque jails &ndash; Walt stares at a painting in the motel room, uninterested in the conversation around him.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/2013/painting_second.jpg" width="500" title="Painting in the Motel" ></p>

<p>He idly speculates: <em>Where do you suppose these come from? I&rsquo;ve seen this one before. I wonder &ndash; are they all in some giant warehouse someplace?</em>, and invites the ire of Uncle Jack &ndash; incredulous at his lack of focus on planning the operation.</p>

<h3>First Appearance</h3>

<p>It turns out that this same painting featured much earlier in the story<sup id="fnref:2"><a href="#fn:2" rel="footnote">2</a></sup>. A browbeaten Walt was finishing up a chemotherapy session, and spent a moment staring at a print of it on the hospital wall. The camera lingers at what is surely an instance of symbolism: the painting is of a man, rowing <em>away</em> from his family on the shore towards a waiting ship.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/2013/painting_first.jpg" width="500" title="Painting in the Hospital" ></p>

<p>Walt&rsquo;s comment is therefore made with the recognition that he&rsquo;s noticed at least two of these things in the wild. Virtually the only constant between these two moments in the <em>Breaking Bad</em> story is the notion of that warehouse somewhere, churning out an endless supply of mediocre stock art.</p>

<p>The inclusion of, and callback to, this painting is just one more in another long line of fantastic touches by the show&rsquo;s creators.</p>
<div class="footnotes">
<hr/>
<ol>
<li id="fn:1">
<p>These events occurred in the fifth season episode, <em>Gliding all Over</em>.<a href="#fnref:1" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
<li id="fn:2">
<p>This was visible in the second season episode <em>Bit by Dead Bee</em>. Walt had just completed implementing his not-altogether-plausible &lsquo;fugue state&rsquo; alibi, and was back in chemo.<a href="#fnref:2" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
</ol>
</div>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
