<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: News | Liggat.org]]></title>
  <link href="http://liggat.org/blog/categories/news/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://liggat.org/"/>
  <updated>2015-01-30T14:31:46-08:00</updated>
  <id>http://liggat.org/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Dave Liggat]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Everyone Should Use Twitter]]></title>
    <link href="http://liggat.org/2014/08/27/everyone-should-use-twitter/"/>
    <updated>2014-08-27T15:20:45-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://liggat.org/2014/08/27/everyone-should-use-twitter</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Twitter&rsquo;s role in the public sphere is a contradictory one. It is at once ubiquious – adorning all manner of billboards and signs, not to mention the lower fifth of the screen of cable news broadcasts – and yet almost entirely foreign to those who do not use it. That last clause verges on the tautological, but the emphasis is on <em>foreign</em>; I submit that Twitter is <em>bizarre</em> and outright <em>strange</em> to its non-users to a much greater extent than is true in the case of Facebook or just about any of the other prominent social web services.<!--more--></p>

<p>Although Twitter&rsquo;s ubiquity ensures that just about everyone has <em>heard</em> of it, and may even be aware that it has developed into a substantial forum for worldwide discourse, I get the sense that most people have never been shown a single, compelling reason why they might personally trouble to open an account.</p>

<p>As a devoted, adoring user of the service<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" rel="footnote">1</a></sup>, this strikes me as a mild tragedy. It is understandable why many people might feel this way; bootstrapping an account from naught to useful is not an especially easy task, and is fraught with several meaningful obstacles:</p>

<ul>
<li><strong>The Bootstrapping Problem</strong>: Twitter gets more interesting with each additional account you discover and follow<sup id="fnref:2"><a href="#fn:2" rel="footnote">2</a></sup>. However, at the dawn of an account – with zero follows – Twitter&rsquo;s &lsquo;interestingness&rsquo; is at a minimum, as low as it will ever be. This is not encouraging to a newcomer.</li>
<li><strong>Utility</strong>: As a consequence, it is not at all clear to a newcomer what possible utility they might receive from this new account. Moreover, newcomers seem to believe that the primary purpose of Twitter is in <em>tweeting</em><sup id="fnref:3"><a href="#fn:3" rel="footnote">3</a></sup>, when in actual fact, <em>reading the timeline</em> is the main reason it&rsquo;s worth having an account. To be sure, it&rsquo;s fun to participate in conversations once in a while, but one can receive an enormous amount of value from Twitter simply by following a set of interesting accounts, reading their updates, and perhaps never once sending a tweet.</li>
<li><strong>Esotericism</strong>: Twitter pioneered, or at least greatly popularized, several new dynamics such as the asymmetric follower/following relationship and <code>@</code>-mentioning. It also has its own conventions which are opaque from the outset<sup id="fnref:4"><a href="#fn:4" rel="footnote">4</a></sup>. Although all of this is well understood by regular users, I get the impression it is intimidating to start with.</li>
</ul>


<p>Twitter has visibly attempted to address these issues<sup id="fnref:5"><a href="#fn:5" rel="footnote">5</a></sup>, though not satisfactorially I would argue. The onboarding process addresses the bootstrapping problem to a degree, but that&rsquo;s only useful once a newcomer has been convinced to sign up. Prior to that point, Twitter has done a poor job communicating the message that, <strong>if you like reading stuff on the web, and most people do, after all; then you would almost certainly enjoy having a Twitter account</strong>.</p>

<p>That is exactly my position. I posit that the intersection of people who (a) currently like reading the internet and (b) would enjoy Twitter with a sufficiently-well-constructed following-list is one and the same.</p>

<p>If you&rsquo;re reading this, and don&rsquo;t have a Twitter account, I <em>implore</em> you to give it a try.</p>

<ol>
<li>Open an account. Using your real name or having the account be associated in any way with your real identity is strictly optional.</li>
<li>Pick some people to follow. See the end of this page for some suggestions.</li>
<li>Have a look at the timeline several times a day. It&rsquo;s not a corporate email inbox – to be doggedly read to completion, but rather, a river of interesting things for perusal and sampling at any time.</li>
</ol>


<p>With a judiciously selected follow-list, Twitter has the potential to become a fascinating window onto the world, tailored to your own interests. It is truly fantastic, and you should give it a try if you haven&rsquo;t already.</p>

<h3>Addendum: Some Follow Suggestions</h3>

<p>Here&rsquo;s a few suggestions of worthwhile accounts to follow<sup id="fnref:6"><a href="#fn:6" rel="footnote">6</a></sup> based on my own interests (the categories are overly-simplistic, of course):</p>

<ul>
<li>Canadian-focus <a href="https://twitter.com/acoyne">@acoyne</a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/MikePMoffatt">@MikePMoffatt</a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/stephenfgordon">@stephenfgordon</a></li>
<li>News <a href="https://twitter.com/guardian">@guardian</a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/BreakingNews">@BreakingNews</a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/CBCNews">@CBCNews</a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/BBCNews">@BBCNews</a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/TheTyee">@TheTyee</a></li>
<li>Economics <a href="https://twitter.com/TheEconomist">@TheEconomist</a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/TimHarford">@TimHarford</a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/Pricenomics">@Pricenomics</a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/planetmoney">@planetmoney</a></li>
<li>Finance <a href="https://twitter.com/felixsalmon">@felixsalmon</a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/dealbook">@dealbook</a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/CdnCouchPotato">@CdnCouchPotato</a></li>
<li>Tech <a href="https://twitter.com/pmarca">@pmarca</a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/BenedictEvans">@BenedictEvans</a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/monkbent">@monkbent</a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/fmanjoo">@fmanjoo</a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/gruber">@gruber</a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/troyhunt">@troyhunt</a></li>
<li>Urbanism <a href="https://twitter.com/StrongTowns">@StrongTowns</a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/neil21">@neil21</a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/modacitylife">@modacitylife</a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/copenhagenize">@copenhagenize</a></li>
<li>Miscellaneous <a href="https://twitter.com/mathbabedotorg">@mathbabedotorg</a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/TheOnion">@TheOnion</a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/StatFact">@StatFact</a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/RealTimeWWII">@RealTimeWWII</a></li>
</ul>

<div class="footnotes">
<hr/>
<ol>
<li id="fn:1">
<p>Twitter is quite possibly <em>my favourite thing</em> about our modern, connected, mobile world &ndash; and I include my iPhone in that list.<a href="#fnref:1" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
<li id="fn:2">
<p>Unlike Facebook, which I contend gets less interesting with each additional friend (beyond a minimal set of close contacts).<a href="#fnref:2" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
<li id="fn:3">
<p>What a tweet even <em>is</em> seems to cause some degree of consternation initially, with many newcomers believing that the act of tweeting is predominantly a way to share breakfast photographs, express inane self-indulgences, or bolster your public persona if you happen to be Ashton Kutcher – all things that no right-thinking individual should engage in.<a href="#fnref:3" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
<li id="fn:4">
<p>e.g. 140-char limit, <code>@</code>-replies <a href="https://support.twitter.com/articles/119138-types-of-tweets-and-where-they-appear">only appear</a> in the timelines of mutual follows.<a href="#fnref:4" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
<li id="fn:5">
<p>As I write this, in August 2014, there has been word of Twitter monkeying with what shows up in timelines; heretofore this was strictly determined by one&rsquo;s followed accounts. This is <strong>not</strong> the way to solve the utility problem, and I hope they see sense.<a href="#fnref:5" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
<li id="fn:6">
<p>Following does not imply endorsement, but it does imply <em>interest</em>.<a href="#fnref:6" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
</ol>
</div>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
